<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Rest Is Best: The Role of Rest and Task Interruptions on Vigilance  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How resting during vigilance tasks can actually improve focus long-term  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Rest Is Best: The Role of Rest and Task Interruptions on Vigilance</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How resting during vigilance tasks can actually improve focus long-term</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #vigilance #rest  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>W. S. Helton and P. N. Russell, &quot;Rest is best: The role of rest and task interruptions on vigilance,&quot; Cognition, vol. 134, pp. 165–173, Jan. 2015, doi: 10.1016/j.cognition.2014.10.001.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Based on the results, taking rest is best for maintaining vigilance. A different perspective can proffer an explanation for this: </p>
<p>Differing tasks which interrupt one during a vigilance task may both utilize distinctly unique resources and require different amounts of resources. The tasks may have elicited different levels of cognitive load.</p>
<p>There exist on-going debate about the origins of vigilance decrement &#91;1&#93;. The best known is based on resource theory. However critics think it is a circular mode of reasoning &#91;2&#93;.</p>
<p>Current findings suggest that vigilance decrement comes from repeated use of executive resources. There may be domain specific interference when the primary task and activities during a break make use of the same resources.</p>
<p>The findings by Ariga do not support the idea that vigilance decrement is due to task under-load. &#91;3&#93; Knowing why resting can assist with refocusing is difficult. Perhaps, rest allowed participants to engage in day dreaming which eliminated task monotony. </p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Rest Is Best: The Role of Rest and Task Interruptions on Vigilance</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best">https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; W. S. Helton and J. S. Warm, “Signal salience and the mindlessness theory of vigilance,” Acta Psychol. &#40;Amst.&#41;, vol. 129, no. 1, pp. 18–25, 2008.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; D. Navon, “Resources—A theoretical soup stone?” Psychol. Rev., vol. 91, no. 2, p. 216, 1984.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; P. A. Hancock, “In search of vigilance: The problem of iatrogenically created psychological phenomena.” Am. Psychol., vol. 68, no. 2, p. 97, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>