<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Loose hypothesis on worsening of cytokine regulation via ASD and COVID19  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 10 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Loose hypothesis on worsening of cytokine regulation via ASD and COVID19</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #asd #autism ##hypothesis #health #mentalhealth #cytokine ##pandemic #covid19 #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Be careful about conflating correlation with causation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have been closely examining the Hypothalamus Pituitary &#40;HPA&#41; axis and have seen how cytokines directly interact with it. &#91;1&#93; Therefore, since ASD has been correlated with cytokine dysregulation &#91;2&#93;, it can be reasonable to suspect that as coronavirae can also impact cytokine regulation &#91;3&#93;, ASD is a risk factor for COVID19 causing direct problems with the HPA axis leading to multiple downstream issues.</p>
<p>ASD has been correlated with abnormal immune function. This includes:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Cytokine dysregulation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Inflammation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Presence of autoantibodies</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Studies show the presence of anti-brain immunoglobulins in ASD patients. &#91;4&#93; ASD status could also be directly correlated with patients’ cytokine and chemokine levels which cause organ inflammation &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>There is a second phase resulting in a cytokine storm which particularly affects respiratory epithelium &#91;5&#93;. The storm activates cytokines IL-1-beta, IL-6 and TNFalfa. These activations aggravate respiratory symptoms. These cytokines cause damage to pulmonary microvasculature. It simultaneously affects apoptosis and chemotaxis resulting in decreases of epithelial barriers and alveolar edema <em>Back up references about cytokines</em></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19">https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19</a>. July 10 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; M. Marmot and R. Wilkinson, Social Determinants of Health, 2nd ed. Oxford University Press, 2006.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; A. M. Depino, “Peripheral and central inflammation in autism spectrum disorders,” Mol. Cell. Neurosci., vol. 53, pp. 69–76, 2013.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; S. N. J. Korsman, G. U. van Zyl, L. Nutt, M. I. Andersson, and W. Preiser, “Human coronaviruses,” in Virology, Elsevier, 2012, pp. 94–95.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; A. Meltzer and J. Van de Water, “The role of the immune system in autism spectrum disorder,” Neuropsychopharmacology, vol. 42, no. 1, pp. 284–298, 2017.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; Q. Ye, B. Wang, and J. Mao, “Cytokine storm in COVID-19 and treatment,” J. Infect., 2020.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>