<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  A Systematic Review of Publications Assessing Reliability and Validity of the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System &#40;BRFSS&#41;  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06072021202628-brfss-systematic-review/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06072021202628-brfss-systematic-review/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A systematic review to determine the reliability and validity of the BRFSS  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>A Systematic Review of Publications Assessing Reliability and Validity of the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System &#40;BRFSS&#41;</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> June 7 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A systematic review to determine the reliability and validity of the BRFSS</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #brfss #survey #reliability #validity #reports #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>C. Pierannunzi, S. S. Hu, and L. Balluz, &quot;A systematic review of publications assessing reliability and validity of the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System &#40;BRFSS&#41;, 2004–2011,&quot; BMC Med Res Methodol, vol. 13, no. 1, p. 49, Dec. 2013, doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-13-49.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>How Reliability and Validity Were Measured</li><li>Conclusions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Reduction of non-response bias through the introduction of new weighting techniques. &#91;1&#93; <em>QUESTION: What is non-response bias and how do you adjust for that?</em></p>
<h3 id="how_reliability_and_validity_were_measured">How Reliability and Validity Were Measured</h3>
<p>High reliable papers included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Conducted reliability tests using repeated test/retest measures</p>
</li>
<li><p>Used multiple samples/populations</p>
</li>
<li><p>Used multiple time periods.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ran statistical tests</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>How authors achieved higher validity by:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Comparing BRFSS to physical measures.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<p>Self-report on chronic conditions between BRFSS and surveys are highly reliable.</p>
<p>As time between conducting the same survey lapses, reliability for some questions decrease when re-asked. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>Sometimes, self-reports from the BRFSS were very reliable but prevalence differed. <em>QUESTION: What does it mean when self-reports are highly reliable and prevalence rates still differ? Seems really strange and I am not sure why this would happen...</em></p>
<p>Similarities between BRFSS and other surveys using self-reports persisted across different modes of reporting like phone calls or in-person interviews. Researchers observed BRFSS reliability and validity for some cohorts but not for others. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>All surveys consistently showed the proportion of respondents indicating general health to be &quot;excellent&quot; was declining. <em>RESEARCH OPPORTUNITY</em></p>
<p>BRFSS physical activity measures and responses were compared sometimes to physical device measures.Prevalence variation estimates found occasionally; trends similar when comparing survey results over time. <em>QUESTION: Interesting how with devices prevalences did vary but trends were found to be similar across demographics. I wonder what reports did that? I&#39;ll stick a pin in this for now.</em></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>A Systematic Review of Publications Assessing Reliability and Validity of the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System &#40;BRFSS&#41;</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/06072021202628-brfss-systematic-review">https://jacobzelko.com/06072021202628-brfss-systematic-review</a>. June 7 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; D. G. Altman and J. M. Bland, “Diagnostic tests. 1: Sensitivity and specificity.” BMJ, vol. 308, no. 6943, p. 1552, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; M. M. Yore et al., “Reliability and validity of the instrument used in BRFSS to assess physical activity.” Med. Sci. Sports Exerc., vol. 39, no. 8, pp. 1267–1274, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; L. A. Mucci, P. A. Wood, B. Cohen, K. M. Clements, P. Brawarsky, and D. R. Brooks, “Validity of self-reported health plan information in a population-based health survey,” J. Public Health Manag. Pract., vol. 12, no. 6, pp. 570–577, 2006.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Emerging insights into income and poverty during the COVID-19 pandemic  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 28 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Emerging insights into income and poverty during the COVID-19 pandemic</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #pandemic #covid #economics #poverty #population #survey  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. Han, B. Meyer, and J. Sullivan, &quot;Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic,&quot; National Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, MA, w27729, Aug. 2020. doi: 10.3386/w27729.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>General Insights</li><li>Methods of Research</li><li>Key Conclusions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="general_insights">General Insights</h3>
<p>This study provides a template for understanding large economic shocks as they happen to counter the problem of data availability during major economic shocks. The start of the pandemic saw an unprecedented decline in economic activity in the US. The largest single month decline in US unemployment was 14 percent in April 2020.</p>
<p>The federal government&#39;s response totalled to nearly three trillion dollars spent to counter pandemic effects. Their response comprised of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Economic Impact Payments &#40;tax rebates&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Small business loans</p>
</li>
<li><p>Massive increase in unemployment insurance as part of the CARES Act</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="methods_of_research">Methods of Research</h3>
<p>Basic Monthly Current Population Survey &#40;Monthly CPS&#41;, was used due to its quick release to understand the impact of macroeconomic conditions and government policies on US families&#39; incomes.</p>
<p>Family income from respondents in their first or fifth month in the survey were observed for a monthly sample ranging from 8,999 households and 20,822 individuals in February 2020 to 6,149 households and 14,383 individuals in April 2020.  Monthly CPS data from IPUMS-CPS &#91;1&#93; Generally, 90&#37; of earnings are reported in CPS, as opposed to ~60&#37; of unemployment insurance. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<h3 id="key_conclusions">Key Conclusions</h3>
<p>Without US government intervention, poverty would have risen by 2.7 percentage points between January and June.</p>
<p>The COVID Impact survey &#91;3&#93; finds an increase in food insecurity when compared to a different earlier survey while the Census Bureau&#39;s Household Pulse survey &#91;4&#93; finds high rates of inability to pay rent.  These sources suggest increased hardship after the pandemic. The increase in deprivation is not due to the overall income loss, but rather due to other disruptions of the pandemic, including possibly the unevenness of the income flows.</p>
<p>Disruptions such as:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Closures of schools</p>
</li>
<li><p>Stores</p>
</li>
<li><p>Churches and other facilities</p>
</li>
<li><p>The uncertainty about future income streams</p>
</li>
<li><p>Concerns about the health of family and friends</p>
</li>
<li><p>Other disruptions</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic">https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic</a>. December 28 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Flood, M. King, R. Rodgers, S. Ruggles, and J. Warren, “Integrated public use microdata series, current population survey: Version 7.0 &#91;dataset&#93;. Minneapolis, MN: Integrated public use microdata; 2020.”</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; B. D. Meyer, W. K. Mok, and J. X. Sullivan, “Household surveys in crisis,” J. Econ. Perspect., vol. 29, no. 4, pp. 199–226, 2015.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; L. Bauer, “The COVID-19 Crisis Has Already Left Too Many Children Hungry in America,” 06-May-2020. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www.hamiltonproject.org/blog/the<em>covid</em>19<em>crisis</em>has<em>already</em>left<em>too</em>many<em>children</em>hungry<em>in</em>america. &#91;Accessed: 08-Nov-2020&#93;.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; J. Fields et al., “Design and Operation of the 2020 Household Pulse Survey, 2020,” U.S. Census Bureau, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>