<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Direct Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Direct Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #direct #self #harm ##mentalhealth #illness #mental #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Direct self-harm is defined as the deliberate, direct destruction or alteration of body tissue without conscious suicidal intent, but resulting in injury severe enough for tissue damage to occur &#91;1&#93;. </p>
<p>Examples are of Direct Self Harm are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cutting, burning, scratching, and hitting of oneself &#91;2&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Skin bleaching &#91;3&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hair-pulling &#91;4&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ingesting hazardous chemicals &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The term &quot;direct self-harm&quot; is often used interchangeably with the terms self-injury &#91;6&#93;, self-mutilation &#91;7&#93;, and self-wounding &#91;8&#93;. Despite the exact wording, the distinction of direct self-harm is that it is non-suicidal but does cause direct injury to the body.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Direct Self-Harm</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm">https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; A. R. Favazza, “The coming of age of self-mutilation,” J. Nerv. Ment. Dis., vol. 186, no. 5, pp. 259–268, 1998.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; B. Møhl, P. La Cour, and A. Skandsen, “Non-suicidal self-injury and indirect self-harm among Danish high school students,” Scand. J. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry Psychol., vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 11–18, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; C. A. Charles, “Skin bleaching, self-hate, and black identity in Jamaica,” J. Black Stud., vol. 33, no. 6, pp. 711–728, 2003.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; B. A. Iwata, M. F. Dorsey, K. J. Slifer, K. E. Bauman, and G. S. Richman, “Toward a functional analysis of self-injury,” J. Appl. Behav. Anal., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 197–209, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; K. L. Gratz, “Measurement of deliberate self-harm: Preliminary data on the Deliberate Self-Harm Inventory,” J. Psychopathol. Behav. Assess., vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 253–263, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; E. D. Klonsky, “The functions of deliberate self-injury: A review of the evidence,” Clin. Psychol. Rev., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 226–239, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; A. R. Favazza and R. J. Rosenthal, “Diagnostic issues in self-mutilation,” Psychiatr. Serv., vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 134–140, 1993.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; D. Tantam and J. Whittaker, “Personality disorder and self-wounding,” Br. J. Psychiatry, vol. 161, no. 4, pp. 451–464, 1992.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>