<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Are Computable Phenotypes?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview into what computable phenotypes are and how they are used.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Are Computable Phenotypes?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 7 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview into what computable phenotypes are and how they are used.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #ehr #electronic #health #records #computable #phenotypes #codes #icd-9 #icd-10 #snomed-ct #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Operational Definitions</li><li>Computable Phenotypes Definitions<ol><li>Creating Computable Phenotypes</li><li>Characteristics of a Good Phenotype Definitions</li><li>Determining the Validity of a Phenotype Definition</li></ol></li><li>Available Phenotype Definitions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="operational_definitions">Operational Definitions</h3>
<p><strong>Phenotype:</strong> a measurable biological, behavioral, or cognitive marker found more often in specific individuals than the general population; the appearance it presents to observers.&#91;1&#93;</p>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/./08122022205622-assessing-phenotype-fairness"><strong>Phenotyping:</strong></a> Identifying a set of patients with a particular disease </p>
<p><strong>Computable phenotype:</strong> a clinical element that can derived from queries to an EHR or ancillary data sources &#40;such as claims data, or disease registries&#41; using a defined set of data elements and logical expressions.  It does not require chart review or interpretation by a clinician. </p>
<p><strong>Data element:</strong> the unit of data being queried, exchanged, or analyzed. It includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Descriptive name for the concept</p>
</li>
<li><p>A specified value set</p>
</li>
<li><p>Additional metadata</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Value set:</strong> the set of possible information associated with a particular data element. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p><strong>Metadata:</strong> descriptive data about objects, including data objects; data about data.</p>
<h3 id="computable_phenotypes_definitions">Computable Phenotypes Definitions</h3>
<p><strong>Computable phenotype definitions:</strong> classifying individuals with a given characteristic of interest from EHRs. Done by using data routinely collected in EHRs or ancillary data sources &#40;such as claims data, or disease registries&#41;.</p>
<p>Computable phenotype definitions enable reproducible queries of EHRs. They are made of data elements and boolean operators which are executed by a computer. Furthermore, they rely on value sets derived from standardized coding systems.</p>
<p>These definitions help identify people with particular conditions across healthcare organizations by using common definitions. Standard phenotype definitions can enable direct identification of cohorts. This allows decision-makers to specifically target screening tests and interventions to such cohorts.</p>
<h4 id="creating_computable_phenotypes">Creating Computable Phenotypes</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Define how a concept should be studied given available data.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Identify which diagnoses, treatments, and patient characteristics suggest a condition of interest.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Specify clinical condition being searched for and how that would be represented in various EHRs.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="characteristics_of_a_good_phenotype_definitions">Characteristics of a Good Phenotype Definitions</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Does not conflict with a previously pre-defined phenotype definitions</p>
</li>
<li><p>Details of a definition need be communicated.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It should enable reproducible queries in other contexts.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><p>They must always yield similar results given same data; be reliable.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Assess implementation for a given setting</p>
</li>
<li><p>Phenotype definition must be compared using available clinical gold standard.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="determining_the_validity_of_a_phenotype_definition">Determining the Validity of a Phenotype Definition</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Ability to correctly identify which individuals exhibit the phenotype.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="available_phenotype_definitions">Available Phenotype Definitions</h3>
<p>This paper contains a plethora of resources regarding phenotype definitions:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>R. Richesson and M. Smerek, &quot;Electronic health records-based phenotyping,&quot; Rethinking clinical trials: A living textbook of pragmatic clinical trials, vol. 2016, 2014.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Are Computable Phenotypes?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes">https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes</a>. January 7 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; R. Richesson and M. Smerek, “Electronic health records-based phenotyping,” Rethink. Clin. Trials Living Textb. Pragmatic Clin. Trials, vol. 2016, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; “NIH Common Data Elements &#40;CDE&#41; Repository.” https://cde.nlm.nih.gov/home &#40;accessed Dec. 30, 2020&#41;.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Why everyone should care about &#39;Computable Phenotypes&#39;  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12292020005502-care-computable-phenotypes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12292020005502-care-computable-phenotypes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A brief summary on why this paper was not very useful in discussing computable phenotypes.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Why everyone should care about &#39;Computable Phenotypes&#39;</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 28 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A brief summary on why this paper was not very useful in discussing computable phenotypes.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #computable #phenotypes #sepsis #lung #informatics  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>R. C. Tasker, &quot;Why everyone should care about ‘Computable Phenotypes,’&quot; Pediatr Crit Care Med, vol. 18, no. 5, pp. 489–490, May 2017, doi: 10.1097/PCC.0000000000001115.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>I do not believe the author is very familiar with the notion of mutltimodal analysis or standard data fusion methodologies. This was such a strange article that was more excitement and jubilation over the phenomenon of the possibility of computable phenotypes that I think the author was distracted from the message they were trying to convey. Though, they did talk about some applications regarding lung injury and sepsis, there was nothing really to suggest novelty in their assessment.</p>
<p>I reviewed this author&#39;s work and it appears the author has no formal training in informatics or analytics. So, I do not fault them for this article - however, to me, it read like something out of MIT Technology Review or a Science &amp; Technology Magazine. Not a professional scientific publication.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Why everyone should care about &#39;Computable Phenotypes&#39;</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12292020005502-care-computable-phenotypes">https://jacobzelko.com/12292020005502-care-computable-phenotypes</a>. December 28 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>