<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Lord of the Flies  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/04112022004224-lord-of-flies/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/04112022004224-lord-of-flies/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A review of the book as well as thoughts on why I did not enjoy it  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Lord of the Flies</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> April 10 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A review of the book as well as thoughts on why I did not enjoy it</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary ##book #survival #social #critique #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>W. Golding, Lord of the flies: Casebook edition. Penguin, 1987.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>I did not enjoy this book much at all. When I had finished reading it, I was left thinking to myself, &quot;that was it? This is the book so many put on a pedestal?&quot; I very much expected more for a supposed critique on the banality of man. Instead, it read a very contrived scenario that just did not feel much like life. To explain my thoughts, here are some of my findings about the book after researching the author:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>It has been well documented that the author used his students in experiments to test human behavior.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>These experiments were very contrived and did were very haphazardly done &#91;1&#93;</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><p>This book was written as a parody of a different book called Coral Island where kids were lost on an island and made a utopia.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The author wrote this as if to say this is what really happens with kids on an island.&#91;1&#93;</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><p>The book is highly idiosyncratic to British life and schooling.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Just these three points made me think the book was awful. As the book was written to talk about how children, left to their own devices, would create society and destroy it,it is oddly moralistic. You are put in a position to watch the unfurling of this horrific story take place from an objective standpoint. But based on point one, you are not all that objective.</p>
<p>Point two I feel is not talked about a lot but should be more. If this book is just parody then why is it treated as novel and even realistic at all? Coral Island was contrived just as Lord of the Flies is now,just in the opposite direction. Whether man falls to utopia or dystopia is not a binary choice but a sliding scale of morality That is very dependent on many factors.</p>
<p>Also it should not be forgotten that this book is a critique on British schooling as well. That context alone should remind that this book does not parody much of life at all but a very small cross section of it. How much can be taken from British life to other modes of living is most likely minimal.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Lord of the Flies</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/04112022004224-lord-of-flies">https://jacobzelko.com/04112022004224-lord-of-flies</a>. April 10 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. Carey, William golding: The man who wrote lord of the flies. Faber &amp; Faber, 2012.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> June 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #spacing #effect #critique #education #system #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>F. N. Dempster, &quot;A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research,&quot; American Psychologist, p. 8, 1988.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</li><li>Miscellaneous Concepts</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="issues_regarding_the_adoption_of_the_spacing_effect_into_classroom_settings">Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been studied in recent years</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is still relatively new</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect does not have any thing to do with current issues educators face.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has yet to be shown well in school activities.</p>
</li>
<li><p>There are gaps in literature about the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>School-based studies do not show the spacing effect.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been well demonstrated in a classroom setting</p>
</li>
<li><p>Not enough is known about practical class implementation to warrant application of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is not well comprehended</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the most concerning issues concerning usage of the spacing effect:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Ahistorical character of research on the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>Some failures to obtain the effect with school-like activities</p>
</li>
<li><p>Paucity of impressive classroom demonstrations of the phenomenon</p>
</li>
<li><p>Limited knowledge of classroom practice</p>
</li>
<li><p>Incomplete understanding of the psychological bases of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Probably the most legitimate barrier to utilization of the spacing effect in educational settings is the scarcity of in class demonstrations of its usage.</strong></p>
<p>However, these four issues are not considered as such strong impediments to the implementation of the spacing effect in classroom settings:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Is not new and has been studied</p>
</li>
<li><p>Continues to receive recent documentation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Can assist in addressing educational issues</p>
</li>
<li><p>Is demonstrated to lend itself well to school-like activities</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="miscellaneous_concepts">Miscellaneous Concepts</h3>
<p><strong>Lag effects</strong> are believed to occur when performance on a memory task improves as the number of intervening items between successive presentations increases.</p>
<p><strong>Jost&#39;s Law:</strong> If two memories are equal in how well they were learned but at differing times, the older memory will gain more out of a review than the new one. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique">https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique</a>. June 8 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. A. McGeoch, “The psychology of human learning.” 1942.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>