<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Developing a Robust Computable Phenotype Definition Workflow to Describe Health and Disease in Observational Health Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01102023212115-computable-phenotypes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01102023212115-computable-phenotypes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Considerations and discussion on a workflow for developing computable phenotype definitions to define disease  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Developing a Robust Computable Phenotype Definition Workflow to Describe Health and Disease in Observational Health Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> April 15 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Considerations and discussion on a workflow for developing computable phenotype definitions to define disease</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #computable #phenotype #observational #health #blog #equity #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. S. Zelko et al., “Developing a Robust Computable Phenotype Definition Workflow to Describe Health and Disease in Observational Health Research.” arXiv, Mar. 30, 2023. doi: 10.48550/arXiv.2304.06504.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Background</li><li>What&#39;s the Purpose about This Paper?</li><li>What&#39;s the Process?</li><li>What Are the Trade-offs in Developing a Definition?</li><li>Wrap-Up</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>This small blog post gives a very high level overview of a paper I authored on developing phenotype definitions which are computable and robust to a disease being examined.  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06504">This paper is vailable on arXiv under a CC BY-SA 4.0 license</a>.  Please <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/resources/">reach out to me</a> if you have any issues accessing this paper and I will send you a PDF&#33;</p>
<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>While working on some of my notes one day, I realized I had the beginnings of a paper&#33; In particular, I was working on a note about <a href="https://jacobzelko.com//01072021074632-computable-phenotypes">computable phenotypes</a> and thinking about <a href="https://jacobzelko.com//01022021031334-all-payer-claims">All Payer Claims Databases</a>. Additionally, I am in the course of a current endeavor built on a study I conducted last year called, <a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7779877"><em>A Pilot Characterization Study Assessing Health Equity in Mental Healthcare Delivery within the State of Georgia</em></a> which has made me think strongly about the whole concept of developing definitions of disease.</p>
<p>It just so happened while I was thinking about these ideas, my Georgia Tech Research Institute colleague, Dr. Shenita Freeman, let me know about an upcoming IEEE conference, the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230325190023/http://2023.cbms-conference.org/"><em>2023 IEEE Computer Based Medical Systems conference</em></a>. We both took a look at the opportunity and saw that a paper about computable phenotypes as well as the overall notion of phenotype definitions was a good idea for the conference. I reached out to some collaborators and we were off on writing this paper&#33;</p>
<h3 id="whats_the_purpose_about_this_paper">What&#39;s the Purpose about This Paper?</h3>
<p>What if I told you, how we, as researchers, speak about disease is, wrong – or at least, not quite accurate? For example, if I tell you, &quot;I research diabetes&#33;&quot;, well that is great and a noble cause but that doesn&#39;t help with telling people what it is that you are <em>actually</em> doing. As any diabetic knows, there is a huge difference between Type I Diabetes and Type II Diabetes and that doesn&#39;t consider other species of diabetes such as gestational diabetes, etc. So, it seems to me, that we need some sort of rigorous way to talk about disease, right?</p>
<p>Yes&#33; Many researchers over the years have been defining what are called <a href="https://jacobzelko.com//01072021074632-computable-phenotypes">&quot;phenotypes&quot;</a> which can be things like disease diagnoses &#40;such as Type II Diabetes&#41; and lab measurements &#40;like blood glucose, HbA1C, etc.&#41;. Then, we can build upon these phenotypes into what is called a &quot;phenotype definition&quot;. Simply put, these are a set of instructions that tells us <em>how</em> we are observing these phenotypes. Going back to our rather vague diabetes researcher, they tell us that they are actually investigating Type II Diabetes in geriatric populations within patient data they have access to. Now that is a lot more useful&#33;  A possible phenotype definition for what our researcher friend is doing is: &quot;Patients who are 65 or older with a diagnosis of or related to Type II Diabetes.&quot;</p>
<p>Our researcher is in much better shape on explaining what they have done.  So good that they are on their way to a research conference to present on findings from this definition&#33; Their fellow researchers, as well as some clinicians, at the conference love what they are doing and want to know how they can reproduce this definition with their own patient datasets. And, our researcher friend has documented the process... Right?</p>
<p>Definitely&#33; They have prepared it in the form of a computable phenotype definition&#33; They took the diabetes phenotype definition, looked up medical diagnosis codes, and reviewed patient data that is generally to see what could actually be computed on their patient data. Our researcher chose to implement their computable phenotype definition within a query language like SQL but having the computable phenotype definition on hand, other researchers could either adapt the SQL or re-implement it in another approach they prefer.</p>
<p>And just like that, our researcher now has a much clearer, meaningful, and impactful answer to the question, &quot;What disease are you studying?&quot;</p>
<h3 id="whats_the_process">What&#39;s the Process?</h3>
<p><img src="https://jacobzelko.com/assets/03302023175728-phenotype-workflow-diagram.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>We spent a lot of time thinking through each step a researcher could potentially take on developing a phenotype definition and this diagram summarized our thinking of the entire process. Additionally, to summarize these steps, we created a checklist that could be followed here for developing a phenotype definition: </p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Intent</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Decide on a motivation to guide phenotype definition construction</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Literature Review</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Identify phenotypes</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Review or validate selected phenotypes</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Identify Phenotypes</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Specify phenotypes</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Add constraints</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Translate needs to phenotype definition</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Define disqualifiers and/or strengtheners</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Combine relevant phenotypes with a logic description</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Develop Computable Phenotype</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Review what concepts are consistently present in data</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Implement phenotype definition in a computable form</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Execute Definition</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Execute computable phenotype definition on database</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Assess &amp; Revise</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Consider assumptions within phenotype definition</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Revise phenotype definition as needed</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Do, Monitor, &amp; Evaluate</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Answer research question or achieve goal.</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#91; &#93; Repeat phenotype definition checklist as appropriate</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To learn more about this checklist, definitely read the second part of the paper&#33; </p>
<h3 id="what_are_the_trade-offs_in_developing_a_definition">What Are the Trade-offs in Developing a Definition?</h3>
<p>The paper further goes into details about some of the trade-offs within developing a phenotype definition.  You may be surprised to hear that there would have to be trade-offs in defining a disease for a population. However, in practice, some counter-intuitive observations emerge:</p>
<p>The first is what I refer to as the paradox of phenotype definitions. A very well-intentioned but somewhat naive approach when thinking about researching specific subpopulations is to define your phenotype definition as specifically as possible. For example, a possible phenotype definition could be &quot;White male patients with depression between the ages of 40 - 49 living within rural Tennessee counties&quot;. However, with each <a href="https://jacobzelko.com//11042022134535-structural-intersectionality">intersecting feature &#40;&quot;axis&quot;&#41; imposed on a population</a>, the resulting number of patients captured is smaller and smaller. Going back to our example, if you have 1000 males in Tennessee, 100 people between the ages of 40-49, and only 50 people within rural parts of the state, then at best, you&#39;ll only end up with 50 people matching your phenotype definition. The question becomes less of how to make a precise definition and more of balancing the trade-off between if a phenotype definition actually represents the population one is investigating and how useful a phenotype definition in practice will be. </p>
<p>The second, is how a phenotype definition can differ from a computable phenotype definition. What I mean by that is a team of clinicians who may want to study a specific disease make a very clinically accurate picture of a patient population in a phenotype definition. However, when an informaticist looks at the definition and tries to implement it into a computable phenotype definition, there may be some aspects of the original phenotype definition that do not map well to a software implementation in practice. For more details, I suggest strongly to look at the first part of this paper as this topic is quite extensive.</p>
<p>Finally, and by no means exhaustive to our list of trade-offs, is the idea of, &quot;Is the data we want to analyze even computable?&quot; An excellent example that had to be cut from the paper for space reasons is the emergence of COVID19. When COVID19 emerged as a threat to humanity, everyone wanted to analyze it and understand it as rapidly as possible. However, the problem was, was that there was a long &#40;in the context of the pandemic&#41; period in which collecting data on COVID19 diagnosis and symptom-type data was not possible. Hospitals would code deaths as related to symptoms exacerbated by COVID19 &#40;myocardial infarction, pneumonia, etc.&#41;, diagnoses related to presented symptoms &#40;bronchitis, stroke, etc.&#41; but never to a formal COVID19 diagnosis. This has since been remedied by emergency measures taken by <a href="https://icd.who.int/en">ICD</a> for medical coding but now, much of the earlier pandemic data, if someone wanted to study COVID19 with any kind of phenotype definition for COVID19, is not accurate. This presents a disconnect between a known problem &#40;COVID19&#41; to be studied and what could actually be studied &#40;the data that is actually available for computation&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="wrap-up">Wrap-Up</h3>
<p>In summary, I sincerely believe that this paper is quite useful in many different areas&#33; Especially, this paper can now serve as a sort of touchstone for interdisciplinary teams when discussing these concepts. </p>
<p>Please let me know if you have any questions and comments or if you notice any egregious errors within the paper in the comments&#33;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Developing a Robust Computable Phenotype Definition Workflow to Describe Health and Disease in Observational Health Research</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01102023212115-computable-phenotypes">https://jacobzelko.com/01102023212115-computable-phenotypes</a>. April 15 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  JuliaCon proposal for giving a full length talk on using Julia in an international healthcare study  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 15 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> JuliaCon proposal for giving a full length talk on using Julia in an international healthcare study</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #archive #juliacon #health #equity #mental #juliahealth</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Original Submission<ol><li>Abstract</li><li>Proposal</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="original_submission">Original Submission</h3>
<h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4>
<p>This talk explores the use of Julia in a novel observational health research study that explores health equity and mental health in ~100 million patients in an international collaborative effort across more than 4 countries. Contributions and efforts within the JuliaHealth and adjacent communities have made working with this data possible. The approaches and results shared will be valuable for potential researchers and will open new frontiers for high performance computing and health analytics.</p>
<h4 id="proposal">Proposal</h4>
<p>Conducting health research studies at scale to understand the health of specific communities and subpopulations has long been a struggle. This has been due to a variety of issues, such as a lack of international standards in the structure of electronic health records, patient claims data, and diagnoses. Moreover, the investigation of questions related to the topic of health equity &#40;that is, the skewed distribution of health resources or services to various subpopulations seeking healthcare&#41; has been largely stalled due to these problems.</p>
<p>In a previous talk I gave, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v&#61;5XsWUZX6lFM">Using Julia for Observational Health Research</a>, I presented early work on the success of using Julia within the space of observational health research in utilizing the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/02082021170353-cdm-standardized-tables/">OMOP Common Data Model</a>. In that previous work, I conducted a pilot study to characterize prevalence rates in mental health care for <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/#workable_definitions_of_intersectionality">intersectional subpopulations</a> suffering from bipolar disorder, depression, and/or suicidality. This work utilized novel tooling and approaches created within Julia to successfully analyze data from ~2.5 million Medicaid subscribers within the U.S. state of Georgia. This work earned the <a href="https://www.ohdsi.org/2022-collaborator-showcase">highest awards at the top observational health research venue</a>, drove another successful grant proposal, and resulted in <a href="https://www.nahdo.org/conference/2022/agenda">multiple invited talks</a>. Buoyed by the interest and success of this pilot work, my team and I have moved this project into the next phase: the examination of more than 100 million patients from more than 4 countries across the globe.</p>
<p>In this talk, I will present advances within the JuliaHealth community and the broader Julia ecosystem that have made possible such large scale and federated analyses. In particular, novel JuliaHealth tools such as <a href="https://juliahealth.org/OMOPCDMCohortCreator.jl/">OMOPCDMCohortCreator.jl</a> will be highlighted to show how to analyze &quot;big&quot; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/10282021140730-real-world-evidence/#united_states_food_and_drug_administration_definitions">real world data</a>, how using Julia can be of huge benefit within this space, and how Julia community members could start using these tools for their own research. As this study now takes place across multiple countries, time will also be spent discussing how Julia lends itself very well to robust analyses using literate programming tools such as <a href="https://quarto.org">Quarto</a> or <a href="https://github.com/JunoLab/Weave.jl">Weave.jl</a> and versioning processes through <a href="https://github.com/JuliaDynamics/DrWatson.jl">DrWatson.jl</a> or <a href="https://github.com/iterative/dvc">Data Version Control</a>, which can be utilized to handle each country&#39;s specific needs. Additionally, I will spend some time discussing issues encountered &#40;both technical and anthropological&#41;, ways that the Julia ecosystem could potentially grow to support future work in this research domain, and opportunities for Julia users to get involved. Finally, I will share my personal thoughts on what open questions there are to be addressed in observational health research and how Julia can be a tool to address public health questions and provide insight into questions of health disparities.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this talk will highlight the real world use of Julia in large-scale health research studies built on real world data. Moreover, it will show the potential of the various ecosystems within Julia to analyze and tackle complex questions within health equity. Through this talk, I invite future Julia users and researchers to join me in pursuing the potential of Julia within the space of observational health research.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal">https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal</a>. January 15 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 4 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary #intersectionality #theory #health #research #equity  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Workable Definitions of Intersectionality</li><li>Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>Intersectionality and intersectionality theory is a really cool emerging area of research within health research. Wanted to create this note to summarize intersectionality ideas.</p>
<h3 id="workable_definitions_of_intersectionality">Workable Definitions of Intersectionality</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Intersectionality</strong> - more describes an approach to disentangle and understand the overlapping systems of oppression that contribute to inequality &#40;Collins 2000; Crenshaw 1991&#41;.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Embedded into this notion are several concepts such as social context and complexity &#40;Collins and Bilge 2020&#41;</p>
<h3 id="why_are_intersectional_approaches_needed">Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality">Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</a> - An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory">https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory</a>. November 4 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 4 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibiliography #intersectionality #sociology #medical #equity #disparity #research  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. Homan, T. H. Brown, and B. King, &quot;Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research,&quot; J Health Soc Behav, vol. 62, no. 3, pp. 350–370, Sep. 2021, doi: 10.1177/00221465211032947.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Reading Motivation</li><li>What Is Intersectionality?</li><li>Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</li><li>How Is Health Impacted by Intersectionality?</li><li>How Can Intersectionality Help Address Health Inequity?</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="reading_motivation">Reading Motivation</h3>
<p>I was suggested this paper by Sarah Gasman of Boston Medical Center. She suggested it as has it holds great relevance to some of my research on health disparities. I must say, this paper was revelatory and plan a future discussion with the study authors due to how incredible it was to my mind.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_intersectionality">What Is Intersectionality?</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory">What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</a> - An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and intersectionality theory as an area of health and health disparities research.</p>
<h3 id="why_are_intersectional_approaches_needed">Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</h3>
<p>Prior literature has shown multiple examples where an understanding of intersectionality is useful in a health context: 	- Racism, sexism, and classism are interlocking, mutually constituted, and reinforcing &#40;Collins 2000; Crenshaw 1991; Dill and Zambrana 2009&#41; 	- Effects of racial, gender, and socioeconomic stratification are nonadditive &#40;meaning that racial, gender, and socioeconomic aspects do not all equally contribute to problems in intersectionality &#91;e.g. gender could have more impact than race considerations in certain situations&#93;&#41;. 	It was observed that the greatest racial inequalities in health were found among women and furthermore seen among those women with higher levels of socioeconomic status &#40;Brown et al. 2016; Cummings and Jackson 2008; Warner and Brown 2011&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="how_is_health_impacted_by_intersectionality">How Is Health Impacted by Intersectionality?</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights the possible synergistic effects of inequality on populations &#40;Choo and Ferree 2010; McCall 2005&#41;.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Health is simultaneously shaped by an array of individual-level social positions &#40;Brown et al. 2016; Hargrove 2018; Schulz and Mullings 2006&#41;. 	- Health disparities at the intersection of race and gender can be covered by unidimensional health research. 	They can overlook the unique experiences of women of color and the multiple forms of oppression that impact one&#39;s life &#40;Bowleg 2012; King 1988; Weber 2010&#41;. 	- The relationship between socioeconomic status &#40;SES&#41; and health is racialized. 	Education, income, and wealth seem to be less protective for the health of blacks compared to whites &#40;Assari 2018; Boen, Keister, and Aronson 2020; Colen, Krueger, and Boettner 2018; Hudson et al. 2013&#41;. 	- Attributing perceived interpersonal discrimination to categories &#40;e.g., race, gender, class, and others&#41; is associated with worse health outcomes &#40;Grollman 2012, 2014&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="how_can_intersectionality_help_address_health_inequity">How Can Intersectionality Help Address Health Inequity?</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights social inequalities in many facets of society, across socially constructed groups, and how social inequalities are not caused by social statuses or identities per se but from systems of oppression &#40;Cho, Crenshaw, and McCall 2013&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality demonstrates how social inequalities are shaped by a confluence of factors often obscured by unidimensional approaches &#40;Dill and Zambrana 2009; McCall 2005&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality underscores utility of examining systems within and between social contexts &#40;Choo and Ferree 2010&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights the complex nature of the social world.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Intersectionality research itself is characterized by its complexity.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality">https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality</a>. November 4 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> October 9 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #advantage #disadvantage #equity ##thought #race #class #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</li><li>The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</li><li>An Emerging Tension</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This concerns my evolving thoughts concerning those who move from a state of historical advantage to one of disadvantage. The language of advantage to disadvantage comes from a Dr. Sylvie &#91;XXX&#93; who described this notion first at the &#91;2021 NAHDO Conference&#93;. &lt;&#33;–Find Dr. Sylvie&#39;s last name–&gt;</p>
<h3 id="thoughts_on_the_emerging_disadvantaged_trends_in_us_caucasian_populations">Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</h3>
<p>Of particular note, there has been the emergence of a sub-class of persons in the United States amongst the low-income communities. Unlike historically marginalized people groups, such as African Americans, Asian American and Pacific Islanders, or Latin Americans, this particular sub-class exists at the intersection of traditional disadvantage and historical advantage: Caucasian. How can a class of such long-standing advantage find itself disadvantaged is the very question I have been thinking about.</p>
<h3 id="the_intersections_of_advantaged_and_disadvantaged">The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</h3>
<p>I recall from a talk from the MIT Health Equity Conference that a Dr. &#91;XXX&#93; said the phrase, &quot;Race is not monolithic.&quot; &lt;&#33;–Find reference to MIT talk and Dr&#39;s name–&gt; That statement I think could also be extended to class structure as the aphorism, &quot;Class is not monolithic.&quot; In popular discussion, the conversation about disadvantaged populations generally have focused particularly at the intersection of disadvantage-disadvantage with respect to race and class. Yet, the intersection of advantage-disadvantage produces an uncomfortable problem: how should we handle these populations?</p>
<p>This intersectional breakdown could be summarized loosely as follows:</p>
<table><tr><th align="right">Type</th><th align="right">Race</th><th align="right">Class</th><th align="right">Examples</th></tr><tr><td align="right">Historically advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Victorian aristocracy, robber barons</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Emerging advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Textile traders, public servants</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Transitional disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Coal miners, share croppers</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Apparent disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Slaves, serfs</td></tr></table>
<h3 id="an_emerging_tension">An Emerging Tension</h3>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged">https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged</a>. October 9 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>