<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  JuliaCon proposal for giving a full length talk on using Julia in an international healthcare study  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 15 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> JuliaCon proposal for giving a full length talk on using Julia in an international healthcare study</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #archive #juliacon #health #equity #mental #juliahealth</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Original Submission<ol><li>Abstract</li><li>Proposal</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="original_submission">Original Submission</h3>
<h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4>
<p>This talk explores the use of Julia in a novel observational health research study that explores health equity and mental health in ~100 million patients in an international collaborative effort across more than 4 countries. Contributions and efforts within the JuliaHealth and adjacent communities have made working with this data possible. The approaches and results shared will be valuable for potential researchers and will open new frontiers for high performance computing and health analytics.</p>
<h4 id="proposal">Proposal</h4>
<p>Conducting health research studies at scale to understand the health of specific communities and subpopulations has long been a struggle. This has been due to a variety of issues, such as a lack of international standards in the structure of electronic health records, patient claims data, and diagnoses. Moreover, the investigation of questions related to the topic of health equity &#40;that is, the skewed distribution of health resources or services to various subpopulations seeking healthcare&#41; has been largely stalled due to these problems.</p>
<p>In a previous talk I gave, <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v&#61;5XsWUZX6lFM">Using Julia for Observational Health Research</a>, I presented early work on the success of using Julia within the space of observational health research in utilizing the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://jacobzelko.com/02082021170353-cdm-standardized-tables/">OMOP Common Data Model</a>. In that previous work, I conducted a pilot study to characterize prevalence rates in mental health care for <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/#workable_definitions_of_intersectionality">intersectional subpopulations</a> suffering from bipolar disorder, depression, and/or suicidality. This work utilized novel tooling and approaches created within Julia to successfully analyze data from ~2.5 million Medicaid subscribers within the U.S. state of Georgia. This work earned the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://www.ohdsi.org/2022-collaborator-showcase">highest awards at the top observational health research venue</a>, drove another successful grant proposal, and resulted in <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://www.nahdo.org/conference/2022/agenda">multiple invited talks</a>. Buoyed by the interest and success of this pilot work, my team and I have moved this project into the next phase: the examination of more than 100 million patients from more than 4 countries across the globe.</p>
<p>In this talk, I will present advances within the JuliaHealth community and the broader Julia ecosystem that have made possible such large scale and federated analyses. In particular, novel JuliaHealth tools such as <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://juliahealth.org/OMOPCDMCohortCreator.jl/">OMOPCDMCohortCreator.jl</a> will be highlighted to show how to analyze &quot;big&quot; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://jacobzelko.com/10282021140730-real-world-evidence/#united_states_food_and_drug_administration_definitions">real world data</a>, how using Julia can be of huge benefit within this space, and how Julia community members could start using these tools for their own research. As this study now takes place across multiple countries, time will also be spent discussing how Julia lends itself very well to robust analyses using literate programming tools such as <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://quarto.org">Quarto</a> or <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://github.com/JunoLab/Weave.jl">Weave.jl</a> and versioning processes through <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://github.com/JuliaDynamics/DrWatson.jl">DrWatson.jl</a> or <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://github.com/iterative/dvc">Data Version Control</a>, which can be utilized to handle each country&#39;s specific needs. Additionally, I will spend some time discussing issues encountered &#40;both technical and anthropological&#41;, ways that the Julia ecosystem could potentially grow to support future work in this research domain, and opportunities for Julia users to get involved. Finally, I will share my personal thoughts on what open questions there are to be addressed in observational health research and how Julia can be a tool to address public health questions and provide insight into questions of health disparities.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this talk will highlight the real world use of Julia in large-scale health research studies built on real world data. Moreover, it will show the potential of the various ecosystems within Julia to analyze and tackle complex questions within health equity. Through this talk, I invite future Julia users and researchers to join me in pursuing the potential of Julia within the space of observational health research.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>100 Million Patients: Julia for International Health Studies</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal">https://jacobzelko.com/01152023193153-juliacon-study-proposal</a>. January 15 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 4 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary #intersectionality #theory #health #research #equity  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Workable Definitions of Intersectionality</li><li>Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>Intersectionality and intersectionality theory is a really cool emerging area of research within health research. Wanted to create this note to summarize intersectionality ideas.</p>
<h3 id="workable_definitions_of_intersectionality">Workable Definitions of Intersectionality</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Intersectionality</strong> - more describes an approach to disentangle and understand the overlapping systems of oppression that contribute to inequality &#40;Collins 2000; Crenshaw 1991&#41;.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Embedded into this notion are several concepts such as social context and complexity &#40;Collins and Bilge 2020&#41;</p>
<h3 id="why_are_intersectional_approaches_needed">Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality.md">Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</a> - An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory">https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory</a>. November 4 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 4 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An introduction to intersectionality theory and medical sociological ideas at play within health disparities research</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibiliography #intersectionality #sociology #medical #equity #disparity #research  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. Homan, T. H. Brown, and B. King, &quot;Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research,&quot; J Health Soc Behav, vol. 62, no. 3, pp. 350–370, Sep. 2021, doi: 10.1177/00221465211032947.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Reading Motivation</li><li>What Is Intersectionality?</li><li>Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</li><li>How Is Health Impacted by Intersectionality?</li><li>How Can Intersectionality Help Address Health Inequity?</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="reading_motivation">Reading Motivation</h3>
<p>I was suggested this paper by Sarah Gasman of Boston Medical Center. She suggested it as has it holds great relevance to some of my research on health disparities. I must say, this paper was revelatory and plan a future discussion with the study authors due to how incredible it was to my mind.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_intersectionality">What Is Intersectionality?</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022141714-what-intersectionality-theory.md">What Is Intersectionality and Intersectionality Theory?</a> - An overview and summary on what is intersectionality and intersectionality theory as an area of health and health disparities research.</p>
<h3 id="why_are_intersectional_approaches_needed">Why Are Intersectional Approaches Needed?</h3>
<p>Prior literature has shown multiple examples where an understanding of intersectionality is useful in a health context: 	- Racism, sexism, and classism are interlocking, mutually constituted, and reinforcing &#40;Collins 2000; Crenshaw 1991; Dill and Zambrana 2009&#41; 	- Effects of racial, gender, and socioeconomic stratification are nonadditive &#40;meaning that racial, gender, and socioeconomic aspects do not all equally contribute to problems in intersectionality &#91;e.g. gender could have more impact than race considerations in certain situations&#93;&#41;. 	It was observed that the greatest racial inequalities in health were found among women and furthermore seen among those women with higher levels of socioeconomic status &#40;Brown et al. 2016; Cummings and Jackson 2008; Warner and Brown 2011&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="how_is_health_impacted_by_intersectionality">How Is Health Impacted by Intersectionality?</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights the possible synergistic effects of inequality on populations &#40;Choo and Ferree 2010; McCall 2005&#41;.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Health is simultaneously shaped by an array of individual-level social positions &#40;Brown et al. 2016; Hargrove 2018; Schulz and Mullings 2006&#41;. 	- Health disparities at the intersection of race and gender can be covered by unidimensional health research. 	They can overlook the unique experiences of women of color and the multiple forms of oppression that impact one&#39;s life &#40;Bowleg 2012; King 1988; Weber 2010&#41;. 	- The relationship between socioeconomic status &#40;SES&#41; and health is racialized. 	Education, income, and wealth seem to be less protective for the health of blacks compared to whites &#40;Assari 2018; Boen, Keister, and Aronson 2020; Colen, Krueger, and Boettner 2018; Hudson et al. 2013&#41;. 	- Attributing perceived interpersonal discrimination to categories &#40;e.g., race, gender, class, and others&#41; is associated with worse health outcomes &#40;Grollman 2012, 2014&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="how_can_intersectionality_help_address_health_inequity">How Can Intersectionality Help Address Health Inequity?</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights social inequalities in many facets of society, across socially constructed groups, and how social inequalities are not caused by social statuses or identities per se but from systems of oppression &#40;Cho, Crenshaw, and McCall 2013&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality demonstrates how social inequalities are shaped by a confluence of factors often obscured by unidimensional approaches &#40;Dill and Zambrana 2009; McCall 2005&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality underscores utility of examining systems within and between social contexts &#40;Choo and Ferree 2010&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Intersectionality highlights the complex nature of the social world.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Intersectionality research itself is characterized by its complexity.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Structural Intersectionality as a New Direction for Health Disparities Research</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality">https://jacobzelko.com/11042022134535-structural-intersectionality</a>. November 4 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> October 9 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #advantage #disadvantage #equity ##thought #race #class #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</li><li>The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</li><li>An Emerging Tension</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This concerns my evolving thoughts concerning those who move from a state of historical advantage to one of disadvantage. The language of advantage to disadvantage comes from a Dr. Sylvie &#91;XXX&#93; who described this notion first at the &#91;2021 NAHDO Conference&#93;. &lt;&#33;–Find Dr. Sylvie&#39;s last name–&gt;</p>
<h3 id="thoughts_on_the_emerging_disadvantaged_trends_in_us_caucasian_populations">Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</h3>
<p>Of particular note, there has been the emergence of a sub-class of persons in the United States amongst the low-income communities. Unlike historically marginalized people groups, such as African Americans, Asian American and Pacific Islanders, or Latin Americans, this particular sub-class exists at the intersection of traditional disadvantage and historical advantage: Caucasian. How can a class of such long-standing advantage find itself disadvantaged is the very question I have been thinking about.</p>
<h3 id="the_intersections_of_advantaged_and_disadvantaged">The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</h3>
<p>I recall from a talk from the MIT Health Equity Conference that a Dr. &#91;XXX&#93; said the phrase, &quot;Race is not monolithic.&quot; &lt;&#33;–Find reference to MIT talk and Dr&#39;s name–&gt; That statement I think could also be extended to class structure as the aphorism, &quot;Class is not monolithic.&quot; In popular discussion, the conversation about disadvantaged populations generally have focused particularly at the intersection of disadvantage-disadvantage with respect to race and class. Yet, the intersection of advantage-disadvantage produces an uncomfortable problem: how should we handle these populations?</p>
<p>This intersectional breakdown could be summarized loosely as follows:</p>
<table><tr><th align="right">Type</th><th align="right">Race</th><th align="right">Class</th><th align="right">Examples</th></tr><tr><td align="right">Historically advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Victorian aristocracy, robber barons</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Emerging advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Textile traders, public servants</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Transitional disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Coal miners, share croppers</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Apparent disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Slaves, serfs</td></tr></table>
<h3 id="an_emerging_tension">An Emerging Tension</h3>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged">https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged</a>. October 9 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>