<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Thoughts on Forester: A Scientist&#39;s Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05172024064639-forest-zettelkasten/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05172024064639-forest-zettelkasten/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Some preliminary and early thoughts on Forester, a robust tool for scientists and mathematicians in developing and working with one&#39;s own Zettelkasten.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Thoughts on Forester: A Scientist&#39;s Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 17 2024</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Some preliminary and early thoughts on Forester, a robust tool for scientists and mathematicians in developing and working with one&#39;s own Zettelkasten.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #blog #forester #sterling #zettelkasten #tool #thought #open #source #note #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Jon Sterling. Forester. https://github.com/jonsterling/ocaml-forester</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Transclusions Done Right</li><li>Overall Impressions</li><li>Developing a Forester Workflow</li><li>Thoughts for Now</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>In discussion with my friend and mentor, <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05192024173906-evan-patterson">Dr. Evan Patterson</a>, I was introduced to a tool created by Dr. Jon Sterling called Forester. These are some of my early thoughts on trying out Forester for my own research and workflow.</p>
<h3 id="transclusions_done_right">Transclusions Done Right</h3>
<p>In my mind, it feels to me that Forester really nailed how transclusions should work in a Zettelkasten type of workflow. In my mind, it is the perfect ambient environment for quickly building and stringing ideas together in coherent and yet atomic ways. Here&#39;s an example of it in action:</p>
<p><img src="https://jacobzelko.com/assets/05182024220110-forester-transclude.gif" alt="" /></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Forester Transclusion:</strong> As one can see, the transclusion is snappy, encourages from its foundation the creation of small pieces of information as different files, and is easy to put together.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What I also didn&#39;t really highlight is that it has great support for various kinds of backlinks that I haven&#39;t really had a chance to explore yet. I think backlinking is another crucial element of Zettelkastens and this is another thing that Forester&#39;s transclusion approach got right. Finally, I haven&#39;t tested this yet, but apparently handling of citations via \(\mathbf{BibTeX}\) and some of Forester&#39;s unique markup syntax enables citations to get rendered &quot;automatically&quot; between transcluded notes meaning that I would personally not have to worry about creating a bibliography for a note that has several transclusions in it as long as the source notes themselves have the relevant and needed citations.</p>
<h3 id="overall_impressions">Overall Impressions</h3>
<p>I played around with Forester for several hours and had quite some fun with the tool. The syntax was relatively straightforward to pick up thanks to the <a href="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-007N.xml">published markup syntax guide</a> and a <a href="https://forest.localcharts.org/lc-0002.xml">nice write-up from Owen Lynch</a>. It wraps around HTML elements using a strange combination of XML and XSTL – interestingly, the tool itself was written in OCaml and this served as my first introduction to ML-style languages. Here&#39;s an example of the mark-up which is, quite pointedly, called <code>tree</code> files:</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia">\title&#123;Jacob S. Zelko Personal Details&#125;
\taxon&#123;bio&#125;
\date&#123;2024-05-16&#125;
\import&#123;macros&#125;\&lt;html:div&gt;&#91;style&#93;&#123;
  width: 50\&#37;; 
  height: 400px; 
  background-image: url&#40;&#39;jz.jpg&#39;&#41;; 
  background-size: contain; 
  background-repeat: no-repeat;
&#125;&#123;&#125;\p&#123;&#125;\p&#123;
  My name is Jacob Scott Zelko&#33; 
  I am currently pursuing my MS in Applied Mathematics at Northeastern University &#40;NEU&#41; 
  and am a trainee of NEU&#39;s Roux Institute.
&#125;</code></pre>
<p>As one can see, the syntax is relatively straightforward &#40;although I had to do an &quot;ugly&quot; hack to get image rendering to work&#41;. It feels very \(\LaTeX\)-ish in the sense that all the curly braces have come back – with a vengeance&#33; One is able to create their own macros similar to how you can in various programming languages as well as within \(\LaTeX\) and inject HTML directly into your documents similar to how you can with Markdown. In fact, to me, it feels a hybrid between Markdown and \(\LaTeX\) Although the syntax is a bit gnarly, where it really shines is it&#39;s handling of mathematical notation directly in your browser. Thanks to a macro and <code>sty</code> file Owen created for the platform, <a href="https://forest.localcharts.org">LocalCharts</a>, I can readily render and draw commutative diagrams simply and easily directly within my notes:</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia">\p&#123;
  \quiver&#123;    \begin&#123;tikzcd&#125;
      &amp;&amp; X \\
      \\
      A &amp;&amp; &#123;A \times B&#125; &amp;&amp; B
      \arrow&#91;&quot;&#123;p_1&#125;&quot;&#39;, from&#61;1-3, to&#61;3-1&#93;
      \arrow&#91;&quot;u&quot;&#39;, dashed, from&#61;1-3, to&#61;3-3&#93;
      \arrow&#91;&quot;&#123;p_2&#125;&quot;, from&#61;1-3, to&#61;3-5&#93;
      \arrow&#91;&quot;&#123;\pi_1&#125;&quot;&#39;, from&#61;3-3, to&#61;3-1&#93;
      \arrow&#91;&quot;&#123;\pi_2&#125;&quot;&#39;, from&#61;3-3, to&#61;3-5&#93;
    \end&#123;tikzcd&#125;  &#125;
&#125;</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: the macro <code>quiver</code> is what allows me to create this <code>tikzcd</code> diagram directly in my notes. Aside from the <code>p</code> and <code>quiver</code> notation, the commutative diagram <code>tikz</code> code I wrote here is strictly \(\LaTeX\) – finally, full Tikz support in the browser and easily done too&#33;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One thing that I should also mention is the first rate support Forester does have for mathematics typesetting. Out of the box, it supports most of \(\LaTeX\) math formatting and enables one to quickly and easily render mathematics equations or notation where necessary. To my understanding, it&#39;s way of rendering is much richer than MathJax or \(\KaTeX\) but I am unsure of all the internals of how the math is rendered.</p>
<h3 id="developing_a_forester_workflow">Developing a Forester Workflow</h3>
<p>As Forester is still quite new, it is understandable if the workflow isn&#39;t quite sorted yet. I personally felt that this was one of the more underdeveloped aspects of the Forester ecosystem. After reviewing available tools, I settled on this approach:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Writing</strong>: using my <a href="https://github.com/TheCedarPrince/Service">Neovim configuration</a> to write notes quickly.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Live Updates</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/kentookura">Kento Okura</a> created a really nice Forester tool called &quot;<a href="https://github.com/kentookura/forest-server">forest-server</a>&quot; in Rust that allows previews and builds to happen instantly.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Preview</strong>: I use the <a href="https://vivaldi.com">Vivaldi browser</a> to do a live preview of my notes changing and updating in real time.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Here&#39;s an example of the workflow in action:</p>
<p><img src="https://jacobzelko.com/assets/05192024172349-forester-preview.gif" alt="" /></p>
<p>The key command here I use is the function <code>forest watch 1234 -- &quot;build forest.toml&quot;</code> in the base of my &quot;forest&quot;. As I save my file, the command to build the forest is triggered and updates the note rather quickly. There is some flashing going on with the updating that I do not know how to fix – can be a bit jarring but is mostly fine.</p>
<h3 id="thoughts_for_now">Thoughts for Now</h3>
<p>Although I quite like Forester, I am a bit hesitant to transfer over to it myself for all my Zettelkasten needs. One of the biggest reasons for this is that my own Zettelkasten at this point has nearly \(600\) notes all written in markdown. To translate them over, I could write a parser for <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/NoteMate.jl/dev/">NoteMate.jl</a> that would allow ready translation from my <a href="04172022033744-open-knowledge-standard.md">note style</a> to a <code>tree</code> file.</p>
<p>Additionally, there are a few features that I feel just aren&#39;t quite &quot;there yet&quot;. Particularly, the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The syntax for <code>tree</code> files, although a great start, is missing some things I find important.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This includes more ergonomic syntax for including images, code blocks, quote blocks, etc. that I rely on within markdown.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The wrapping around HTML elements doesn&#39;t feel quite complete.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As an example, to include an image on a page, I can write something like <code>\&lt;html:img&gt;&#91;src&#93;&#123;photo.png&#125;</code> which is easy enough. But what if I want to inject more attributes to the HTML element here, such as the <code>max-width</code> of the image? That was not clear to me in my readings of the source code and syntax reference.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Although I thought that the transclusion methods of Forester by default are great, it does not appear to me how one can reference sections of a note via transclusion.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>For example, within my markdown set-up, not only can I reference other notes, I can also link to the direct section within a particular note. I have not seen any such &quot;section referencing&quot; capabilities available in Forester if I just want to transclude &quot;part&quot; of a note.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Lack of interoperability with other note types or note systems.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As I mentioned, I still have \(\approx 600\) markdown notes within my personal Zettelkasten so being able to go between other note types is crucial. What&#39;s more, related to this problem, is that markdown or \(\LaTeX\) is far more ubiquitous and accessible across multiple platforms if I need to preview or reference something on the spot. I haven&#39;t yet seen this available with <code>tree</code> files yet.</p>
<p>With that all to say, if I had started my personal Zettelkasten journey with Forester, I think I probably would&#39;ve figured out ways to get around all these issues. As of now, these issues prevent me from wanting to move my entire Zettelkasten over to the system.</p>
<p>However, with that said, I think I actually will try giving Forester more of a test with some of my mathematics studies and research. It&#39;s first rate support for mathematics is superb and although the workflow is quite minimal at the time, while writing some notes in the <code>tree</code> files, I was beginning to see just how natural and ergonomic it was to write within the system. Depending on how things go with my experiments with Forester, I may end up having to write a parser of some kind in the near future&#33;</p>
<p>If you use or have used Forester, please let me know your experience with it and comment below – would love to hear about your experiences&#33;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Thoughts on Forester: A Scientist&#39;s Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05172024064639-forest-zettelkasten">https://jacobzelko.com/05172024064639-forest-zettelkasten</a>. May 17 2024.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on the Zettelkasten note taking system as made popular by sociologist Niklas Luhmann.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 2 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on the Zettelkasten note taking system as made popular by sociologist Niklas Luhmann.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary ##zettelkasten #learning #research #tool #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Selecting Notes for a Zettelkasten</li><li><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles">Principles of Zettelkasten</a></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="selecting_notes_for_a_zettelkasten">Selecting Notes for a Zettelkasten</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria">Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten.
- **Rationale:** Enumerates a robust system for how to add notes to the Zettelkasten</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="03172020033742-antifragility">Antifragility</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** An overview on Nassim Taleb&#39;s thoughts on Antifragility
- **Rationale:** Zettelkastens should be antifragile -- i.e. they thrive off of disorder and chaos and adapt to it meaningfully.</code></pre>
<h3 id="a_hrefhttpsjacobzelkocom03092020031618-zettelkasten-principlesprinciples_of_zettelkasten"><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles">Principles of Zettelkasten</a></h3>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** General principles on how to create and use a Zettelkasten</code></pre>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten">https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten</a>. December 2 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Principles of the Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  General principles on how to create and use a Zettelkasten.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Principles of the Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 2 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> General principles on how to create and use a Zettelkasten.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #zettelkasten #principles #atomicity #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<ol>
<li><p>&quot;Principle of Atomicity&quot; – each zettel should contain only one idea &#40;principle credited to Christian Tietze&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Each zettel should be self-contained and understandable as a standalone scrap of thought.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Link each zettel and explain why you are linking them together.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Reword gathered information in your own words &#40;unless if it is a verbatim quote or something&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Add references to each zettel.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Don&#39;t be afraid to add your own ideas to the Zettelkasten – embrace it.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Have no fear when it comes to organization – the order will arise organically in the Zettelkasten.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Never delete a zettel and don&#39;t worry too much about when you create zettels; the more information the better.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Don&#39;t overthink the Zettelkasten. Keep it simple and efficient.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Principles of the Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles">https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles</a>. December 2 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Niklas Luhmann&#39;s Card Index: The Fabrication of Serendipity  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05032020155207-fabrication-serendipity/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05032020155207-fabrication-serendipity/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A more in-depth examination of the Zettelkasten method  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Niklas Luhmann&#39;s Card Index: The Fabrication of Serendipity</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 3 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A more in-depth examination of the Zettelkasten method</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #database #computer #niklasluhmann #zettelkasten  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. F. K. Schmidt, Niklas Luhmann&#39;s Card Index: The Fabrication of Serendipity, Sociologica, vol. Vol 12, pp. 53-60 Pages, Jul. 2018, doi: 10.6092/ISSN.1971-8853/8350.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;As early as in the 1950s to 1960s, Luhmann simulated a modern computer-based database system &#91;...&#93;.&quot; &#40;pg. 59&#41;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I actually think that the Zettelkasten method by Luhmann is distinctly different from a computer database. The reason being, is that this is far more overlapping and far reaching than a discrete system like a simple computer database. One could argue that relations could be made analogous to relational databases but here, the relations are far more abstract than they are in the traditional relational database. If anything, Luhmann&#39;s Zettelkasten is more similar to a graph-type system - such as a knowledge graph - than a database </p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Luhmann&#39;s card index allows the production of new and often unexpected knowledge by relating concepts and thoughts that do not have much in common at first sight &#91;...&#93; &#91;I&#93;t makes &#91;...&#93; serendipity possible in a systemically and theoretically informed way.&quot; &#40;pg. 54&#41;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The power of the Zettelkasten comes from these accidental connections. Very similar to how one may spread out pieces of paper on a table and make a new connection, so does this method simulate it in very much the same way.</p>
<p>Luhmann employed ambiguity and indecisiveness into the development of the Zettelkasten approach whenever he added a new piece of information to the Zettelkasten. Rather than assigning the piece of information to one discrete category, he enabled that piece of info to naturally attach itself to other pieces of information as <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum">knowledge falls across a spectrum.</a> &#40;pg. 56&#41;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Niklas Luhmann&#39;s Card Index: The Fabrication of Serendipity</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05032020155207-fabrication-serendipity">https://jacobzelko.com/05032020155207-fabrication-serendipity</a>. May 3 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 30 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #zettelkasten #information #knowledge #criteria #questions #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Selecting Information for a Zettel</li><li>Zettel Creation</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="selecting_information_for_a_zettel">Selecting Information for a Zettel</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Does this not add to the overall nature of the Zettelkasten? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>What sort of topics could this open in the Zettelkasten? Are these topics you are willing to invest into? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Where does this new note possibly fit into in the rest of the conversation with your Zettelkasten? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Can this information be added to an already existing Zettel or theme? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="zettel_creation">Zettel Creation</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Do you have enough information do write a new zettel?&#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Do you understand the information enough in the zettel you are creating? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Each Zettel should fit onto a screen.  &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria">https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria</a>. March 30 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers. 2017.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  How to Take Smart Notes  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Takeaways from the book How to Take Smart Notes  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>How to Take Smart Notes</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 29 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Takeaways from the book How to Take Smart Notes</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #knowledge #notetaking #zettelkasten #mentalmodels #writing #blog #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Quotes from the Book:</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This was overall a book on knowledge management – in particular, how to take, digest, and use the notes we make while reading material, listening to lectures, or absorb knowledge in general. Sonke Ahrens, the author of the book, also gave a rather in-depth overview of the Zettelkasten method created by sociologist Niklas Luhmann. I found the book useful in giving legitimately very good advice on note-taking, great anecdotes to illustrate his point, and also assistance on using the Zettelkasten method. </p>
<p>Furthermore, Ahrens made an interesting point saying that if you are approaching writing where you start with just a blank page, you are missing the point. When you approach a blank page, it <em>ought</em> not feel blank but rather the place to put your notes and ideas together that you have been collecting about a particular topic. Ahrens believes that fundamental teachings about how to write long-form papers are wrong in that they do not start with the most crucial aspect of the writing process – free form thought. And free form thought, when investigating a topic, is best captured using a global sort of note taking method like the Zettelkasten.</p>
<h3 id="quotes_from_the_book">Quotes from the Book:</h3>
<pre><code class="language-julia">&quot;Every intellectual endeavour starts with a note&quot; &#91;pg 8&#93;&quot;We only write if it helps us with our own thinking.&quot; &#91;pg 101&#93;</code></pre>
<p>These two quotes get at the idea that when we write and create notes, we are not only creating notes but also playing with ideas and digesting them into our minds.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes">https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes</a>. March 29 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>