<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Electronic Health Records  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01082021031034-electronic-health-records/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01082021031034-electronic-health-records/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of Electronic Health Records  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Electronic Health Records</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 7 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of Electronic Health Records</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #ehr #healthcare #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Assessment of EHRs</li><li>Limitations of EHRs</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="assessment_of_ehrs">Assessment of EHRs</h3>
<p>US Department of Health and Human Services&#39; &#40;HHS&#41; Office of the National Coordinator of Health Information Technology &#40;ONC&#41; specifies standards for EHR systems. This is to ensure that EHRs meet &quot;Meaningful Use&quot; criteria.</p>
<p>EHR data is generally from patients who have the means of seeing a provider. &#91;1&#93; This data may be available from different encounters. Examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Inpatient</p>
</li>
<li><p>Outpatient</p>
</li>
<li><p>Emergency department visits</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="limitations_of_ehrs">Limitations of EHRs</h3>
<p>EHRs are not optimized for secondary uses. They have multiple limitations for research &#91;1&#93;, &#91;2&#93; EHR data is recorded during healthcare visitations. As a result, bias can favor those sicker in datasets. This results in what is known as informative censoring &#91;1&#93;, &#91;3&#93;, &#91;4&#93; It is important to distinguish between &quot;not present&quot; in datasets versus &quot;did not assess&quot;.</p>
<p>Errors propagate EHRs and ancillary sources. Data is entered by providers during visitation or memory. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<p>Healthcare standards change over time. Collection standards vary by location. Much data is unstructured and narrative in nature. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01112021180936-we-may-think">Vannevar Bush article &quot;As We May Think&quot;</a> also has relation to this very same issue. Regarding how clinicians&#39; recall or anyone&#39;s recall of an incident from more than a few days ago may be impossible. There are analogies between the two disparate lines of thought: one clinical, the other academic: both overwhelming.</p>
<p>Only a few data fields are common across different EHRs. Most phenotype definitions use combinations of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>ICD-9 codes</p>
</li>
<li><p>Medication names</p>
</li>
<li><p>Laboratory tests.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>EHRs will use ICD-10 codes for diagnoses and potentially SNOMED-CT codes for problem lists and other aspects of EHRs.  EHRs also consist of free form text where Natural Language Processing could be of use. &#91;5&#93; ICD-9-CM diagnosis codes can be found in technical billing, professional billing, and/or problem lists.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Electronic Health Records</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01082021031034-electronic-health-records">https://jacobzelko.com/01082021031034-electronic-health-records</a>. January 7 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; R. Richesson and M. Smerek, “Electronic health records-based phenotyping,” Rethink. Clin. Trials Living Textb. Pragmatic Clin. Trials, vol. 2016, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; K. B. Bayley, T. Belnap, L. Savitz, A. L. Masica, N. Shah, and N. S. Fleming, “Challenges in using electronic health record data for CER: Experience of 4 learning organizations and solutions applied,” Med. Care, pp. S80–S86, 2013.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; W. J. Shih, “Problems in dealing with missing data and informative censoring in clinical trials,” Curr. Control. Trials Cardiovasc. Med., vol. 3, no. 1, pp. 1–7, 2002.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; N. R. Council et al., The prevention and treatment of missing data in clinical trials. National Academies Press, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; J. F. Ludvigsson et al., “Use of computerized algorithm to identify individuals in need of testing for celiac disease,” J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc., vol. 20, no. e2, pp. e306–e310, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Are Computable Phenotypes?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview into what computable phenotypes are and how they are used.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Are Computable Phenotypes?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 7 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview into what computable phenotypes are and how they are used.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #ehr #electronic #health #records #computable #phenotypes #codes #icd-9 #icd-10 #snomed-ct #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Operational Definitions</li><li>Computable Phenotypes Definitions<ol><li>Creating Computable Phenotypes</li><li>Characteristics of a Good Phenotype Definitions</li><li>Determining the Validity of a Phenotype Definition</li></ol></li><li>Available Phenotype Definitions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="operational_definitions">Operational Definitions</h3>
<p><strong>Phenotype:</strong> a measurable biological, behavioral, or cognitive marker found more often in specific individuals than the general population; the appearance it presents to observers.&#91;1&#93;</p>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/./08122022205622-assessing-phenotype-fairness"><strong>Phenotyping:</strong></a> Identifying a set of patients with a particular disease </p>
<p><strong>Computable phenotype:</strong> a clinical element that can derived from queries to an EHR or ancillary data sources &#40;such as claims data, or disease registries&#41; using a defined set of data elements and logical expressions.  It does not require chart review or interpretation by a clinician. </p>
<p><strong>Data element:</strong> the unit of data being queried, exchanged, or analyzed. It includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Descriptive name for the concept</p>
</li>
<li><p>A specified value set</p>
</li>
<li><p>Additional metadata</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Value set:</strong> the set of possible information associated with a particular data element. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p><strong>Metadata:</strong> descriptive data about objects, including data objects; data about data.</p>
<h3 id="computable_phenotypes_definitions">Computable Phenotypes Definitions</h3>
<p><strong>Computable phenotype definitions:</strong> classifying individuals with a given characteristic of interest from EHRs. Done by using data routinely collected in EHRs or ancillary data sources &#40;such as claims data, or disease registries&#41;.</p>
<p>Computable phenotype definitions enable reproducible queries of EHRs. They are made of data elements and boolean operators which are executed by a computer. Furthermore, they rely on value sets derived from standardized coding systems.</p>
<p>These definitions help identify people with particular conditions across healthcare organizations by using common definitions. Standard phenotype definitions can enable direct identification of cohorts. This allows decision-makers to specifically target screening tests and interventions to such cohorts.</p>
<h4 id="creating_computable_phenotypes">Creating Computable Phenotypes</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Define how a concept should be studied given available data.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Identify which diagnoses, treatments, and patient characteristics suggest a condition of interest.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Specify clinical condition being searched for and how that would be represented in various EHRs.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="characteristics_of_a_good_phenotype_definitions">Characteristics of a Good Phenotype Definitions</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Does not conflict with a previously pre-defined phenotype definitions</p>
</li>
<li><p>Details of a definition need be communicated.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It should enable reproducible queries in other contexts.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><p>They must always yield similar results given same data; be reliable.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Assess implementation for a given setting</p>
</li>
<li><p>Phenotype definition must be compared using available clinical gold standard.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="determining_the_validity_of_a_phenotype_definition">Determining the Validity of a Phenotype Definition</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Ability to correctly identify which individuals exhibit the phenotype.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="available_phenotype_definitions">Available Phenotype Definitions</h3>
<p>This paper contains a plethora of resources regarding phenotype definitions:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>R. Richesson and M. Smerek, &quot;Electronic health records-based phenotyping,&quot; Rethinking clinical trials: A living textbook of pragmatic clinical trials, vol. 2016, 2014.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Are Computable Phenotypes?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes">https://jacobzelko.com/01072021074632-computable-phenotypes</a>. January 7 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; R. Richesson and M. Smerek, “Electronic health records-based phenotyping,” Rethink. Clin. Trials Living Textb. Pragmatic Clin. Trials, vol. 2016, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; “NIH Common Data Elements &#40;CDE&#41; Repository.” &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://cde.nlm.nih.gov/home. &#91;Accessed: 30-Dec-2020&#93;.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>