<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Jevons Paradox?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08112023144820-jevons-paradox-explained/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08112023144820-jevons-paradox-explained/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of Jevon&#39;s Paradox and selected examples  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Jevons Paradox?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 11 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of Jevon&#39;s Paradox and selected examples</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #economics #climate #paradox #overview #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>&quot;Jevons paradox,&quot; Wikipedia. Jul. 05, 2023. Accessed: Aug. 11, 2023. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title&#61;Jevons_paradox&amp;oldid&#61;1163586515</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Overview</li><li>Examples</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>I first came across this paradox within high school history courses. It never left my mind as I found it such a bizarre and counter-intuitive result that had great implications when trying to help or improve situations. In a way, it has been a guiding principle in my life to think through interventions.</p>
<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>When technological progress or government policy increases efficiency of resource usage, but the falling cost of this resource results in increases of its usage, rather than a reduction. bauerBookReviewPerspectives2009?, yorkUnderstandingJevonsParadox2016?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Put more plainly, the paradox emerges when you improve the efficiency of a resource to decrease its use but instead, the improved efficiency increases the demand of the resource.</p>
<h3 id="examples">Examples</h3>
<p>The most canonical example comes from environmental economics wherein a city with a vehicle traffic problem wants to reduce traffic in their city. To remedy this problem, they think that increasing the number of lanes in their main city highway will reduce traffic. So, they build additional lanes. But rather than improve traffic, traffic becomes even worse as a result of more people wanting to drive through the city. schneiderCityLabUniversityInduced2018?</p>
<p>Where Jevons first observed this was in the mid-1800&#39;s. He saw that when James Watt created a steam engine that greatly improved the efficiency of coal-ran steam engines, it made using coal very cost effective. As a result, Jevons observed that the use of coal, rather than staying the same or going down, increased as people wanted to use coal more often. jevonsCoalQuestionInquiry1866? Thus, the inception of Jevons Paradox. </p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Is Jevons Paradox?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08112023144820-jevons-paradox-explained">https://jacobzelko.com/08112023144820-jevons-paradox-explained</a>. August 11 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Emerging insights into income and poverty during the COVID-19 pandemic  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 28 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Emerging insights into income and poverty during the COVID-19 pandemic</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #pandemic #covid #economics #poverty #population #survey  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. Han, B. Meyer, and J. Sullivan, &quot;Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic,&quot; National Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, MA, w27729, Aug. 2020. doi: 10.3386/w27729.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>General Insights</li><li>Methods of Research</li><li>Key Conclusions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="general_insights">General Insights</h3>
<p>This study provides a template for understanding large economic shocks as they happen to counter the problem of data availability during major economic shocks. The start of the pandemic saw an unprecedented decline in economic activity in the US. The largest single month decline in US unemployment was 14 percent in April 2020.</p>
<p>The federal government&#39;s response totalled to nearly three trillion dollars spent to counter pandemic effects. Their response comprised of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Economic Impact Payments &#40;tax rebates&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Small business loans</p>
</li>
<li><p>Massive increase in unemployment insurance as part of the CARES Act</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="methods_of_research">Methods of Research</h3>
<p>Basic Monthly Current Population Survey &#40;Monthly CPS&#41;, was used due to its quick release to understand the impact of macroeconomic conditions and government policies on US families&#39; incomes.</p>
<p>Family income from respondents in their first or fifth month in the survey were observed for a monthly sample ranging from 8,999 households and 20,822 individuals in February 2020 to 6,149 households and 14,383 individuals in April 2020.  Monthly CPS data from IPUMS-CPS &#91;1&#93; Generally, 90&#37; of earnings are reported in CPS, as opposed to ~60&#37; of unemployment insurance. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<h3 id="key_conclusions">Key Conclusions</h3>
<p>Without US government intervention, poverty would have risen by 2.7 percentage points between January and June.</p>
<p>The COVID Impact survey &#91;3&#93; finds an increase in food insecurity when compared to a different earlier survey while the Census Bureau&#39;s Household Pulse survey &#91;4&#93; finds high rates of inability to pay rent.  These sources suggest increased hardship after the pandemic. The increase in deprivation is not due to the overall income loss, but rather due to other disruptions of the pandemic, including possibly the unevenness of the income flows.</p>
<p>Disruptions such as:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Closures of schools</p>
</li>
<li><p>Stores</p>
</li>
<li><p>Churches and other facilities</p>
</li>
<li><p>The uncertainty about future income streams</p>
</li>
<li><p>Concerns about the health of family and friends</p>
</li>
<li><p>Other disruptions</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic">https://jacobzelko.com/12282020152055-income-poverty-pandemic</a>. December 28 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Flood, M. King, R. Rodgers, S. Ruggles, and J. Warren, “Integrated public use microdata series, current population survey: Version 7.0 &#91;dataset&#93;. Minneapolis, MN: Integrated public use microdata; 2020.”</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; B. D. Meyer, W. K. Mok, and J. X. Sullivan, “Household surveys in crisis,” J. Econ. Perspect., vol. 29, no. 4, pp. 199–226, 2015.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; L. Bauer, “The COVID-19 Crisis Has Already Left Too Many Children Hungry in America,” May 06, 2020. https://www.hamiltonproject.org/blog/the<em>covid</em>19<em>crisis</em>has<em>already</em>left<em>too</em>many<em>children</em>hungry<em>in</em>america &#40;accessed Nov. 08, 2020&#41;.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; J. Fields et al., “Design and Operation of the 2020 Household Pulse Survey, 2020,” U.S. Census Bureau, 2020. Accessed: Nov. 08, 2020. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/technical-documentation/hhp/2020<em>HPS</em>Background.pdf</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>