<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Definitions Concerning Terrorism  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022133230-definitions-around-terrorism/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022133230-definitions-around-terrorism/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A summary note focused on definitions concerning terrorism and  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Definitions Concerning Terrorism</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 28 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A summary note focused on definitions concerning terrorism and</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary #definition #terrorism #radicalization #fear #violence #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>What Is Terrorism?</li><li>Goals of Terrorism</li><li>What Is Violent Radicalization</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="what_is_terrorism">What Is Terrorism?</h3>
<p>Terrorism is defined as the use of violence and intimidation in the pursuit of political aims. Terrorism is not an individual experience; it is violence at a population level and worthy of attention in fields focusing on socioecological understanding of social processes and human behavior <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors.md">Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</a>. Often the threat of violence – is enough to accomplish an objective &#40;this holds true often for terrorist groups as well&#41;.</p>
<h3 id="goals_of_terrorism">Goals of Terrorism</h3>
<p>Instill a population level of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Fear</p>
</li>
<li><p>Uncertainty</p>
</li>
<li><p>Vulnerability</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As well as:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Undermine health and well-being of populations</p>
</li>
<li><p>Not preventing avoidable morbidity and mortality - Yehuda R, Hyman SE. The impact of terrorism on brain, and behavior: what we know and what we need to know. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2005;30:1773–1780.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what_is_violent_radicalization">What Is Violent Radicalization</h3>
<p>Violent radicalization the process of adopting or promoting an ideologically based violence to advance political, religious, or social change via an extremist belief system <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors.md">Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</a>.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Definitions Concerning Terrorism</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08282022133230-definitions-around-terrorism">https://jacobzelko.com/08282022133230-definitions-around-terrorism</a>. August 28 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Social Determinants Surrounding Terrorism  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022134930-social-determinants-terrorism/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022134930-social-determinants-terrorism/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Working note on the social determinants of terrorist activity in a vein inspired by the notion of social determinants of health  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Social Determinants Surrounding Terrorism</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 28 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Working note on the social determinants of terrorist activity in a vein inspired by the notion of social determinants of health</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #social #determinants #terrorism #health #violence #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Definitions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="definitions">Definitions</h3>
<p>Social cohesion is the connectedness and solidarity in populations. This includes the absence of social conflict and presence of social bonds.27 A measure used to quantify social cohesion is trust. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors.md">Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</a></p>
<p>Social capital are the features of social structures that are resources for community members to create action.27 Social capital acts as a safety net for individuals to protect against losses like physical health, mental health, and life satisfaction.31<a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors.md">Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</a> &#40;See <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08282022135955-social-capital.md">Features of Social Capital</a> for further insight on what social capital is and its importance&#41;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Social Determinants Surrounding Terrorism</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08282022134930-social-determinants-terrorism">https://jacobzelko.com/08282022134930-social-determinants-terrorism</a>. August 28 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Features of Social Capital  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022135955-social-capital/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08282022135955-social-capital/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on what social capital is and how it affects  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Features of Social Capital</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 28 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on what social capital is and how it affects</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary #social #capital #risk #terrorism #violence #crime #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Varying levels of social capital in a population is an important determinant of health in children, adolescents, adults, and aging populations.28,33 <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors.md">Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</a></p>
<p>Low levels of social capital, can be a risk factors for population health such as:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Prevention of crime.33,35</p>
</li>
<li><p>High risk behaviors such as spread of suicidal ideation36 and alcohol and other drug use among adolescents.37</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Social capital brings people together in at least two ways:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Bring alike people together to create bonding networks</p>
</li>
<li><p>Bring people not alike together to create bridging networks. 29,30</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Features of Social Capital</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08282022135955-social-capital">https://jacobzelko.com/08282022135955-social-capital</a>. August 28 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  The Origins Of Terrorism: Cross-country Estimates Of Socio-economic Determinants Of Terrorism  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220628-origins-terrorism/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220628-origins-terrorism/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Brief summary of paper examining socioeconomic impacts or determinants of terroristic ideology  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>The Origins Of Terrorism: Cross-country Estimates Of Socio-economic Determinants Of Terrorism</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 28 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Brief summary of paper examining socioeconomic impacts or determinants of terroristic ideology</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #terrorism #socioeconomics #determinants #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>A. Freytag, J. J. Krüger, D. Meierrieks, and F. Schneider, &quot;The origins of terrorism: Cross-country estimates of socio-economic determinants of terrorism,&quot; European Journal of Political Economy, vol. 27, pp. S5–S16, Dec. 2011, doi: 10.1016/j.ejpoleco.2011.06.009.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>I personally only found this paper mildly interesting. In my research in terrorism, I was not as interested in this sort of research literature as it was too granular for what I was investigating – which was a broad level of investigation as an initial pass.</p>
<p>Their biggest takeaway from their study was that they found contrary to mainstream literature now, there is a socioeconomic impact to account for when researching terrorism. This especially extends the poor socioeconomic conditions individuals find themselves in such as insufficient welfare policies, economic discrimination, and low levels of economic openness. &#40;e.g., Burgoon, 2006; Blomberg and Hess, 2008; Krieger and Meierrieks, 2010; Caruso and Schneider, 2011&#41; Additionally, to fight terrorism, they surmised that improving socioeconomic conditions could in fact counter terrorist growth. </p>
<p>&lt;&#33;–TODO: Add citations–&gt;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>The Origins Of Terrorism: Cross-country Estimates Of Socio-economic Determinants Of Terrorism</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220628-origins-terrorism">https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220628-origins-terrorism</a>. August 28 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A review on how terrorism intersects with the social determinants of health  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> August 19 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A review on how terrorism intersects with the social determinants of health</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #terrorism #social #determinants #health #cohesion #social #isolation  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>H. E. Alcalá, M. Z. Sharif, and G. Samari, &quot;Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective,&quot; Health Equity, vol. 1, no. 1, pp. 87–95, Aug. 2017, doi: 10.1089/heq.2016.0016.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Public Health Approach to Terrorism</li><li>Shortcomings of Addressing Terrorism from a Public Health Perspective</li><li>Factors Leading to Extremism</li><li>Studying Gang Violence as a Proxy for Terrorist Groups</li><li>Positive Approaches to Mitigate Radicalization</li><li>Problems with Whiteness and Terrorism Classifications</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This paper was probably the best paper I have read on the subject of terrorism research and how it intersects with public health and the social determinants of health. It provided a comprehensive background on what terrorism and radicalism are as well as some very useful public health terminology introducing the concept of social cohesion and social capital. Furthermore, it got at the concept of how examining terrorism and gang violence from a public health perspective is very understudied and underutilized when exploring this space.</p>
<h3 id="public_health_approach_to_terrorism">Public Health Approach to Terrorism</h3>
<p>2.6&#37; of terrorism deaths happen in the West. 72&#37; belong to:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Syria</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pakistan</p>
</li>
<li><p>Iraq</p>
</li>
<li><p>Nigeria</p>
</li>
<li><p>Afghanistan - Institute for Economics and Peace. Global Terrorism Index. New York, NY. 2015.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Terrorism associated with negative mental health outcomes in:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>depression</p>
</li>
<li><p>anxiety</p>
</li>
<li><p>posttraumatic stress disorder</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Amongst others - Rousseau C, Jamil U, Bhui K, et al. Consequences of 9/11 and the war on terror on children’s and young adult’s mental health: a systematic review of the past 10 years. Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2015;20:173–193.</p>
<h3 id="shortcomings_of_addressing_terrorism_from_a_public_health_perspective">Shortcomings of Addressing Terrorism from a Public Health Perspective</h3>
<p>Historically public health has focused on: </p>
<ul>
<li><p>Preparedness strategies</p>
</li>
<li><p>Containment of terrorist fallout</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>What has been missing in this space is examining:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Social determinants of terrorism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Determinants for violent radicalization</p>
</li>
<li><p>Risk factors for terrorism</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="factors_leading_to_extremism">Factors Leading to Extremism</h3>
<p>A case study from the United Kingdom shows that violent radicalization is an outcome of a complex interaction among social, political, cultural, historical, and interpersonal factors.7 </p>
<p>Discrimination can be thought of as a &quot;comorbidity&quot; of social isolation and exclusionary behavior. One form of systematic discrimination is immigration policy as it directly contributes to social segregation.9 Feelings of marginalization have been shown to lead to decreased self-worth and, in turn, increase radicalization.57 Those discriminated against could then fall easily to extremist influence and ideology as a result of weakening social cohesion.52</p>
<h3 id="studying_gang_violence_as_a_proxy_for_terrorist_groups">Studying Gang Violence as a Proxy for Terrorist Groups</h3>
<p>A proxy to study terrorism is to study gang violence</p>
<p>At the individual level, gangs and terrorist organizations appeal to individuals who are psychologically deviant, have limited access to socioeconomic opportunities, or are marginalized members of society.39–44 In fact, terrorist groups attract a range of unstable individuals.45</p>
<blockquote>
<p>NOTE: This seems to contradict the paper <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220130-people-become-terrorists.md">Why Do People Become Terrorists</a> as it notes that instead, it was observed how many of these people who are not fully psychologically deviant but rather of clear mind. Furthermore, in my attempt to reconcile such different observations, I would posit that rather, both explanations and comments are valid but that &quot;unstable individuals&quot; seem to conflate a kind of negative aspect to a person whereas the linked paper avoids the notion of unstable persons and instead explains how most of these people are of clear opinion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Goals generally exclusive to gangs:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Symbolic ends</p>
</li>
<li><p>Looser structure</p>
</li>
<li><p>Less temporary collaborations</p>
</li>
<li><p>Shorter memberships</p>
</li>
<li><p>Gang occupies physical space.46</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The main difference between gangs and terrorist groups is that gangs are often not politically motivated.47 </p>
<h3 id="positive_approaches_to_mitigate_radicalization">Positive Approaches to Mitigate Radicalization</h3>
<p>Dutch police actively sought to integrate individuals from Syria by connecting them with a psychiatrist or mentor. Then, they provided assistance to find housing or means to return to school. To round out this reintegration process, they went even further to provide &quot;whatever they needed to fully integrate back into society.&quot;67 </p>
<p>This approach, believes that to fight terrorism through policing and/or &quot;profiling&quot; will create real or perceived discrimination, humiliation, and/or marginalization. Other papers have shown <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08232022220130-people-become-terrorists.md">this to be an accurate assessment</a>.</p>
<p>&lt;&#33;–TODO: Add citations to note–&gt;</p>
<h3 id="problems_with_whiteness_and_terrorism_classifications">Problems with Whiteness and Terrorism Classifications</h3>
<p>Muslim Americans who come from the Middle East are often classified as &quot;White&quot; by categories set forth by the Office of Management and Budget. However, this is in complete opposition to the fact that a large proportion of Muslim Americans do not identify as &quot;White&quot;. 15 An implicit assumption and implicit problem is that people labeled &quot;White&quot; are assumed to be &quot;racially neutral.&quot;15 </p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Social Determinants of Health, Violent Radicalization, and Terrorism: A Public Health Perspective</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors">https://jacobzelko.com/08192022115354-health-terrorism-factors</a>. August 19 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>