<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Indirect Self Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Indirect self harm definition and associated examples  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Indirect Self Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Indirect self harm definition and associated examples</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #self #harm #indirect #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p><strong>Indirect self-harm</strong> &#40;ISH&#41; are non-suicidal actions that individuals take to physically mistreat or abuse themselves. It does not immediately lead to direct bodily damage &#91;1&#93;. Examples of ISH are eating disorders, remaining in physically abusive relationships, extended abuse of substances, and flippant behavior &#91;1&#93;.</p>
<p>Indirect self-harm &#40;ISH&#41; is conceptually different from <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm.md">direct self-harm</a> &#40;DSH&#41;. Generally, ISH is an expression of centering oneself. It is a way to control one&#39;s feelings or to exact punishment. &#91;2&#93; As such, ISH can be a coping mechanism to handle emotional anguish, rage and frustration. &#91;1&#93; Some use it as a means to lower tension &#91;3&#93;.</p>
<p>Eating disorders have the highest mortality rate of all mental illnesses. &#91;4&#93; For women aged 15-24, mortality rates related to Anorexia are 12 times greater than other mortality rates. &#91;5&#93; As such, the eating disorder community is generally the most prolific indirect self-harm community. A majority of the literature about  indirect self-harm literature is centered around it &#91;6&#93;–&#91;9&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. A. S. Germain and J. M. Hooley, “Direct and indirect forms of non-suicidal self-injury: Evidence for a distinction,” Psychiatry Res., vol. 197, no. 1–2, pp. 78–84, 2012.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; D. Owens, J. Horrocks, and A. House, “Fatal and non-fatal repetition of self-harm: Systematic review,” Br. J. Psychiatry, vol. 181, no. 3, pp. 193–199, 2002.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; K. L. Gratz, “Measurement of deliberate self-harm: Preliminary data on the Deliberate Self-Harm Inventory,” J. Psychopathol. Behav. Assess., vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 253–263, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; P. F. Sullivan et al., “Mortality in anorexia nervosa,” Am. J. Psychiatry, vol. 152, no. 7, pp. 1073–1074, 1995.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; F. R. Smink, D. Van Hoeken, and H. W. Hoek, “Epidemiology of eating disorders: Incidence, prevalence and mortality rates,” Curr. Psychiatry Rep., vol. 14, no. 4, pp. 406–414, 2012.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; P. A. Adler and P. Adler, “Self-injurers as loners: The social organization of solitary deviance,” Deviant Behav., vol. 26, no. 4, pp. 345–378, 2005.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; S. R. Brotsky and D. Giles, “Inside the ‘pro-ana’ community: A covert online participant observation,” Eat. Disord., vol. 15, no. 2, pp. 93–109, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; R. A. Fleming-May and L. E. Miller, “‘I’m scared to look. But I’m dying to know’: Information seeking and sharing on Pro-Ana weblogs,” Proc. Am. Soc. Inf. Sci. Technol., vol. 47, no. 1, pp. 1–9, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;9&#93; L. R. Shade, “Weborexics: The ethical issues surrounding pro-ana websites,” Acm Sigcas Comput. Soc., vol. 33, no. 4, p. 2, 2003.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Direct Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Direct Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #direct #self #harm ##mentalhealth #illness #mental #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Direct self-harm is defined as the deliberate, direct destruction or alteration of body tissue without conscious suicidal intent, but resulting in injury severe enough for tissue damage to occur &#91;1&#93;. </p>
<p>Examples are of Direct Self Harm are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cutting, burning, scratching, and hitting of oneself &#91;2&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Skin bleaching &#91;3&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hair-pulling &#91;4&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ingesting hazardous chemicals &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The term &quot;direct self-harm&quot; is often used interchangeably with the terms self-injury &#91;6&#93;, self-mutilation &#91;7&#93;, and self-wounding &#91;8&#93;. Despite the exact wording, the distinction of direct self-harm is that it is non-suicidal but does cause direct injury to the body.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; A. R. Favazza, “The coming of age of self-mutilation,” J. Nerv. Ment. Dis., vol. 186, no. 5, pp. 259–268, 1998.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; B. Møhl, P. La Cour, and A. Skandsen, “Non-suicidal self-injury and indirect self-harm among Danish high school students,” Scand. J. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry Psychol., vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 11–18, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; C. A. Charles, “Skin bleaching, self-hate, and black identity in Jamaica,” J. Black Stud., vol. 33, no. 6, pp. 711–728, 2003.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; B. A. Iwata, M. F. Dorsey, K. J. Slifer, K. E. Bauman, and G. S. Richman, “Toward a functional analysis of self-injury,” J. Appl. Behav. Anal., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 197–209, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; K. L. Gratz, “Measurement of deliberate self-harm: Preliminary data on the Deliberate Self-Harm Inventory,” J. Psychopathol. Behav. Assess., vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 253–263, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; E. D. Klonsky, “The functions of deliberate self-injury: A review of the evidence,” Clin. Psychol. Rev., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 226–239, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; A. R. Favazza and R. J. Rosenthal, “Diagnostic issues in self-mutilation,” Psychiatr. Serv., vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 134–140, 1993.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; D. Tantam and J. Whittaker, “Personality disorder and self-wounding,” Br. J. Psychiatry, vol. 161, no. 4, pp. 451–464, 1992.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What is Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Exploration of the idea of Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What is Digital Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Exploration of the idea of Digital Self-Harm</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #harm #digital #non-suicidal #self #mentalhealth #illness #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Digital Self Harm is any online communication and activity that leads to, supports, or exacerbates non-suicidal yet intentional harm or impairment of an individual’s physical wellbeing. It includes consuming and generating online content. Digital self-harm occurs when a person’s behaviors are negatively influenced through his or her online activities in such a manner that these online activities lead to the infliction of non-suicidal direct or indirect physical harm to oneself. </p>
<p>Digital self-harm is believed to be growing at a rate that will not stop without check. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Defining Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on what is digital self harm  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Defining Digital Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on what is digital self harm</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #self #harm #online #digital #suicide #mentalhealth #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. Pater and E. Mynatt, &quot;Defining Digital Self-Harm,&quot; in Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing, Portland Oregon USA, Feb. 2017, pp. 1501–1513, doi: 10.1145/2998181.2998224.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Examples of Digital Self-Harm</li><li>Problems with the Internet</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This paper aims to define what digital self-harm is.</p>
<p>Digital self harm: online communication and activity that leads to, supports, or exacerbates non-suicidal yet intentional harm or impairment of an individual’s physical wellbeing.  It includes consuming and generating online content.  Digital self-harm occurs when a person’s behaviors are negatively influenced through his or her online activities in such a manner that these online activities lead to the infliction of non-suicidal direct or indirect physical harm to oneself. </p>
<p>Traditionally, eating disorder treatments generally include individual and family therapy or group therapy. Interpersonal and cultural forces that sustain self-harm activities are scrutinized.</p>
<p>As a field, CSCW and HCI health research appears to unconsciously emphasize the positive health benefits of technology &#91;1&#93;–&#91;3&#93;.  This unaddressed bias can have great consequences on platform design and policy and must be scrutinized.</p>
<p>Digital self-harm is believed to be growing at a rate that will not stop without check. &#91;4&#93;</p>
<h3 id="examples_of_digital_self-harm">Examples of Digital Self-Harm</h3>
<p>Pro-anorexic digital self-harm example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>IF YOU WANT TO LOSE WEIGHT, GO ON A DIET FATTY.  ONE IS EITHER ANA/MIA OR NOT. IT IS A GIFT AND YOU CANNOT DECIDE TO HAVE AN EATING DISORDER. SO IF YOU ARE LOOKING FOR A WAY TO LOSE WEIGHT, S-S-S-S-SORRY JUNIOR&#33;&#33; MOVE ON, TRY JENNY CRAIG</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Two different ways the language around cutting is used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Normalizing behavior: attempts in legitimizing activities to deal with mental health issues</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pathologizing behavior: focuses on a bodily disgust with the behavior being wrong morally.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="problems_with_the_internet">Problems with the Internet</h3>
<p>The internet creates an environment for reinforced strengthening of behavioral issues within an affected individual through encouragement of destructive behaviors. This sort of cybernetic reinforcement mechanism could lead to the fast and serious manifestations of underlying disease symptoms.</p>
<p>ED websites may have contagion-like effects on individuals investigating eating disorders prior to exhibiting any commitment to a disorder. &#91;5&#93; Regarding adolescents, a concern is a healthy desire for weight-loss could lead to unintended exposure of ED content.</p>
<p><em>QUESTION: I wonder if there is a corollary definition about unintentional digital self-harm? People who are not necessarily interested in self-harm, but come into it anyways.</em></p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; M. De Choudhury, M. R. Morris, and R. W. White, “Seeking and sharing health information online: Comparing search engines and social media,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 1365–1376.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; J. Huh and W. Pratt, “Weaving clinical expertise in online health communities,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 1355–1364.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. L. Jacobs, J. Clawson, and E. D. Mynatt, “My journey compass: A preliminary investigation of a mobile tool for cancer patients,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 663–672.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; D. L. Borzekowski, S. Schenk, J. L. Wilson, and R. Peebles, “E-Ana and e-Mia: A content analysis of pro–eating disorder web sites,” Am. J. Public Health, vol. 100, no. 8, pp. 1526–1534, 2010.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #harm #self #suicide #mentalhealth #illness #hurting #pain ##summary #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>In 2014, WHO found that 20&#37; of children aged 15 confirmed having self-harmed within the last year. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<p>Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself. &#91;2&#93; Examples include restrictive and binge eating, cutting, hitting, scratching, burning, bleaching of an individual’s body, and other forms of self-mutilation. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Self-harm generally pertains to non-life threatening actions individuals perform to negatively impact their health. This starts with actions like cutting and wrist slashing. &#91;4&#93; It can then lead to more severe acts of injuring human body tissue &#91;5&#93; and to <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm.md">indirect self-harming behavior</a> such as eating disorders &#91;6&#93;</p>
<p>There are many types of self-harming behavior such as:</p>
<ol>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm.md">Indirect Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm.md">Direct Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm.md">Digital Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Further complicating discrete categories is that not all people that self-harm are <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020192840-suicide.md">suicidal</a>. &#91;7&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; E. D. Klonsky, “The functions of deliberate self-injury: A review of the evidence,” Clin. Psychol. Rev., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 226–239, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. K. Nock, “Self-injury,” Annu. Rev. Clin. Psychol., vol. 6, pp. 339–363, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; H. Graff and R. Mallin, “The syndrome of the wrist cutter,” Am. J. Psychiatry, vol. 124, no. 1, pp. 36–42, 1967.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; E. D. Klonsky, T. F. Oltmanns, and E. Turkheimer, “Deliberate self-harm in a nonclinical population: Prevalence and psychological correlates,” Am. J. Psychiatry, vol. 160, no. 8, pp. 1501–1508, 2003.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; C. Zlotnick, J. I. Mattia, and M. Zimmerman, “Clinical correlates of self-mutilation in a sample of general psychiatric patients,” J. Nerv. Ment. Dis., vol. 187, no. 5, pp. 296–301, 1999.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; J. Quigley, S. Rasmussen, and J. Mcalaney, “Normative misperceptions of suicidal and self-harming behaviours in an undergraduate student population,” 2014.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Underestimating Digital Media Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020221842-digital-media/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020221842-digital-media/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Twenge&#39;s critique of modern day assessment of the negative impacts of social media on adolescents.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Underestimating Digital Media Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 25 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Twenge&#39;s critique of modern day assessment of the negative impacts of social media on adolescents.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #harm #depression #social #media #factors #mental #illness ##health #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The consideration of only monotonic effects were accounted. Relationships between digital media use and health are generally non-monotonic. Associations often follow a J-shaped curve. The first issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski. This is nicknamed the Goldilocks hypothesis which was posited by Przybylski himself. &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4. &#91;1&#93; A. K. Przybylski and N. Weinstein, &quot;A large-scale test of the goldilocks hypothesis: quantifying the relations between digital-screen use and the mental well-being of adolescents,&quot; Psychological Science, vol. 28, no. 2, pp. 204–215, 2017.</p>
<p>The global adolescent mental health crisis started around 2012 and greatly affects girls more so than boys &#91;5&#93;. As TV is now commonplace and TV watching amongst adolescents has declined after 2012 &#91;6&#93;, TV watching does not suggest an adequate explanation for the sudden increase in mental health disorders. The second issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4. &#91;5&#93; S. McManus et al., &quot;Prevalence of non-suicidal self-harm and service contact in England, 2000–14: repeated cross-sectional surveys of the general population,&quot; The lancet psychiatry, vol. 6, no. 7, pp. 573–581, 2019. &#91;6&#93; J. M. Twenge, G. N. Martin, and B. H. Spitzberg, &quot;Trends in US Adolescents’ media use, 1976–2016: The rise of digital media, the decline of TV, and the &#40;near&#41; demise of print.,&quot; Psychology of Popular Media Culture, vol. 8, no. 4, p. 329, 2019.</p>
<p>The Monitoring the Future dataset examines digital media usage via two ways. </p>
<ol>
<li><p>A minimal variance scale with labels that range from &quot;never&quot; to &quot;almost every day.&quot;</p>
</li>
<li><p>A sufficiently varied count of weekly hours spent on digital media.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>However, Orben and Przybylski only included low-variance items. The fourth issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski. &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4. &#91;1&#93; J. E. Schulenberg, L. D. Johnston, P. M. O’Malley, J. G. Bachman, R. A. Miech, and M. E. Patrick, &quot;Monitoring the Future national survey results on drug use, 1975-2016: Volume II, College students and adults ages 19-55,&quot; 2017.</p>
<p>Including controls that could in fact be mediators. The fifth issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski. Orben and Przybylski control for factors such as negative attitudes towards school, time spent with parents, parent distress and closeness to parents, which could be caused by heavy social media use. &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4.</p>
<p>Using \(r^{2}\) for effect size has multiple problems. The sixth issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski. &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4. &#91;1&#93; C. J. Ferguson, &quot;An effect size primer: a guide for clinicians and researchers.,&quot; 2016. &#91;2&#93; D. C. Funder and D. J. Ozer, &quot;Evaluating effect size in psychological research: Sense and nonsense,&quot; Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science, vol. 2, no. 2, pp. 156–168, 2019.</p>
<p>Heavy use of social media is regularly correlated with negative mental health outcomes of varying severity. This relationship disproportionately affects girls. Given that there is no plausible alternative explanation for this association, associations with a variety of adverse mental health conditions in girls should not be dismissed. Adverse events being rising rates of anxiety, depression, self-harm and suicide &#91;0&#93; J. M. Twenge, J. Haidt, T. E. Joiner, and W. K. Campbell, &quot;Underestimating digital media harm,&quot; Nat Hum Behav, vol. 4, no. 4, pp. 346–348, Apr. 2020, doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0839-4. &#91;1&#93; S. McManus et al., &quot;Prevalence of non-suicidal self-harm and service contact in England, 2000–14: repeated cross-sectional surveys of the general population,&quot; The lancet psychiatry, vol. 6, no. 7, pp. 573–581, &#91;1&#93; &#91;2&#93; J. M. Twenge, &quot;Why increases in adolescent depression may be linked to the technological environment,&quot; Current opinion in psychology, vol. 32, pp. 89–94, 2020.2019.</p>
<p>Effect sizes include many individual items. These are lower in internal reliability than multiple-item scales and thus produce lower effect sizes. Scales with more items count more heavily in the analysis because they have more items. &#91;1&#93; L. J. Cronbach and P. E. Meehl, &quot;Construct validity in psychological tests.,&quot; Psychological bulletin, vol. 52, no. 4, p. 281, 1955. The third issue raised by Jean Twenge against &quot;The association between adolescent well-being and digital technology use&quot; by Orben and Przybylski</p>
<p>Mediators are a possible reason behind an effect. They should not be controlled. This is from an email conversation with Jean Twenge about this issue. For example, it is plausible that excessive social media use causes teens to spend less time with their parents. Thus this variable should not be a covariate, as it might partially explain why the correlation between social media use and depression occurs in the first place. </p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>