<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  The Open Knowledge Model  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/04172022033744-open-knowledge-standard/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/04172022033744-open-knowledge-standard/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A working proposal on a standard knowledge format for taking notes  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>The Open Knowledge Model</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> April 16 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A working proposal on a standard knowledge format for taking notes</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #open #knowledge #standard ##summary #format #blog #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Model Components</li><li>Digressions and Recommendations for Model<ol><li>Title Block</li><li>Bibliography Block</li><li>Notes</li><li>References</li></ol></li><li>Implementation Examples</li><li>Tools for Working with Model</li><li>Conclusion</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>Knowledge is one of the most nebulous ideas known to mankind since nearly the beginning of time. What may be knowledge to one person may be useless noise to another - this encapsulates the difficulty in defining knowledge. As a result of its many possible meanings, I put forth a rather opinionated proposal for what I term the &quot;Open Knowledge Model&quot;.</p>
<p>The Open Knowledge Model is a standard that defines not how to maintain knowledge in what are typically coined &quot;knowledge management systems&quot;. Instead, its focus is on how to structure information that goes directly into such systems. It is fully compatible with the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://www.iso.org/standard/68683.html">ISO 30401</a> standard.</p>
<p>There are many different knowledge management systems available to someone – from a pen and pencil to various software offerings. Each of these offerings are very unique and accordingly offer benefits and cons. This model remains independent of any such offering but instead prescribes a model to structure information in any of the offerings one chooses to pursue.</p>
<h3 id="model_components">Model Components</h3>
<p>The model is composed of the following sections:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Title Block</strong> - this is a unique block that begins with the name of the note followed by three required subcomponents:</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Date** - the date the note was created
- **Summary** - a brief, single sentence summary of what this note is about
- **Keywords** - keywords that can be used to find or associated with the content of this note</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Bibliography Block</strong> - this contains the bibliographic information that is associated with the specific note</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Notes</strong> - where one&#39;s notes go on the note subject in whatever format one so chooses</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>References</strong> - list of references used in the note</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>And that is the core requirement of the model.  What follows are a few digressions on this model. </p>
<h3 id="digressions_and_recommendations_for_model">Digressions and Recommendations for Model</h3>
<h4 id="title_block">Title Block</h4>
<p>It is recommended that for <strong>Date</strong>, one chooses a consistent convention for how one will record the date across their knowledge base using this model.  In practice, there can be as many <strong>Keywords</strong> as one chooses, but it is often better to be more concise in what you choose as words.</p>
<h4 id="bibliography_block">Bibliography Block</h4>
<p>It can be possible that there isn&#39;t one bibliography associated with this not or none at all.  In those situations, it makes sense to perhaps write something like: &quot;Not Available&quot;.</p>
<h4 id="notes">Notes</h4>
<p>This is the most critical piece to any note.  One can structure and write their notes in any way they please here.  Include images, diagrams, code snippets – anything your knowledge management system supports. The model imposes no specific structure here – implementations may differ.</p>
<h4 id="references">References</h4>
<p>It is recommended to never write down the references section manually. Instead, offload this to a third party reference manager or another tool that could generate this information from a given note. </p>
<h3 id="implementation_examples">Implementation Examples</h3>
<p>To give an example of implementations, here are some examples of implementations:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/08032021134232-notes-template.md">Markdown Implementation</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="tools_for_working_with_model">Tools for Working with Model</h3>
<p>Here are a list of some tools that have emerged to work with the Open Knowledge Model: </p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://github.com/TheCedarPrince/NoteMate">NoteMate.jl</a> - a companion for working with a knowledge management system that adheres to the Open Knowledge Model.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Written in Julia and offers parsing from Markdown notes to other target formats.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>This standard is an active work in progress and is the product of years of experimentation.  If you find problems with this model or believe it too restrictive or unwise, please comment in the discussion or reach out to me. My hope is that this standard will co-evolve with new tools and increase the utility of any person&#39;s knowledge management system.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>The Open Knowledge Model</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/04172022033744-open-knowledge-standard">https://jacobzelko.com/04172022033744-open-knowledge-standard</a>. April 16 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  As We May Think  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01112021180936-we-may-think/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01112021180936-we-may-think/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on Vannevar Bush&#39;s concept of a memex and additional thoughts on the issue of information overload  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>As We May Think</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 11 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on Vannevar Bush&#39;s concept of a memex and additional thoughts on the issue of information overload</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #memex #thinking #knowledge #management #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>V. Bush and others, &quot;As we may think,&quot; The Atlantic monthly, vol. 176, no. 1, pp. 101–108, 1945.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>The Failure of the Publication Machine</li><li>The idea of Automated Knowledge Systems</li><li>Regarding Thought</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="the_failure_of_the_publication_machine">The Failure of the Publication Machine</h3>
<p>Publication has been extended beyond usefulness of the record. Current methods for finding relevant information is impractical.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: Very convicting retrospection on how we handle copious amounts of information. A record which contains too little information is not informative and one that contains too much is overwhelming.</em></p>
<p>Those who try to stay current with research may have difficulty to recall last month&#39;s material studied.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: This is so convicting&#33; Even though it is a nearly 80 year old paper, the problems that he discusses are still in existence&#33;  The problem of having too many papers and the inability to extract the truly worthwhile pieces of information are still present.</em></p>
<h3 id="the_idea_of_automated_knowledge_systems">The idea of Automated Knowledge Systems</h3>
<p>When one associates information along logical processes, creativity is limited to data selection to match a process. After this initial surge of creativity, the work is fit for automation</p>
<h3 id="regarding_thought">Regarding Thought</h3>
<p>There exist no substitute for nuanced thinking. Imagination and repetitious thinking are diverse. Repetitive thought is much easier automated.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: I like this notion of repetitive thought. As much as there are repetitive thought, there are repetitive actions accordingly.</em></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>As We May Think</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01112021180936-we-may-think">https://jacobzelko.com/01112021180936-we-may-think</a>. January 11 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Famous Quotes  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07222020181007-famous-quotes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07222020181007-famous-quotes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A collection of favorite quotes from books and people.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Famous Quotes</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 22 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A collection of favorite quotes from books and people.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #knowledge #quotes #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Quotes Regarding Knowledge</li><li>Quotes Regarding Books</li><li>Quotes Regarding Fame</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="quotes_regarding_knowledge">Quotes Regarding Knowledge</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;There are known knowns; there are things we know that we know. There are known unknowns; that is to say, there are things that we now know we don’t know. But there are also unknown unknowns — there are things we do not know we don’t know.&quot; - Secretary of State, Donald Rumsfeld</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.&quot; - Sherlock Holmes, Sir Arthur Conan Doyle</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An inductive approach to knowledge that Sherlock Holmes takes to solve puzzles and problems.</p>
<h3 id="quotes_regarding_books">Quotes Regarding Books</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Dorian Gray had been poisoned by a book&quot; - Oscar Wilde, <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/04202022021854-picture-dorian-gray.md">The Picture of Dorian Gray</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This quote gets at how the influence of a book can corrupt an individual or push someone further to corruption. In Gray&#39;s case, he was already corrupted but the book further pushed him beyond what evil he was already capable of pursuing.</p>
<h3 id="quotes_regarding_fame">Quotes Regarding Fame</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;For there is only one thing in the world worse than being talked about, and that is not being talked about.&quot; - Oscar Wilde, <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/04202022021854-picture-dorian-gray.md">The Picture of Dorian Gray</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When you attain fame, at least you are talked about – whether positively or negatively. But to not be talked about means no one even knows who you are.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Famous Quotes</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07222020181007-famous-quotes">https://jacobzelko.com/07222020181007-famous-quotes</a>. July 22 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  False Expertise  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07132020022756-media-timothy/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07132020022756-media-timothy/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How Timothy speaks truth to today about false expertise abounding from social media  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>False Expertise</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How Timothy speaks truth to today about false expertise abounding from social media</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #social #media #polarization #knowledge #1timothy #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<blockquote>
<p>As I urged you when I went into Macedonia, stay there in Ephesus so that you may command certain people not to teach false doctrines any longer or to devote themselves to myths and endless genealogies. Such things promote controversial speculations rather than advancing God’s work — which is by faith. The goal of this command is love, which comes from a pure heart and a good conscience and a sincere faith. Some have departed from these and have turned to meaningless talk. They want to be teachers of the law, but they do not know what they are talking about or what they so confidently affirm.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><p>1 Timothy 1:3 - 7</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I was reading this passage in 1 Timothy and was thinking about how it very much relates to one of the current issues being faced in the world. Social media&#39;s negative impact on individuals. Particularly the parallels drawn between Paul&#39;s letter and today are very much talking about the same thing. People being drawn away to nonsensical things that are not useful to life. Or, worse, becoming supposed &quot;experts&quot; in fields that they truly know nothing about but have heard enough <em>things</em> to give them the impression of having learned something.</p>
<p>And Paul very explicitly calls these people out by saying they do not know anything. Furthermore, Paul states how these sort of meaningless discussions only promote controversial speculations rather than actually pushing us forward to a meaningful goal. This is very much a problem being faced in today&#39;s society where social media is being used to promote narratives or stories as a means of information but in reality, does not deliver on anything. Furthermore, the polarization that comes from such negative discussion is almost exactly the same as Paul is describing. The only real difference may be how this is impacting so many more individuals than in the past, but the same problems persist: polarization, false impressions of expertise, and endless arguments or quabbling. </p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>False Expertise</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07132020022756-media-timothy">https://jacobzelko.com/07132020022756-media-timothy</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Incremental Reading  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05092020053727-incremental-reading/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05092020053727-incremental-reading/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of the process of incremental reading  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Incremental Reading</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 9 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of the process of incremental reading</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #incremental #reading ##knowledge ##technique #generation #interleaving #breaks #brief #attention #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li><strong>Footnotes:</strong></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Incremental reading follows the general format. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Identify written pieces of interest.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Prioritize the pieces according to personal urgency.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Allocate a comfortable reading time duration per piece with a timed, short break in-between. <sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup></p>
</li>
<li><p>While reading each piece, annotate material that is of interest or difficult to process.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Transfer annotations from each piece to an index card representation &#40;actual or digital&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pause reading and review collected annotations using a <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems.md">spaced repetition system</a>.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Once annotations have been thoroughly revised and reviewed, repeat from step 2 until finished with pieces over the next several days.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Incremental reading helps with improving focus and promotes learning while moving uniformly to finish reading. <sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> &#91;2&#93;, &#91;3&#93; Ingesting raw annotations into a spaced repetition system enables one to process them without being overwhelmed. On each repetition of a particular annotation, rewriting or modifying that information is crucial in cementing understanding. <sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup> After finishing revisions and reviews, this process is repeated until done with reading the pieces.</p>
<h3 id="footnotes"><strong>Footnotes:</strong></h3>
<p><sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> Ariga and Lleras demonstrated that attention on a particular task can be extended via brief and uncommon respites of a controlled nature. <a href="&#91;Click for more details&#93;&#40;/06052020031214-brief-breaks.md&#41;">4</a></p>
<p><sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> It is suggested that interleaving material forces one to differentiate between different topics. When pressured under practice, this can heighten one&#39;s perception about differentiators. It leads to better embedding of concept abstractions that foster retention and transfer. &#91;2&#93;, <a href="&#91;Click for more details&#93;&#40;/05252020211350-hard-on-self.md&#41;">3</a></p>
<p><sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup> Generating an explanation about a topic rather than just being given a solution can be more effective than the spacing effect. This is called the generation effect. <a href="&#91;Click for more details&#93;&#40;/05252020211350-hard-on-self.md&#41;">2</a></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Incremental Reading</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05092020053727-incremental-reading">https://jacobzelko.com/05092020053727-incremental-reading</a>. May 9 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; Master How To Learn, “Demonstration: My Workflow of Incremental Reading,” 09-Dec-2018. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www.masterhowtolearn.com/2018-12-09-demonstration-my-workflow-of-incremental-reading/. &#91;Accessed: 19-May-2020&#93;.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, et al., “Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,” Psychol. Real World Essays Illus. Fundam. Contrib. Soc., vol. 2, no. 59–68, 2011.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; J. B. Shea and R. L. Morgan, “Contextual interference effects on the acquisition, retention, and transfer of a motor skill.” J. Exp. Psychol. &#91;Hum. Learn.&#93;, vol. 5, no. 2, p. 179, 1979.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; A. Ariga and A. Lleras, “Brief and rare mental ‘breaks’ keep you focused: Deactivation and reactivation of task goals preempt vigilance decrements,” Cognition, vol. 118, no. 3, pp. 439–443, Mar. 2011, doi: 10.1016/j.cognition.2010.12.007.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 30 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #zettelkasten #information #knowledge #criteria #questions #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Selecting Information for a Zettel</li><li>Zettel Creation</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="selecting_information_for_a_zettel">Selecting Information for a Zettel</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Does this not add to the overall nature of the Zettelkasten? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>What sort of topics could this open in the Zettelkasten? Are these topics you are willing to invest into? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Where does this new note possibly fit into in the rest of the conversation with your Zettelkasten? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Can this information be added to an already existing Zettel or theme? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="zettel_creation">Zettel Creation</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Do you have enough information do write a new zettel?&#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Do you understand the information enough in the zettel you are creating? &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Each Zettel should fit onto a screen.  &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria">https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria</a>. March 30 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers. 2017.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  How to Take Smart Notes  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Takeaways from the book How to Take Smart Notes  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>How to Take Smart Notes</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 29 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Takeaways from the book How to Take Smart Notes</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #knowledge #notetaking #zettelkasten #mentalmodels #writing #blog #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Quotes from the Book:</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This was overall a book on knowledge management – in particular, how to take, digest, and use the notes we make while reading material, listening to lectures, or absorb knowledge in general. Sonke Ahrens, the author of the book, also gave a rather in-depth overview of the Zettelkasten method created by sociologist Niklas Luhmann. I found the book useful in giving legitimately very good advice on note-taking, great anecdotes to illustrate his point, and also assistance on using the Zettelkasten method. </p>
<p>Furthermore, Ahrens made an interesting point saying that if you are approaching writing where you start with just a blank page, you are missing the point. When you approach a blank page, it <em>ought</em> not feel blank but rather the place to put your notes and ideas together that you have been collecting about a particular topic. Ahrens believes that fundamental teachings about how to write long-form papers are wrong in that they do not start with the most crucial aspect of the writing process – free form thought. And free form thought, when investigating a topic, is best captured using a global sort of note taking method like the Zettelkasten.</p>
<h3 id="quotes_from_the_book">Quotes from the Book:</h3>
<pre><code class="language-julia">&quot;Every intellectual endeavour starts with a note&quot; &#91;pg 8&#93;&quot;We only write if it helps us with our own thinking.&quot; &#91;pg 101&#93;</code></pre>
<p>These two quotes get at the idea that when we write and create notes, we are not only creating notes but also playing with ideas and digesting them into our minds.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes">https://jacobzelko.com/03292020180520-smart-notes</a>. March 29 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What are Mental Models?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020221326-what-mental-models/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03292020221326-what-mental-models/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A brief synopsis on what mental models are  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What are Mental Models?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 29 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A brief synopsis on what mental models are</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #mentalmodels #structure #thinking #knowledge  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Mental models are provide you with patterns of thinking. To paraphrase the author, Sonke Ahrens, in his book, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, well-crafted structures &#40;in our case mental models&#41; are things you can trust as it works in the background to manage everything that prevents you from getting to what is of most importance &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What are Mental Models?</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03292020221326-what-mental-models">https://jacobzelko.com/03292020221326-what-mental-models</a>. March 29 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers. 2017.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Education as a Spectrum  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The idea that there is no clear delineation of knowledge in reality.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Education as a Spectrum</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 9 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The idea that there is no clear delineation of knowledge in reality.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #education #knowledge #science #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Kuhnian Reasoning on Non-Linearity of Education</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>My best friend Wesley Samples believes that education – and for that matter, knowledge – falls more along a spectrum than in discrete categories &#40;such as Mathematics and Biology&#41;. One can look at biology and find the idea of the golden ratio repeated across nature &#91;1&#93;, &#91;2&#93;; example being the <em>Aeonium Tabuliforme</em>:</p>
<p><img src="https://jacobzelko.com/03102020015817-aeonium-tabuliforme.jpg" alt="saucer plant" /></p>
<p>There is the idea of the creature being a biological entity motivating questions such as</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Why does the Nautilus have a shell like this?</p>
</li>
<li><p>What function does it serve?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="kuhnian_reasoning_on_non-linearity_of_education">Kuhnian Reasoning on Non-Linearity of Education</h3>
<p>Beyond Kuhn&#39;s general <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05152022174848-structure-revolutions.md">musing in the _Structure of Scientific Revolutions</a>, his thought can also be linked to the notion that science and education is not linear.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Education as a Spectrum</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum">https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum</a>. March 9 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; Golden ratio discovered in a quantum world. Eurekalert.org, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; R. Padovan, “Proportion: Science, Philosophy, Architecture,” Nexus Netw. J., vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 113–122, 2002, doi: 10.1007/s00004-001-0008-7.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>