<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> June 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #spacing #effect #critique #education #system #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>F. N. Dempster, &quot;A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research,&quot; American Psychologist, p. 8, 1988.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</li><li>Miscellaneous Concepts</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="issues_regarding_the_adoption_of_the_spacing_effect_into_classroom_settings">Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been studied in recent years</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is still relatively new</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect does not have any thing to do with current issues educators face.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has yet to be shown well in school activities.</p>
</li>
<li><p>There are gaps in literature about the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>School-based studies do not show the spacing effect.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been well demonstrated in a classroom setting</p>
</li>
<li><p>Not enough is known about practical class implementation to warrant application of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is not well comprehended</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the most concerning issues concerning usage of the spacing effect:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Ahistorical character of research on the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>Some failures to obtain the effect with school-like activities</p>
</li>
<li><p>Paucity of impressive classroom demonstrations of the phenomenon</p>
</li>
<li><p>Limited knowledge of classroom practice</p>
</li>
<li><p>Incomplete understanding of the psychological bases of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Probably the most legitimate barrier to utilization of the spacing effect in educational settings is the scarcity of in class demonstrations of its usage.</strong></p>
<p>However, these four issues are not considered as such strong impediments to the implementation of the spacing effect in classroom settings:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Is not new and has been studied</p>
</li>
<li><p>Continues to receive recent documentation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Can assist in addressing educational issues</p>
</li>
<li><p>Is demonstrated to lend itself well to school-like activities</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="miscellaneous_concepts">Miscellaneous Concepts</h3>
<p><strong>Lag effects</strong> are believed to occur when performance on a memory task improves as the number of intervening items between successive presentations increases.</p>
<p><strong>Jost&#39;s Law:</strong> If two memories are equal in how well they were learned but at differing times, the older memory will gain more out of a review than the new one. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique">https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique</a>. June 8 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. A. McGeoch, “The psychology of human learning.” 1942.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Spacing Effect  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A summary of the spacing effect  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Spacing Effect</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 28 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A summary of the spacing effect</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #spacing #effect  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Associated terminology:<ol><li>Footnotes:</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The spacing effect accounts for the fact that learning is improved when studying is spread out over time. It was first discovered and described by Hermann Ebbinghaus during 1880 - 1885. &#91;1&#93; His findings were later accurately reproduced and documented by <em>Murre &amp; Dros</em>. &#91;2&#93; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020172154-replication-ebbinghaus.md">&#40;Click for results of that study here&#41;</a></p>
<p>The spacing effect has not been very well utilized in US-based education institutes despite its multitudinous benefits. &#91;3&#93; Cepeda et al. determined that in a memory based challenge, spaced based learning outperformed massed learning ~96&#37; of the time. &#91;4&#93; This coincides with the deficient processing view posited by Hintzman that stated how massed repetition leads to a lack of attention in later reviews. &#91;5&#93;</p>
<p>According to <em>Pyc and Rawson</em>, labored but correct recall while practicing improves memory. Spacing items of recall produce greater effort during retrieval and enables thorough conversion of the item to memory. <sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> &#91;6&#93; Semantic processing of information during repetitions assists in making that information more <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03172020033742-antifragility.md">anti-fragile, to borrow from Nassim Taleb,</a> during reviews. This causes performance in later memory testing to be unaffected by changes in such things like the type of font used when presented information. <sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> &#91;7&#93; </p>
<p>However, a confounding factor in the idea of the spacing effect is the encoding variability theory. This theory states that one&#39;s performance on a memory test is related to overlaps amongst current contextualized material both during testing and while encoding. According to this view, spaced repetition typically entails some variability in presentation contexts. Yet, this results in a positive outcome being that there are then more retrieval cues associated with that material. &#91;8&#93;</p>
<p>However, there are concerns about the spacing effect that have impeded its overall adoption into educational formats. <em>Dempster</em> made a case examining potential rationales for the lack of adoption in a review of the current state of the spacing effect &#40;though the study is old over 30 years old, it still remains that education systems do not incorporate the spacing effect&#41;. &#91;3&#93; His biggest point of concern was the lack of studies that showed effective classroom utilization of the method.</p>
<p>Despite such misgivings, it is still a phenomenon that have given rise to many benefits and potential applications for at least personal education. Principle of which is in the form of<a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems.md">spaced repetition systems.</a> These systems have determined the best spacing algorithms for a learner to use the spacing effect to assist in learning diverse educational material.</p>
<h3 id="associated_terminology">Associated terminology:</h3>
<p>Lag: the length of time between learning repetitions. &#91;9&#93;</p>
<h4 id="footnotes">Footnotes:</h4>
<p><sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> This is known as the retrieval effort hypothesis.</p>
<p><sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> Short-term perceptual priming is the mechanism that supports the spacing effects in cued-memory tasks when <em>unfamiliar</em> stimuli are used as targets. </p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Spacing Effect</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect">https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect</a>. May 28 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; H. Ebbinghaus, “Ueber das gedächtnis,” 1885.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; J. M. J. Murre and J. Dros, “Replication and Analysis of Ebbinghaus’ Forgetting Curve,” PLoS ONE, vol. 10, no. 7, p. e0120644, Jul. 2015, doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0120644.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; F. N. Dempster, “A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research,” Am. Psychol., p. 8, 1988.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; N. J. Cepeda, H. Pashler, E. Vul, J. T. Wixted, and D. Rohrer, “Distributed practice in verbal recall tasks: A review and quantitative synthesis.” Psychol. Bull., vol. 132, no. 3, p. 354, 2006.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; D. L. Hintzman, “Theoretical implications of the spacing effect.” 1974.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; M. A. Pyc and K. A. Rawson, “Testing the retrieval effort hypothesis: Does greater difficulty correctly recalling information lead to higher levels of memory?” J. Mem. Lang., vol. 60, no. 4, pp. 437–447, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; N. Mammarella, R. Russo, and S. Avons, “Spacing effects in cued-memory tasks for unfamiliar faces and nonwords,” Mem. Cognit., vol. 30, no. 8, pp. 1238–1251, 2002.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; S. M. Cormier, Basic processes of learning, cognition, and motivation. Psychology Press, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;9&#93; M. J. Kahana and M. W. Howard, “Spacing and lag effects in free recall of pure lists,” Psychon. Bull. Rev., vol. 12, no. 1, pp. 159–164, 2005.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How increasing difficulties in learning can increase better long-term learning. Examples included.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 25 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How increasing difficulties in learning can increase better long-term learning. Examples included.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography ##finish #performance #learning #forgetting #retrieval #strength #storage #generation #effect #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, and others, &quot;Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,&quot; Psychology and the real world: Essays illustrating fundamental contributions to society, vol. 2, no. 59 - 68, 2011.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Difficulties which can encourage learning: </p>
<ol>
<li><p>Varied learning conditions as opposed to constant and predictable ones.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Interleaving instruction on separate topics together.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Spacing study sessions on a given topic.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Using tests as study events. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Learning how to learn is the ultimate survival tool. </p>
<p>Rather do not fret over inputs but rather, output. Consolidate reading material from memory. Get with others to drill one another with questions. Activites that test your ability to generate explications yields more robust learning experiences.</p>
<p>Memory does not function like a video recorder. Reviewing the same material ad nauseam is not effective for memory. Learning involves attaching novel information to what is known by oneself. </p>
<p>Generating an explanation about a topic rather than just being given a solution can be more effective than the spacing effect. This is called the generation effect.</p>
<p>Learning difficulties which are desirable trigger encoding and retrieval processes that support storage strength. If the learner is unable to successfully handle presented difficulties, they become impediments rather than helps to learning.</p>
<p>Retrieval strength explains the ease in accessing a representation of a specific memory in the brain. It is signficantly affected by factors such as cues and recency of exposure to a material related to that representation.</p>
<p>Studying the same material in two different rooms rather the same room leads to increased recall of that material. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>Interleaved practice produces higher quality prolonged retention and promotes skill transferability. In comparison to blocked practice and other sorts of mass practicing. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Blocked practice is deceptive; it is not the best form of learning though it can appear to be so. &#91;3&#93; </p>
<p>It is suggested that interleaving material forces one to differentiate between different topics. When pressured, this can heighten one&#39;s perception about differentiators. It leads to better embedding of abstractions that foster retention and transfer. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Participants in a motor skills test received 18 patterned trials via a pinball-like machine set-up. Participants were presented with randomly determined patterns &#40;interleaved&#41; or individual patterns that were practiced consecutively &#40;blocked&#41; on the machine. Blocked participants quickly improved versus interleaved participants. After a 10 day break, participants retested under blocked or interleaved conditions. Presented random conditions, the original interleaved participants performed superior to the blocked participants. Blocked participants appeared to have learned nothing. Presented blocked conditions, results were approximately the same but the minimal differences favored interleaving. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Testing is seen as a means of quantitative assessment but not for learning purposes. This is in contradiction to the fact that testing can be highly a highly beneficial tool for learning rather than a measurement of learning taking place. </p>
<p>8 and 12 year olds practiced tossing beanbags at a target on the floor while having their vision blocked at each throw. Half of each age group practiced throwing at a fixed distance target. The rest threw at targets of varying distances. After sufficient practices and a break, all children were tested under fixed target conditions for their age group. Children who practiced at variable distances performed better than fixed target participants. Introducing variation outmatched benefits of fixed distance practice. &#91;4&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self">https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self</a>. May 25 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; R. A. Bjork, “Memory and metamemory considerations in the,” Metacognition Knowing Knowing, vol. 185, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; S. M. Smith, A. Glenberg, and R. A. Bjork, “Environmental context and human memory,” Memory &amp; Cognition, vol. 6, no. 4, pp. 342–353, Jul. 1978, doi: 10.3758/BF03197465.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; J. B. Shea and R. L. Morgan, “Contextual interference effects on the acquisition, retention, and transfer of a motor skill.” J. Exp. Psychol. &#91;Hum. Learn.&#93;, vol. 5, no. 2, p. 179, 1979.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; R. Kerr and B. Booth, “Specific and varied practice of motor skill,” Percept. Mot. Skills, vol. 46, no. 2, pp. 395–401, 1978.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Spaced Repetition Systems  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  What are Spaced Repetition Systems and what is available?  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Spaced Repetition Systems</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 25 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> What are Spaced Repetition Systems and what is available?</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #spaced #repetition #system #spacing #effect ##learning #software  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Software Implementations</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>There are multiple algorithms available used for effectively implementing the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect.md">spacing effect</a>. The earliest algorithm comes from the original discoverer of the spacing effect, Hermann Ebbinghaus. The algorithm <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020172154-replication-ebbinghaus.md">has been replicated</a> and scrutinized examined multiple times. &#91;1&#93;–&#91;3&#93; Spaced repetition systems are based around proper implementations of such algorithms.</p>
<p>Before the advent of computers, it was very difficult to implement such a system. The best system to take advantage of this effect was the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system.md">Leitner System which used paper note cards</a> to assist with remembering information. However, this was still a somewhat fragile system and difficult to manage.</p>
<p>With computers, there have been several pieces of software made to automate and keep track of repetitions <em>for a learner</em>. A majority of these systems directly adapted the Leitner System from the analog to the digital world. Each software generally has proprietary algorithms that supposedly maximize the spacing effect but are directly inspired by the original work done by Ebbinghaus.</p>
<p>Whether analog or digital, key features of these systems are as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Uses an algorithm implementation of the spacing effect for a user.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Each piece of information is spaced automatically per a user&#39;s perceived difficulty in either remembering or processing that piece of information on a repetition.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pieces of information are generally presented in a &quot;flashcard&quot; format and are stored in &quot;decks&quot;.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="software_implementations">Software Implementations</h3>
<p>There are many pieces of software that utilize spaced repetition. Provided is a table listing some of the most popular ones:</p>
<table><tr><th align="right">Software</th><th align="right">Description</th><th align="right">Reference</th></tr><tr><td align="right">Anki</td><td align="right">Open source flashcard based learning software.</td><td align="right">@AnkiPowerfulIntelligent</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Duolingo</td><td align="right">Popular language learning platform.</td><td align="right">@LearnLanguageFree</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Memrise</td><td align="right">Flashcard based language learning app.</td><td align="right">@zotero-1378</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Quizlet</td><td align="right">Multi-faceted learning platform.</td><td align="right">@Quizlet</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Supermemo</td><td align="right">Software for spacing and incremental reading.</td><td align="right">@LearnFastForget</td></tr></table>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Spaced Repetition Systems</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems">https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems</a>. May 25 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. M. J. Murre and J. Dros, “Replication and Analysis of Ebbinghaus’ Forgetting Curve,” PLoS ONE, vol. 10, no. 7, p. e0120644, Jul. 2015, doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0120644.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; H. Ebbinghaus, “Ueber das gedächtnis,” 1885.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, et al., “Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,” Psychol. Real World Essays Illus. Fundam. Contrib. Soc., vol. 2, no. 59–68, 2011.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>