<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Composite guide in using spaced repetition systems in learning maths  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 6 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Composite guide in using spaced repetition systems in learning maths</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #math #learning #anki #flashcards #spaced #repetition #proofs #theorems #definitions #project #archive #blog</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Introduction</li><li>Principles in Making Anki Cards for Maths</li><li>Card Types<ol><li>Definitions</li><li>Properties</li><li>Theorems<ol><li>Implication Only Theorems</li><li>Implication and Equivalence Theorems</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>Self Testing</li><li>The &quot;Ankification&quot; of Proofs<ol><li>Initial Glances of a Proof</li><li>Building Out a Conceptual Roadmap of a Proof</li><li>Consider the Alternatives of a Proof</li></ol></li><li>Conclusion</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>A major goal in my life is to get better with studying maths. As I fully intend to study mathematics more rigorously, a powerful component and tool in my studying toolbox has been Spaced Repetition Systems like Anki or Memrise. In particular, I wanted to know how to use these sort of systems to study and retain math more effectively in my studies – which sometimes face unexpected interruptions. This post serves as a guide to do just that.</p>
<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>TODO: Add this discussion into here How I operate is that Anki is a supplement to my learning and not the whole piece. For example, I use Anki to learn definitions and their properties, but then when I work on proofs, I usually scribble that down into my notes and then try my best at linking together different definitions until I have something pleasant. &#91;11:51 AM&#93;TheCedarPrince: I say “linking” intentionally as my notes are stored within a Zettelkasten where each of the definitions I’ve learned are also found. So then I weave together the notes quickly into longer form pieces or proofs or what have you &#91;11:52 AM&#93;TheCedarPrince: Let me know if you have any questions — happy to hear your thoughts&#33;</p>
<h3 id="principles_in_making_anki_cards_for_maths">Principles in Making Anki Cards for Maths</h3>
<p>These principles are curated specifically to think about maths and Anki:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Anki is a complement to learning – it is not the whole process of learning.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With maths, it is required to sit down, to struggle, and fully work through concepts. Anki is at best a complement to help you remember what you have learned or know.  At worst, a distraction that one ends up frustrated with as one is not seeing the progress they want to see.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><p>Add small pieces that are worth remembering to Anki.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Keep <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles">Anki pieces as atomic as possible &#40;see the linked note and think of them as Anki cards instead of &quot;zettels&quot;&#41;</a>. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><p>Be brutally honest in marking an Anki review. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Good cards lead to good results – take the time on making good cards. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>If having problems with a certain topic or set of questions, break the topic down to the smallest components possible to better understand the overall topic. &#91;2&#93;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Identify the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning">facts, procedures, and concepts</a> and try to use those in creating smaller supplementary cards to help you with a concept. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<h3 id="card_types">Card Types</h3>
<p>In maths, there are many different types of things to learn. Accordingly, there are a few different types of cards that are useful to make this learning process easier.</p>
<h4 id="definitions">Definitions</h4>
<p>In learning definitions, some useful principles to keep in mind in constructing Anki cards that test definitions are the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>A definition can usually be broken down across the following parts:</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- The object to be defined
- Its descriptor &#40;this is a unique definition for this object&#41;
- Notation conventions for this object
- Properties associated with the object 
- Any context that the object may be associated with &#40;e.g. when exploring a set, are we talking about sets with in ZFC Set Theory or within the category of &#36;Set&#36;?&#41; &#91;4&#93;</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p>There can be many different definitions for the same object</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- In this case, create different cards for each different definition</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p>Use clozes liberally to study each part of a given definition &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>TODO: Include example note outline here</p>
<h4 id="properties">Properties</h4>
<p>TODO: Add what I have learned about property cards TODO: Include example note outline here </p>
<h4 id="theorems">Theorems</h4>
<p>As identified in &#91;4&#93;, there are typically two types of theorems: <em>Implication Only</em> and <em>Implication and Equivalency</em>.</p>
<h5 id="implication_only_theorems">Implication Only Theorems</h5>
<p><em>Implication Only</em> theorems have the quality that the conditions associated with that particular theorem, when satisfied, imply specific conclusions. Similar to making cards for definitions, there are some principles that can be followed for these sorts of cards:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>An <em>Implication Only</em> theorem can be broken down across the following parts:</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- The theorem name to be defined
- Its descriptor &#40;the definition for this theorem&#41;
- Any context that the theorem may be associated with 
- Notation conventions for this object
- Conditions of the theorem
- Conclusions from this theorem</code></pre>
<h5 id="implication_and_equivalence_theorems">Implication and Equivalence Theorems</h5>
<p><em>Implication and Equivalence</em> theorems possess the virtue where if an associated set of conditions are met, imply that two or more arbitrary statements can be equivalent. &#91;4&#93; Making cards for this type of theorem is almost identical to making cards for definitions. The only key difference is that one should also add fields for the equivalent statements that result from this theorem.</p>
<h3 id="self_testing">Self Testing</h3>
<p>TODO: Add section based on question cards  TODO: Include example note outline here</p>
<h3 id="the_ankification_of_proofs">The &quot;Ankification&quot; of Proofs</h3>
<p>Michael Nielsen wrote an excellent piece on this process called <a href="https://cognitivemedium.com/srs-mathematics">&quot;Using spaced repetition systems to see through a piece of mathematics&quot;</a>.  Basically, he proposes the use of Anki to deeply understand and study proofs. Personally for me, I am not yet confident in an approach to draft proofs in Anki form. I <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01162023063211-ankification-proofs">took notes on Nielsen&#39;s &quot;Ankification&quot; and processing of a proof</a> and am including some digested thoughts he had on working through proofs.</p>
<h4 id="initial_glances_of_a_proof">Initial Glances of a Proof</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Pick out single elements of a proof</p>
</li>
<li><p>Convert these elements to Anki cards</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As you pick out these elements and create cards, they may be able to be formulated into definition cards. Or, they may be needed to become their own special sort of card or fact – anything that can help in the learning process.</p>
<h4 id="building_out_a_conceptual_roadmap_of_a_proof">Building Out a Conceptual Roadmap of a Proof</h4>
<p>A proof is not a linear list of statements.  Per Nielsen, it is much more valuable to think of it as relationships between simple observations.  Each of these connections between observations are not just made for no reason. Rather, determine how to find multiple ways to think of the same observation or come to the same observation that is useful for a proof. At this stage, we are beginning to learn our way comfortably around a proof and finding multiple ways to get to each step in a proof is imperative in building that comfort.</p>
<h4 id="consider_the_alternatives_of_a_proof">Consider the Alternatives of a Proof</h4>
<p>Once you have built significant comfort with a proof, keep considering different aspects of the proof. Consider the alternatives within this proof – if this assumption were changed or that context was altered, what are the ramifications of this proof? This process can continue endlessly but should only stop when you are wholly confident in your understandings of a give proof.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>To conclude, this short guide is by no means exhaustive. Instead, I made this as a short reference for myself in studying maths using a spaced repetition learning process. I&#39;ll certainly come back to revise this as I continue to work and go through the maths I study to share what works for me.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki">https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki</a>. January 6 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; “&#91;Guide&#93; How to Anki Maths the right way,” Jan. 31, 2016. https://www.reddit.com/r/Anki/comments/43mf83/guide<em>how</em>to<em>anki</em>maths<em>the</em>right_way/ &#40;accessed Jan. 09, 2023&#41;.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; M. Nielsen, “Using spaced repetition systems to see through a piece of mathematics,” 2019. http://cognitivemedium.com/srs-mathematics</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; S. Young, Ultralearning. HarperCollins Publishers, 2019.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; L. Thorburn, “Using Anki for mathematics,” Mar. 08, 2020. https://www.lukethorburn.com/anki/ &#40;accessed Jan. 09, 2023&#41;.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; A. Milchior, “How I use Anki to learn mathematics - LessWrong,” Dec. 07, 2016. https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/8ZugMc4E5959Xh86i/how-i-use-anki-to-learn-mathematics &#40;accessed Jan. 09, 2023&#41;.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Weapons of Math Destruction  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11012021133502-weapons-math-destruction/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11012021133502-weapons-math-destruction/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How algorithms and mathematics can be used to construct active harm across populations  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Weapons of Math Destruction</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 1 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How algorithms and mathematics can be used to construct active harm across populations</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #archive #book #weapon #math #destruction</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>O&#39;neil, C. &#40;2016&#41;. Weapons of math destruction: How big data increases inequality and threatens democracy. Broadway Books.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Quotes</li><li>General Observations</li><li>Credit Scores as a Proxy for Human Value</li><li>Concluding Thoughts</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="quotes">Quotes</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Sometimes the job of a data scientist is to know when you don&#39;t know enough.&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="general_observations">General Observations</h3>
<p>According to O&#39;neil, profits have often come about to provide a stand-in as a value judgement on what is right or true. To that end, we are often vetted by algorithmically based on who we are &#40;e.g. our backgrounds, race, etc.&#41; and not on how we actually perform or fare.</p>
<p>Model construction happens from:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>not just from data but from the choices we make about which data to pay attention to—and which to leave out.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Those choices are not just about logistics, profits, and efficiency. They are fundamentally moral. We have to learn to interrogate our data collection process, not just our algorithms.</p>
<h3 id="credit_scores_as_a_proxy_for_human_value">Credit Scores as a Proxy for Human Value</h3>
<p>When considering credit scores, money or wealth is no longer just about a means of survival. Wrapped up in these scores is also a value judgement on someone&#39;s self-worth. </p>
<p>Algorithms prioritize two factors: efficiency and profit. They do not care about justice or the well-being of the people underlying the data they are analyzing.</p>
<h3 id="concluding_thoughts">Concluding Thoughts</h3>
<p>So the first step is to get a grip on our techno-utopia, that unbounded and unwarranted hope in what algorithms and technology can accomplish. Before asking them to do better, we have to admit they can’t do everything</p>
<p>audits have to be carefully designed and tested by human beings, and afterward automated</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Weapons of Math Destruction</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11012021133502-weapons-math-destruction">https://jacobzelko.com/11012021133502-weapons-math-destruction</a>. November 1 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Stereographic Projection  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11132020052431-stereographic-projection/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11132020052431-stereographic-projection/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A small note on the stereographic projection method  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Stereographic Projection</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A small note on the stereographic projection method</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #stereographic #projection #linearalgebra #math #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Note Linked From:</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="note_linked_from">Note Linked From:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/10152020223819-neuriviz-project">NeuriViz Project</a> - An on-going experiment into developing performant neuroscientific visualizations via Julia.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/10182020030856-neuriviz-research-notes">NeuriViz Project Notes</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Stereographic projection is used to project a sphere to a 2D plane.  The algorithm in Cartesian coordinates looks like this:</p>
\[
[1] \ (X, Y) = (\frac{x}{1 - z}, \frac{y}{1 - z})
\]
\[
[2] \ (X, Y, Z)=\left(\frac{2 X}{1+X^{2}+Y^{2}}, \frac{2 Y}{1+X^{2}+Y^{2}}, \frac{-1+X^{2}+Y^{2}}{1+X^{2}+Y^{2}}\right)
\]
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Stereographic Projection</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11132020052431-stereographic-projection">https://jacobzelko.com/11132020052431-stereographic-projection</a>. November 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>