<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Death of a Salesman  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12262020224653-death-salesman/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12262020224653-death-salesman/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A wonderful but scathing critique of the American dream as told from the perspective of a low-income, and at times, lower-middle class, American family with the father eking out an existence as a traveling salesman.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Death of a Salesman</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 26 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A wonderful but scathing critique of the American dream as told from the perspective of a low-income, and at times, lower-middle class, American family with the father eking out an existence as a traveling salesman.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #capitalism #classic #fiction #satisfaction ##book ##blog #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>A. Miller, Death of a Salesman. Penguin Books, 1998.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>What is Satisfaction?</li><li>Shattering of Innocence</li><li>False Expectations</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="what_is_satisfaction">What is Satisfaction?</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;I&#39;m thirty-four years old, I oughta be makin&#39; my future.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That&#39;s when I come running home.  And now, I get here, and I don&#39;t know what to do with myself.  &#91;After a pause&#93; I&#39;ve always made a point of not wasting my life, and everytime I come back here I know that all I&#39;ve done is to waste my life.&quot; </p>
<p><em>Biff talking to his mother about his life&#39;s relative miserable existence</em></p>
<p>His obsession for not wasting his life or waiting almost for his life to start is similar to my thoughts. Interesting. I think the big thing is here is the overinflated notion of being &quot;big&quot; or important.  As though that were the ultimate goal of any man.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;All I can do now is wait for the merchandise manager to die.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And suppose I get to be merchandise manager?  He&#39;s a good friend of mine, and he just built a terrific estate on Long Island.  And he lived there about two months and sold it, and now he&#39;s building another one.  He can&#39;t enjoy it once it&#39;s finished.  And I know that&#39;s just what I would do.  I don&#39;t know what the hell I&#39;m workin&#39; for.  Sometimes I sit in my apartment—all alone.  And I think of the rent I&#39;m paying.  And it&#39;s crazy.  But then, it&#39;s what I always wanted.  My own apartment, a car, and plenty of women.  And still, goddammit, I&#39;m lonely.&quot;</p>
<p><em>Happy talking to his brother, Biff, about his own struggle and situation in life</em></p>
<p>This carries on the theme of the dissatisfaction with the attainment of being &quot;big&quot;. Happy got everything he could want but is still unhappy – contrasting this with Biff is that Biff is unhappy even though he did not get what he wanted.  These are two examples of being dissatisfied in uniquely different ways.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Linda: &quot;&#91;to Willy ...&#93; Why must everybody conquer the world?&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is a powerful insight into Linda&#39;s thinking.  To Linda, Willy already has the best things in the world. He just can&#39;t stop to realize it or rather, it is not enough for him to have a loving family. He needs to be big in the eyes of &quot;people&quot;.  This reminds me of my note on <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07132020022756-media-timothy">&quot;False Expertise&quot;</a> where there, the problem is that being exposed enough to material gives you prestige. In this case, Willy thinks being acknowledged by people as a nice guy is enough to ensure endless success.</p>
<h3 id="shattering_of_innocence">Shattering of Innocence</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Willy: &quot;Never mind&#33;  He&#39;s going to give you those points.  I&#39;ll see to it.&quot; Biff: &quot;He wouldn&#39;t listen to you.&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>The crushing moment when Biff sees through his father and loses complete faith in him.</em></p>
<p>I find this moment in the story more tragic than Willy&#39;s eventual death. It is this moment which doomed Willy and his family for the rest of his life.  It&#39;s never explained why Willy had an affair but, perhaps, that is the point.  A person does not need a reason for slipping.  I find it interesting how Willy tries to keep up the front of being an exemplar amongst men. Though Biff later calls his father, &quot;a prince among men,&quot; I believe it was to keep up Willy&#39;s pretense. I wonder if Willy did confess this incident to his family, if things may have been different...</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Willy </p>
</blockquote>
<p>After all the highways, and the trains, and the appointments, and the years, you end up worth more dead than alive.&quot;</p>
<p>The moment in which Willy realizes his life is not moving towards any grand destiny and decides fully upon suicide. It&#39;s an interesting insight about the idea of providing incentives.</p>
<h3 id="false_expectations">False Expectations</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Willy: &quot;Without a penny to &#91;my brother&#39;s name&#93;, &#91;...&#93; it&#39;s not what you do&#91;.&#93;  It&#39;s who you know and the smile on your face&#33;&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The crux of Willy&#39;s mentality on how life &quot;should be&quot; and how he expects life to work. Ultimately, this is proven false when he fails to get a job after pulling his contacts. In reality, nearly the exact opposite of this maxim is the truth.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Charley: &quot;The only thing you got in this world is what you can sell.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And the funny thing is that you&#39;re a salesman, and you don&#39;t know that.&quot;</p>
<p><em>Willy&#39;s neighbor Charley admonishing him on his frustration with the world not working they way Willy expects it to.</em></p>
<p>Ultimately, this searing criticism of Willy shows to him that he doesn&#39;t have any skills to offer outside of his perfunctory service as a salesman. He is a mediocre man who never tried to adapt and move with the times. And Willy refuses to believe that life passed him by in that way.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Death of a Salesman</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12262020224653-death-salesman">https://jacobzelko.com/12262020224653-death-salesman</a>. July 26 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>