<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Against Method  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The use of anarchy as a philosophical approach to learning anything.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Against Method</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The use of anarchy as a philosophical approach to learning anything.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #education #philosophy #learning #archive #book</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. Feyerabend, <em>Against method</em>, 3rd ed. London ; New York: Verso, 1993.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>General Themes</li><li>Limits of Current Education</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="general_themes">General Themes</h3>
<p>The goal of Against Method is to show that all methodologies have limits.</p>
<p>&quot;Passion&quot;, in Kierkegaard&#39;s sense, should encourage playful exploration of ideas. This passion results in behavior that facilitates circumstances and ideas which can produce a logical framework regarding an idea. &#91;1&#93;  Feyerabend contends that people rely on too narrow and fixed frameworks to understand the world. Only one principle that guides learning under any circumstance of human development is the principle &quot;anything goes.&quot;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>_His central thesis somewhat reminds me of the teaching about everything being permissible but not everything being beneficial.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder how the two can be related fully._</p>
<p>Knowledge according to Feyerabend is not a harmonious convergence towards an ideal. Rather, it is an ocean of alternatives that forces ideas into succinct articulation. Each idea competitively contributes to the development of consciousness. This makes a lot of sense. Rather than ideas being fixed in the mind, they are ever open to change and influence. Unanimity of opinion works for tyranny contends Feyerabend. Variety however is needed for objective knowledge.</p>
<p><strong>Autonomy Principle:</strong> facts exist and are independent of whether one considers alternatives to the theory to be tested.</p>
<p><strong>Theoretical numerical disagreement:</strong> A theory determines a predicted value. What is obtained in reality differs from the prediction.</p>
<h3 id="limits_of_current_education">Limits of Current Education</h3>
<p>Scientific education has the aim of making concepts more accessible at the cost of strict and unchangeable rules.  An essential part of training inhibits intuitions that might lead to a blurring of boundaries. It does this by simplifying its participants in the following manner:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>A domain of research is defined.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The domain is separated from the rest of history.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><p>This domain is then given a &#39;logic&#39; of its own.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Training in such &#39;logic&#39; then conditions the domain&#39;s disciples.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It makes their actions more uniform and it freezes large parts of the historical process as well.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li><p>Stable &#39;facts&#39;  independent of opinion, belief, and cultural background arise and persevere despite the vicissitudes of</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>history.</p>
<p>Makes me think of Godel&#39;s principle that there is a limit to what can be proved within a given domain given the tools of that domain.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Relevant Quote:  &quot;A person&#39;s religion, for example, or his metaphysics, or his sense of humour must not have the slightest connection with his scientific activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His imagination is restrained, and even his language ceases to be his own.&quot;</p>
<p>The <strong>consistency condition</strong> of modern academia demands new hypotheses to agree with accepted theories. It preserves the older theory but not the better theory. Theories should only be changed when a theory disagrees with facts. Discussion of incompatible facts will lead to progress. Discussion of incompatible hypotheses will not.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Kierkegaard, Kierkegaard’s writings, VI, volume 6: Fear and trembling/repetition. Princeton University Press, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Make It Stick: the Science of Successful Learning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How to not only remember things but to understand work  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Make It Stick: the Science of Successful Learning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How to not only remember things but to understand work</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #learning #education #psychology #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. C. Brown, Make it stick: the science of successful learning. Cambridge, Massachusetts: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2014.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Feedback</li><li>Effects of Quizzing</li><li>Characteristics of Learning</li><li>Notable Quotes</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The false idea that repetition improves memory traces back to the mid-1960&#39;s. Psychologist Endel Tulving, from the University of Toronto, tested people on their ability to remember lists of common English nouns.</p>
<h3 id="feedback">Feedback</h3>
<p>Feedback has been extensively studied. &#91;1&#93; It can lead to the following conditions:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Strengthen effects of testing</p>
</li>
<li><p>Be of greater benefit if it&#39;s slightly delayed</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enhance positive and reduces the negative effects of multiple choice testing.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Frequent immediate feedback can be detrimental to long-term learning for motor skills at it provides a crutch during practice that isn&#39;t present during the test. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<h3 id="effects_of_quizzing">Effects of Quizzing</h3>
<p>Quizzing produced a significant improvement relative to no quizzing or directed review of target concepts on unit exams and on cumulative semester and end-of-year exams. A well-placed review quiz produced benefits on the exams that were as robust as several repeated quizzes in some cases.</p>
<p>This phenomenon was first researched at Columbia Middle School. &#91;3&#93;, &#91;4&#93; They reported well-controlled experiments on the benefits of quizzing for middle school students&#39; performances on classroom exams in social studies and science.</p>
<h3 id="characteristics_of_learning">Characteristics of Learning</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Learning needs memory</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learning is a lifelong endeavor.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learning is an acquired skill; often counterintuitive.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="notable_quotes">Notable Quotes</h3>
<blockquote>
<p><em>If you’re good at learning, you have an advantage in life.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; A. C. Butler and H. L. Roediger, “Feedback enhances the positive effects and reduces the negative effects of multiple-choice testing,” Mem. Cognit., vol. 36, no. 3, pp. 604–616, 2008.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; A. W. Salmoni, R. A. Schmidt, and C. B. Walter, “Knowledge of results and motor learning: A review and critical reappraisal.” Psychol. Bull., vol. 95, no. 3, p. 355, 1984.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. A. McDaniel, P. K. Agarwal, B. J. Huelser, K. B. McDermott, and H. L. Roediger III, “Test-enhanced learning in a middle school science classroom: The effects of quiz frequency and placement.” J. Educ. Psychol., vol. 103, no. 2, p. 399, 2011.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; H. L. Roediger III, P. K. Agarwal, M. A. McDaniel, and K. B. McDermott, “Test-enhanced learning in the classroom: Long-term improvements from quizzing.” J. Exp. Psychol. Appl., vol. 17, no. 4, p. 382, 2011.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Ultralearning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A summary of what the ultralearning framework is  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Ultralearning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A summary of what the ultralearning framework is</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #ultralearning #learning #framework #education #self #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>S. Young, Ultralearning. HarperCollins Publishers, 2019.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Principles of Metalearning</li><li>Make a Roadmap for a Learning Project<ol><li>What Is the Project and What Does It Entail?</li><li>How Do We Approach The Project?</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p><strong>Ultralearning</strong>: An intensive, self-directed study framework for quickly acquiring skills and knowledge.</p>
<h3 id="principles_of_metalearning">Principles of Metalearning</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Make a roadmap for the skill you want to learn. Determine how best to learn the subject or skill you want to tackle.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Optimize your situation to make learning and concentrating, easy.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learn by doing the thing you want to become good at.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Master your weakest points by seeking relentless improvement in those areas.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Test and push yourself to remember information as opposed to simply viewing it.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Feedback is not fun but use it and don&#39;t let your ego cloud useful insights.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Know why and what you forget. Begin to remember information for long-term benefit.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Build a thorough understanding of concepts via experimenting or playing with new ideas.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="make_a_roadmap_for_a_learning_project">Make a Roadmap for a Learning Project</h3>
<p>You should invest ~10 percent of your expected learning time into research prior to starting a project.</p>
<h4 id="what_is_the_project_and_what_does_it_entail">What Is the Project and What Does It Entail?</h4>
<p>When asking the question of &quot;What&quot; regarding a learning project, break the knowledge of a subject into &quot;Concepts,&quot; &quot;Facts,&quot; and &quot;Procedures.&quot; This enables the understanding of concepts to be understood in flexible ways. Thankfully, when breaking done this information, facts generally only need to be memorized but a deep understanding may not be not required. In the same vein, procedures are actions that need to be performed and do not involve much conscious thinking.</p>
<h4 id="how_do_we_approach_the_project">How Do We Approach The Project?</h4>
<p>Employing the <strong>Emphasize/Exclude Method</strong> is to find areas of study that align with identified goals. Part of this method is to omit or delay from your curriculum material which do not align with your goals. Familiarize yourself with what is common for <strong>benchmarking</strong>, or the ways people learn a skill or subject, regarding your project.</p>
<p><strong>Directness:</strong> learning being directly related to the way you want to use the information.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06082020234244-dempster-critique/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> June 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A critique of possible reasons for why the Spacing Effect is not applied in American educational settings.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #spacing #effect #critique #education #system #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>F. N. Dempster, &quot;A Case Study in the Failure to Apply the Results of Psychological Research,&quot; American Psychologist, p. 8, 1988.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</li><li>Miscellaneous Concepts</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="issues_regarding_the_adoption_of_the_spacing_effect_into_classroom_settings">Issues regarding the adoption of the spacing effect into classroom settings.</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been studied in recent years</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is still relatively new</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect does not have any thing to do with current issues educators face.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has yet to be shown well in school activities.</p>
</li>
<li><p>There are gaps in literature about the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>School-based studies do not show the spacing effect.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect has not been well demonstrated in a classroom setting</p>
</li>
<li><p>Not enough is known about practical class implementation to warrant application of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>The spacing effect is not well comprehended</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the most concerning issues concerning usage of the spacing effect:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Ahistorical character of research on the spacing effect</p>
</li>
<li><p>Some failures to obtain the effect with school-like activities</p>
</li>
<li><p>Paucity of impressive classroom demonstrations of the phenomenon</p>
</li>
<li><p>Limited knowledge of classroom practice</p>
</li>
<li><p>Incomplete understanding of the psychological bases of the spacing effect</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Probably the most legitimate barrier to utilization of the spacing effect in educational settings is the scarcity of in class demonstrations of its usage.</strong></p>
<p>However, these four issues are not considered as such strong impediments to the implementation of the spacing effect in classroom settings:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Is not new and has been studied</p>
</li>
<li><p>Continues to receive recent documentation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Can assist in addressing educational issues</p>
</li>
<li><p>Is demonstrated to lend itself well to school-like activities</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="miscellaneous_concepts">Miscellaneous Concepts</h3>
<p><strong>Lag effects</strong> are believed to occur when performance on a memory task improves as the number of intervening items between successive presentations increases.</p>
<p><strong>Jost&#39;s Law:</strong> If two memories are equal in how well they were learned but at differing times, the older memory will gain more out of a review than the new one. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. A. McGeoch, “The psychology of human learning.” 1942.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  We Are Not Linear; Why Do We Learn Linearly?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020013824-linear-thinking/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03302020013824-linear-thinking/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Idea on thinking linearly  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>We Are Not Linear; Why Do We Learn Linearly?</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 30 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Idea on thinking linearly</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##idea #thinking #education  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>I am not in full agreement that learning material should normally be presented in a linear fashion as the brain itself is not ordered generally in a linear fashion but rather a global and far-reaching format. My question is global learning a more effective presentation of knowledge type than linear learning? This thought was inspired by <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em> &#91;1&#93; </p>
<p>This idea is also linked to the idea of <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum.md">Education as a Spectrum</a>.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking – for Students, Academics and Nonfiction Book Writers. 2017.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Education as a Spectrum  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020022908-education-spectrum/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The idea that there is no clear delineation of knowledge in reality.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Education as a Spectrum</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 9 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The idea that there is no clear delineation of knowledge in reality.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #education #knowledge #science #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Kuhnian Reasoning on Non-Linearity of Education</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>My best friend Wesley Samples believes that education – and for that matter, knowledge – falls more along a spectrum than in discrete categories &#40;such as Mathematics and Biology&#41;. One can look at biology and find the idea of the golden ratio repeated across nature &#91;1&#93;, &#91;2&#93;; example being the <em>Aeonium Tabuliforme</em>:</p>
<p><img src="https://jacobzelko.com/03102020015817-aeonium-tabuliforme.jpg" alt="saucer plant" /></p>
<p>There is the idea of the creature being a biological entity motivating questions such as</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Why does the Nautilus have a shell like this?</p>
</li>
<li><p>What function does it serve?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="kuhnian_reasoning_on_non-linearity_of_education">Kuhnian Reasoning on Non-Linearity of Education</h3>
<p>Beyond Kuhn&#39;s general <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05152022174848-structure-revolutions.md">musing in the _Structure of Scientific Revolutions</a>, his thought can also be linked to the notion that science and education is not linear.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; Golden ratio discovered in a quantum world. Eurekalert.org, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; R. Padovan, “Proportion: Science, Philosophy, Architecture,” Nexus Netw. J., vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 113–122, 2002, doi: 10.1007/s00004-001-0008-7.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>