<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  A Systematic Review of the Health of Vulnerable Populations within US Rural Societies  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/09082022131551-systematic-rural-review/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/09082022131551-systematic-rural-review/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview and summary of vulnerable populations that are particular to rural US  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>A Systematic Review of the Health of Vulnerable Populations within US Rural Societies</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> September 8 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview and summary of vulnerable populations that are particular to rural US</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #review #vulnerable #populations #rural #us  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>K. M. Gonzalez, &quot;A Systematic Review of the Health of Vulnerable Populations within US Rural Societies,&quot; OJRNHC, vol. 18, no. 1, pp. 112–147, 2018, doi: 10.14574/ojrnhc.v18i1.507.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Reading Movation</li><li>What Is Vulnerability?</li><li>Barriers Often Encountered in Rural Healthcare Settings</li><li>Vulnerabilities Most Often Studied in Rural Health Literature</li><li>Recommendations for Future Research</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="reading_movation">Reading Movation</h3>
<p>I wanted to read this paper to get more a sense for vulnerable populations. Although I was less interested in the specific applications to rural communities, I found the discussion around rural vulnerabilities very interesting as well as clarification around definitions.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_vulnerability">What Is Vulnerability?</h3>
<p>Vulnerable populations are those subgroups that are at risk for experiencing elevated healthcare disparities. &#40;De Chesnay &amp; Anderson, 2016; Shi &amp; Stevens, 2010&#41;.</p>
<p>A potential model to assess vulnerability is that proposed by &#40;Grabovschi et al., 2013&#41; where it can be visaulized as a right triangle with the horizontal axis representing healthcare accessibility and quality; vertical axis represents healthcare needs; hypotenuse is the level of vulnerability.</p>
<h3 id="barriers_often_encountered_in_rural_healthcare_settings">Barriers Often Encountered in Rural Healthcare Settings</h3>
<p>Health disparities continue to be a severe problem across US populations. &#40;Crosby, Wendel, Vanderpool, &amp; Casey, 2012; Penman-Aguilar et al., 2016&#41; Trends in inequalities emerge for patients seeking healthcare across multiple factors such as race, socioeconomic status, and provider accessibility.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Rural dwellers tend to lack insurance compared to urban settings &#40;Barker, Londeree, McBride, Kemper, &amp; Mueller, 2013; Soni, Hendryx, &amp; Simon, 2017&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Many rural dwellers travel more than 30 minutes for healthcare - it is especially exacerbated where public transportation is lacking and severe poverty exists &#40;Warren &amp; Smalley, 2014, p. xiii&#41;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="vulnerabilities_most_often_studied_in_rural_health_literature">Vulnerabilities Most Often Studied in Rural Health Literature</h3>
<p>46 articles were studied for this systematic review. Population sizes ranged from 10 to 30,874 people. For quantitative studies, populations ranged from 28 to 30,874 participants.</p>
<table><tr><th align="left">Aspects of Vulnerability Considered</th><th align="left">Included papers, n &#40;&#37;&#41;</th></tr><tr><td align="left">Low socioeconomic status</td><td align="left">22&#40;47.8&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Racial/Ethnic Minority</td><td align="left">18&#40;39.1&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chronic physical or mental illness</td><td align="left">11&#40;23.9&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Low level of education</td><td align="left">11&#40;23.9&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Old age</td><td align="left">8&#40;17.4&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Youth</td><td align="left">8&#40;17.4&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Residence in medically underserved area</td><td align="left">6&#40;13.0&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disability</td><td align="left">5&#40;10.9&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pregnancy</td><td align="left">4&#40;8.7&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking</td><td align="left">3&#40;6.5&#37;&#41;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Substance Abuse</td><td align="left">3&#40;6.5&#37;&#41;</td></tr></table>
<h3 id="recommendations_for_future_research">Recommendations for Future Research</h3>
<p>Only one article calculated a power analysis &#40;Komro et al., 2015&#41;.</p>
<p>Power analysis are used in quantitative research to limit error between hypothesis and findings.</p>
<p>There was observed an overrelianceon descriptive correlational designs that impeded adequate theory testing. Studies should incorporate theories and theoretical applications relevant to rural populations.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05222022225241-understanding-media-extensions/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05222022225241-understanding-media-extensions/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on this excellent book on media philosophy and media&#39;s intersection with society and its affects on people and community as well as eerie premonitions for the future of a technological age.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 22 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on this excellent book on media philosophy and media&#39;s intersection with society and its affects on people and community as well as eerie premonitions for the future of a technological age.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##book #review #media #extensions #anxiety #society #medium #global #village #technology #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>M. McLuhan, &quot;Understanding Media the Extensions of Man.&quot; London and New York, Oct. 1994.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Reading Motivation</li><li>The Action and the Reaction</li><li>The Age of Anxiety</li><li>The Medium Is the Message</li><li>Characteristics of a Medium</li><li>Types of Mediums<ol><li>Hot Mediums</li></ol></li><li>Creation of New Systems</li><li>Surviving an Impossible World</li><li>Media as Extensions of Tyranny and Labor</li><li>On Photography and Travel</li><li>How Media Changes Our Habits</li><li>Ads as Reflection of Actual Society</li><li>Media and Society</li><li>Comedy</li><li>Games as a Media</li><li>Media and the Nature of Work</li><li>The Nature of Radio as a Media</li><li>Television&#39;s Idiosyncrasies as a Media</li><li>Miscellany</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="reading_motivation">Reading Motivation</h3>
<p>I had long heard about this author ever since high school. I recall one day picking up a book of his at my community college&#39;s library and being both interested and overwhelmed by it. I have never much read philosophy so this was my first time encountering such a book and at the time, I found it impenetrable beyond my preliminary glances. It wasn&#39;t until this year I ventured on a project to read his magnum opus, <em>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</em>, a nearly 400 page endeavor that spanned nearly 6 months.</p>
<p>I am sure for anyone more expert, they could&#39;ve more readily finished such a book. But, although I found MacLuhan&#39;s ideas very fascinating as well as largely approachable, I could only truly approach and appreciate them if I read his work in very small chunks. So, I worked slowly through this book and have not regretted doing so a single moment.  This book was utterly life changing and has wide implications for the modern day despite this book being written nearly 70 years ago.</p>
<h3 id="the_action_and_the_reaction">The Action and the Reaction</h3>
<p>MacLuhan puts forth an initial thought of the &quot;action and the reaction&quot;. He mentions how in past ages, actions &#40;particularly the development of novel technologies like of a better plow or even printing press&#41; could be executed with relatively minimal care. Not &quot;minimal&quot; in the sense of a lack of importance but that the impact of an action rippled much more slowly through the world. The action could be followed by a well-thought out or better informed reaction by those the action was affecting.</p>
<p>However, today, &quot;the action and the reaction occur almost &#91;simultaneously&#93;&quot;. The action and reaction to a technology used to be slow but now is instantly leaving behind those incapable of adapting to the novelty. As MacLuhan observed, this simultaneity prevents an acclimation period for persons as much of humanity continues to &quot;think in the old, fragmented space and time patterns of the pre-electric age.&quot; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com//12242022202340-relativity-information-gaps.md">I intentionally invoke the word &quot;simultaneity&quot; here as I think this concept of &quot;action and reaction&quot; finds analogy within Einstein&#39;s notion of Relativity of Simultaneity</a> TODO: Create note on Relativity of Simultaneity using this link: https://sites.pitt.edu/~jdnorton/teaching/HPS<em>0410/chapters/Special</em>relativity<em>rel</em>sim/index.html and this one: https://sites.pitt.edu/~jdnorton/Goodies/rel<em>of</em>sim/index.html TODO: Create separate note on analogy between Relativity of Simultaneity and Information Dissemination</p>
<p>In the past, MacLuhan posits that we used technology to create &quot;extensions&quot; that &quot;extended&quot; parts of our bodies – like a knife extending our teeth or a firearm extending our fists. Not so in the electric era.  Rather, we have &quot;extended our central nervous system itself in a global embrace, abolishing both space and time&#91;.&#93;&quot; MacLuhan believes that we are rapidly approaching the point in society and technology wherein, &quot;the creative process of knowing will be collectively and corporately extended to the whole of human society. &#91;... Where&#93; it is no longer possible to adopt the aloof and dissociated role of the literate Westerner.&quot;</p>
<p>Everyone&#39;s business is now everyone&#39;s business.</p>
<h3 id="the_age_of_anxiety">The Age of Anxiety</h3>
<p>One idea that I think MacLuhan fantastically captured and explained much better than modern pundits and observers have done is how our age is one of anxiety. This has been bemoaned in many ways from multiple different groups – be they political, scientific or spiritual – but I have always found the notions being discussed to be buried too much in a specific domain or emerging trend. MacLuhan instead abstracts this concept to a much higher level that gives it, in my opinion, a much better resonance of the true problems of our electric age.</p>
<p>As he says, &quot;If the nineteenth century was the age of the editorial chair, ours is the century of the psychiatrist&#39;s couch.&quot; Something that was hard to grasp at first was the careful delineation he made between a &quot;chair&quot; and a &quot;couch&quot;. For him, the &quot;chair&quot; as an extension of man is a mechanical replacement of one&#39;s spine – a reinforcement to help the &quot;sitter&quot; maintain their position &#40;on an argument or view&#41;.  Instead, the modern &quot;couch&quot; becomes an icon that offers no such support but a sort of endless collapse into ease that thwarts &quot;the temptation to express private points of view and obviates the need to rationalize events.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This is the Age of Anxiety for the reason of the electric implosion that compels commitment and participation, quite regardless of any &quot;point of view&quot;,&quot; is a line of thinking that links back this notion of the &quot;Age of Anxiety&quot; to his original idea on the &quot;action and the reaction&quot;. As man in an electric society can no longer be an observer, the &quot;point of view&quot; &#40;which I understand as one&#39;s own beliefs and thoughts about the world&#41; one may have becomes an obstacle to a global society. Using the means of a psychiatrist&#39;s couch, we can become numbed to even our own beliefs and mental facilities. Instead, the current zeitgeist is to allow our &quot;point of view&quot; fall congruent to the will of the masses and governing authorities.</p>
<p>And here MacLuhan utters his famous line: &quot;the globe is no more than a village,&quot; to illustrate how every problem, every action, every perspective, is now standing and staring at you and how <em>you</em> will act. &quot;It is this implosive factor that alters the position of &#91;various&#93; groups. They can no longer be contained, in the political sense of limited association. They are now involved in our lives, as we in theirs, thanks to the electric media.&quot; We are now obligated to some involvement regardless of one exact point of view.</p>
<p>And therein lies the core problem of this Age of Anxiety: conflicting views in the electric age lead to adversity. Because what if we say, do, or think something that goes askew the prevailing global &quot;point of view&quot;? At best, one could be described as &quot;quaint&quot; or &quot;old-fashioned&quot; perhaps; at worst, one could be excommunicated from the village.</p>
<h3 id="the_medium_is_the_message">The Medium Is the Message</h3>
<p>I think I will have to read more of MacLuhan&#39;s work someday to better understand the concept of &quot;medium&quot; but this is my very loose understanding. As MacLuhan cryptically says, &quot;the medium is the message,&quot; forming the key motif of this entire book. He builds upon earlier language around &quot;extensions&quot; to explain that the message conveyed by a medium consists of the &quot;personal and social consequences&quot; of a medium &#40;i.e. an extension&#41; that result from the scale introduced into our lives by each extension. In short, the message itself is the consequences of a medium that affect reality we inhabit.</p>
<p>In compliment to the &quot;message&quot; of a medium, the &quot;&#39;content&#39; of any medium is always another medium.&quot; When I first read this, I was rather confused as it seemed in contradiction to my earlier understanding of what the message of a medium is. However, what MacLuhan was more referring to as &quot;content&quot; is not again so much the actual &quot;information&quot; in the message but more the &quot;method&quot; of its communication such as the following line of examples:</p>
<pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph LRSpeech --ContentOf--&gt; Writing</code></pre>
<p>Using MacLuhan&#39;s notion of the &quot;content&quot; of a medium, we see that &quot;speech&quot; is fundamentally the content of the medium, &quot;writing&quot;.</p>
<pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph LRWriting --ContentOf--&gt; Print</code></pre>
<p>Then &quot;writing&quot; is the content of the medium of &quot;print&quot;.</p>
<pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph LRPrint --ContentOf--&gt; Telegraph</code></pre>
<p>Finally, &quot;print&quot; is the content of the medium of the &quot;telegraph&quot;.  MacLuhan did point out that you could go even further from the root of &quot;speech&quot; to muscle contractions in one&#39;s throat, to thought, etc. However, I, as well as MacLuhan, found that to be a bit inane and I find it reasonable to call speech a &quot;fundamental&quot; content. It is a bit confusing how MacLuhan uses &quot;content&quot; in this scenario but to summarize my understanding of his central treatise on what he means by &quot;the medium is the message&quot;:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&quot;&#91;The&#93; &#39;message&#39; of any medium &#91;...&#93; is the change &#91;...&#93; that it introduces into human affairs.&quot;</p>
</li>
<li><p>&quot;&#91;T&#93;he medium &#91;...&#93; shapes and controls &#91;...&#93; human association and action.&quot;</p>
</li>
<li><p>The &quot;content&quot; of any medium is another medium</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Even though the delineation between what is a &quot;medium&quot;, what is &quot;content&quot;, and what is a &quot;message&quot; is thorny to parse from MacLuhan&#39;s writing &#40;at least for me&#41;, I think this separation is wholly necessary. In fact, I think this delineation is what is missing from modern discourse on new mediums &#40;ergo technologies&#41;. In culmination of this initial discussion on mediums, I think the most important takeaway for me about mediums is this quote: &quot;it is only too typical that the &#39;content&#39; of any medium blinds us to the character of the medium.&quot; We can limit ourselves by only thinking within existing &quot;content&quot; of a given &quot;medium&quot; rather than viewing the medium wholly.</p>
<p>In short, new mediums enable entirely novel realities. Letters were once highly cherished not only because of their &quot;content&quot; &#40;i.e. the medium of writing and hand-writing&#41; and their &quot;information&quot; &#40;what did the letter say&#41; but also due to the constrained medium of a letter. Letters could take days or weeks to be delivered and would have to encapsulate much within their &quot;information&quot;. Now with the use of instant messaging, we have lost &quot;content&quot; &#40;i.e. hand-writing&#41; in this medium but it introduces an entirely new reality of interacting with the &quot;content&quot;. The &quot;information&quot; conveyed by the &quot;content&quot; of instant messaging can be trivialized much more easily due to the instantaneous nature of the &quot;medium&quot; of instant messaging.</p>
<h3 id="characteristics_of_a_medium">Characteristics of a Medium</h3>
<p>MacLuhan goes onto further explain the characteristics of a medium. &quot;General David Sarnoff made this statement: &quot;We are too prone to make technological instruments the scapegoats for the sins of those who wield them. The products of modern science are not in themselves good or bad; it is the way they are used that determines their value.&quot; That is the voice of the current somnambulism. Suppose we were to say, &quot;Apple pie is in itself neither good nor bad; it is the way it is used that determines its value.&quot; Or, &quot;The smallpox virus is in itself neither good nor bad; it is the way it is used that determines its value.&quot; Again, &quot;Firearms are in themselves neither good nor bad; it is the way they are used that determines their value.&quot; That is, if the slugs reach the right people firearms are good.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 13&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;any medium has the power of imposing its own assumption on the unwary&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 17&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;greatest aid to this end is simply in knowing that the spell can occur immediately upon contact&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 17&#41;</p>
<p>Mediums are virulent. They can infect, inspire, and alter oneself all at once.</p>
<p>&quot;literate man is quite inclined to see others who cannot conform as somewhat pathetic&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 18&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;testers assume that uniform and continuous habits are a sign of intelligence, thus eliminating the ear man and the tactile man&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 18&#41;</p>
<p>Could it be said that these could be geniuses, those who do not conform?</p>
<p>The private point of view according to McLuhan is all at once an illusion as we become who we behold</p>
<p>How media affect or leach into a community should be the underlying area of study in examining the impacts of a media.</p>
<p>&quot;we are losing all confidence in our right to assign guilt&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 22&#41;</p>
<p>Assigning guilt is lost in the electric area. Calling anything wrong or crazy is impossible.</p>
<h3 id="types_of_mediums">Types of Mediums</h3>
<h4 id="hot_mediums">Hot Mediums</h4>
<p>&quot;A hot medium is one that extends one single sense in &quot;high definition.&quot; High definition is the state of being well filled with data.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 30&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;A photograph is, visually, &quot;high definition.&quot; A cartoon is &quot;low definition,&quot; simply because very little visual information is provided. Telephone is a cool medium. or one of low definition, because the ear is given a meager amount of information&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 30&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Hot media are, therefore, low in participation, and cool media are high in participation or completion by the audience&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 31&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;For myth is the instant vision of a complex process that ordinarily extends over a long period. Myth is contraction or implosion of any process, and the instant speed of electricity confers the mythic dimension on ordinary industrial and social&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 33&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;We are certainly coming within conceivable range of a world automatically controlled to the point where we could say, &quot;Six hours less radio in Indonesia next week or there will be a great falling off in literary attention.&quot; Or, &quot;We can &#33; program twenty more hours of TV in South Africa next week to cool down the tribal temperature raised by radio last week.&quot; Whole cultures could now be programmed to keep their emotional climate stable in the same way that we have begun to know something about maintaining equilibrium in the commercial economies of the world&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 36&#41; media based influence and control of ideas</p>
<h3 id="creation_of_new_systems">Creation of New Systems</h3>
<p>&quot;One of the most common causes of breaks in any system is the cross-fertilization with another system, such as happened to print with the steam press, or with radio and movies &#40;that yielded the talkies&#41;.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 49&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Except for light, all other media come in pairs, with one acting as the &quot;content&quot; of the other, obscuring the operation of both&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 63&#41;</p>
<p>McLuhan says that the artist is always the first person to make the intersection of mediums powerful. I wonder if that is so.</p>
<p>&quot;The moment of the meeting of media is a moment of freedom and release from the ordinary trance and numbness imposed by them on our senses.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 67&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;That is what is meant when we say that we daily know more and more about man. We mean that we can translate more and more of ourselves into other forms of expression that exceed ourselves. Man is a form of expression who is traditionally expected to repeat himself and to echo the praise of his Creator&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 69&#41;</p>
<p>I really like this idea that man itself is a type of expression. Meaning, translation is infinite.</p>
<p>He makes an interesting observation about people who are illiterate to this age. They afford technology a sort of tribal magic much like how inexperienced investors expect to make money by throwing funds into stock.</p>
<p>Missing the whole for the parts.</p>
<p>&quot;The artist is the man in any field, scientific or humanistic, who grasps the implications of his actions and of new knowledge in his own time&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 78&#41;</p>
<p>He goes into great detail about how the artists are the ones able to react to new technologies. Is is them who can express the groans of the current reality.</p>
<h3 id="surviving_an_impossible_world">Surviving an Impossible World</h3>
<p>&quot;it is obvious that numbness is the result of any prolonged terror&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 39&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The price of eternal vigilance is indifference.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 39&#41;</p>
<p>Autoamputation is an interesting thought. I was unsure what was meant at first but realize it is the process by which to externalize or remove an internal irritant through some kind of self extension.</p>
<p>The suicidal autoamputation is a more heinous variety where all experiences are external separate to the body. Makes me think of VR and Meta. He points out that this happens because we are not equipped to handle such extreme serialization.</p>
<p>A &quot;closure&quot; is the idea that a person conforms perceptually to a media they are immersed in - like Psalm 113. Finally, more of an explanation on what closures are. They are the worlds media make for themselves.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to numb our central nervous system when it is extended and exposed, or we will die&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 57&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Thus the age of anxiety and of electric media is also the age of the unconscious and of apathy.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 58&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Our private and corporate lives have become information processes just because we have put our central nervous systems outside us in electric technology.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 63&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The mark of our time is its revulsion against imposed patterns. We are suddenly eager to have things and people declare their beings totally.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 8&#41;</p>
<p>Is it wise that we have this revulsion against patterns? Rather, I find it a possible societal regression of a kind. Why do we say in hubris that we know now better to live than in any time of human history? Is man, unrestrained, really man or some primal, base thing?</p>
<h3 id="media_as_extensions_of_tyranny_and_labor">Media as Extensions of Tyranny and Labor</h3>
<p>This is an interesting thought that as the means of communication are improved, so are the means of tyranny</p>
<p>&quot;A speed-up in communications always enables a central authority to extend its operations to more distant margins&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 109&#41;</p>
<p>Clothing can be thought of as an extension as it concerns one&#39;s ability interact with the environment.</p>
<p>Light enables a whole new world or worlds and abolishes the notion of night and day.</p>
<p>&quot;Time is money,&quot; and money is the store of other people&#39;s time and effort&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 152&#41;</p>
<p>Money is the ultimate store of collective human endeavors and the translator of work from priest to prostitute.</p>
<p>&quot;Automation, which is electronic, does not represent physical work so much as programmed knowledge&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 154&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Although the medium is the message, the controls go beyond programming. The restraints are always directed to the &quot;content,&quot; which is always another medium. The content of the press is literary statement, as the content of the book is speech, and the content of the movie is the novel. So the effects of radio are quite independent of its programming&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 337&#41;</p>
<p>Money is not a closed system</p>
<h3 id="on_photography_and_travel">On Photography and Travel</h3>
<p>&quot;Time can be defeated, as it were, by reversal of its characteristics if only it be speeded up enough&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 170&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The age of Jung and Freud is, above all, the age of the photograph, the age of the full gamut of self-critical attitudes&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 218&#41;</p>
<p>I love this critique of photos and travel. Basically, as time goes on the value of those hobbies or objects dull our senses or sense of wonder.</p>
<p>&quot;contrived, prefabricated.&quot; He is not concerned to find out why the photograph has done this to us. But in the same way intelligent people in the past always deplored the way in which the book had become a substitute for inquiry, conversation, and reflection, and never troubled to reflect on the nature of the printed book. The book reader has always tended to be passive, because that is the best way to read. Today, the traveler has become passive&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 219&#41;</p>
<h3 id="how_media_changes_our_habits">How Media Changes Our Habits</h3>
<p>&quot;Difficulty of access does not confer adequacy of perception, though it may involve an object in an aura of pseudo-values, as with a gem, a movie star, or an old master&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 220&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;This now brings us to the factual core of the &quot;pseudoevent,&quot; a label applied to the new media, in general, because of their power to give new patterns to our lives by acceleration of older patterns&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 220&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;All media exist to invest our lives with artificial perception and arbitrary values&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 220&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The car has become the carapace, the protective and aggressive shell, of urban and suburban man&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 248&#41;</p>
<h3 id="ads_as_reflection_of_actual_society">Ads as Reflection of Actual Society</h3>
<p>&quot;Ads are news. What is wrong with them is that they are always good news&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 231&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The steady trend in advertising is to manifest the product as an integral part of large social purposes and processes. With very large budgets the commercial artists have tended to develop the ad into an icon, and icons are not specialist fragments or aspects but unified and compressed images of complex kind. They focus a large region of experience in tiny compass&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 250&#41;</p>
<p>He has a bullseye view of ads in my opinion - its how the milk ads can appear so important to society.</p>
<p>&quot;there are the new massive iconic ads with their compressed images that include producer and consumer, seller and society in a single image&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 251&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Ads seem to work on the very advanced principle that a small pellet or pattern in a noisy, redundant barrage of repetition will gradually assert itself. Ads push the principle of noise all the way to the plateau of persuasion. They are quite in accord with the procedures of brain-washing&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 251&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Ads are not meant for conscious consumption. They are intended as subliminal pills for the subconscious in order to exercise an hypnotic spell&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 252&#41;</p>
<h3 id="media_and_society">Media and Society</h3>
<p>&quot;Any community that wants to expedite and maximize the exchange of goods and services has simply got to homogenize its social life&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 253&#41;</p>
<p>This line makes me think of of Kuhn&#39;s idea of incommensurability.</p>
<p>&quot;our intensely individualist and fragmented Western world, &quot;booze&quot; is a social bond and a means of festive involvement. By contrast, in closely knit tribal society &quot;booze&quot; is destructive of all social pattern and is even used as a means to mystical experience&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 258&#41;</p>
<p>Interesting observation on the role of alcohol in communities.</p>
<p>&quot;Just as we now try to control atom-bomb fallout, so we will one day try to control media fallout. Education will become recognized as civil defense against media fallout&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 337&#41;</p>
<h3 id="comedy">Comedy</h3>
<p>&quot;We think of humor as a mark of sanity for a good reason: in fun and play we recover the integral person, who in the workaday world or in professional life can use only a small sector of his being&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 259&#41;</p>
<p>Beautiful commentary on comedy as a sort of lifeline to the self in a way.</p>
<h3 id="games_as_a_media">Games as a Media</h3>
<p>&quot;A game is a machine that can get into action only if the players consent to become puppets for a time&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 263&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps there is, just for this reason, a desperate need for games in a highly specialized industrial culture, since they are the only form of art accessible to many minds&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 266&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;A moral point of view too often serves as a substitute for understanding in technological matters. That games are extensions, not of our private but of our social selves, and that they are media of communication, should now be plain. If, finally, we ask, &quot;Are games mass media?&quot; the answer has to be &quot;Yes.&quot; Games are situations contrived to permit simultaneous participation of many people in some significant pattern of their own corporate lives.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 270&#41;</p>
<h3 id="media_and_the_nature_of_work">Media and the Nature of Work</h3>
<p>&quot;From this time on, the mere specialist in any field was doomed to the sterility and inanity that echoed an archaic form of the departing mechanical age&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 275&#41;</p>
<p>Really makes me think of Willy Loman from Death of a Salesman and my own grandfather.</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore, no new idea ever starts from within a big operation. It must assail the organization from outside, through some small but competing organization&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 277&#41;</p>
<p>This reminds me of the verse that says how no student can be above his teacher.</p>
<p>&quot;Northcote Parkinson&#39;s law that &quot;work expands so as to fill the time available for its completion&quot; is precisely the zany dynamic provided by the telephone&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 290&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;the main &quot;work to be done&quot; is actually the movement of information. The mere interrelating of people by selected information is now the principal source of wealth in the electric age&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 291&#41;</p>
<p>It is an interesting remark on labor saving devices. Rather than freeing up time, you end up doing more labor and work than before. It brought down the barrier of entry for menial tasks so all could do them.</p>
<p>&quot;A mechanized world is always in the process of getting ready to live, and to this end it brings to bear the most appalling pomp of skill and method and resourcefulness&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 321&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The world eagerly lined up to buy canned dreams&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 322&#41;</p>
<h3 id="the_nature_of_radio_as_a_media">The Nature of Radio as a Media</h3>
<p>&quot;To the blind, all things are unexpected&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 294&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The telephone: speech without walls. The phonograph: music hall without walls. The photograph: museum without walls. The electric light: space without walls&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 313&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;What the Orient saw in a Hollywood movie was a world in which all the ordinary people had cars and electric stoves and refrigerators. So the Oriental now regards himself as an ordinary person who has been deprived of the ordinary man&#39;s birthright&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 325&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;If a government monopolizes the radio, then by mere repetition and byRADIO 325 exclusion of conflicting points of view it can determine the opinions of the population&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 328&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;This is inherent in the very nature of this medium, with its power to turn the psyche and society into a single echo chamber&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 331&#41;</p>
<h3 id="televisions_idiosyncrasies_as_a_media">Television&#39;s Idiosyncrasies as a Media</h3>
<p>&quot;TV is a medium that rejects the sharp personality and favors the presentation of processes rather than of products&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 341&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;grammars of newspaper, or radio, or of film, but who look askew and askance at all non-book media. The simplest question about any psychic aspect, even of the book medium, throws these people into a panic of uncertainty. Vehemence of projection of a single isolated attitude they mistake for moral vigilance. Once these censors became aware that in all cases &quot;the medium is the message&quot; or the basic source of effects, they would turn to suppression of media as such, instead of seeking &quot;content&quot; control. Their current assumption that content or programming is the factor that influences outlook and action is derived from the book medium, with its sharp cleavage between form and content&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 347&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The failure of the sex-integration programs has provided the theme of much of the literature and psychoanalysis of the twentieth century. Race integration, undertaken on the basis of visual uniformity, is an extension of the same cultural strategy of literate man, for whom differences always seem to need eradication, both in sex and in race, and in space and in time&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 349&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Print gave intensity and uniform precision, where before there had been a diffuse texture. Print brought in the taste for exact measurement and repeatability that we now associate with science and mathematics&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 350&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The same new preference for depth participation has also prompted in the young a strong drive toward religious experience with rich liturgical overtones&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 354&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;anybody whose appearance strongly declares his role and status in life is wrong for TV Anybody who looks as if he might be a teacher, a doctor, a businessman, or any of a dozen other things all at the same time is right for TV&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 365&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The TV child expects involvement and doesn&#39;t want a specialist job in the future. He does want a role and a deep commitment to his society&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 370&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;The TV child cannot see ahead because he wants involvement, and he cannot accept a fragmentary and merely visualized goal or destiny in learning or in life&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 370&#41;</p>
<h3 id="miscellany">Miscellany</h3>
<p>&quot;Since our new electric technology is not an extension of our bodies but of our central nervous systems, we now see all technology, including language, as a means of processing experience, a means of storing and speeding information. And in such a situation all technology can plausibly be regarded as weapons&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 379&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Dewart in his Crintanity adn Revolution, wehn he points tothe obsolescence fo the fragemnted balance of power techniques. As an instrument of policy, modern war has come to mean &quot;the existence and end of one society tot he esclusion of another&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 381&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Any subject taken in depth at once relates to other subjects. Arithmetic in grade three or nine, when taught in terms of number theory, symbolic logic, and cultural history, ceases to be mere practice in problems. Continued in their present patterns of fragmented unrelation, our school curricula will insure a citizenry unable to understand the cybernated world in which they live&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 383&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Men are suddenly nomadic gatherers of knowledge, nomadic as never before, informed as never before, free from fragmentary specialism as never before –but also involved in the total social process as never before; since with electricity we extend our central nervous system globally, instantly interrelating every human experience&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 395&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Tradition, in a word, is the sense of the total past as now&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 333&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody experiences far more than he understands&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 351&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;Before the huddle of the city, there was the food-gathering phase of man the hunter, even as men have now in the&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 378&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;electric age returned psychically and socially to the nomad state. Now, however, it is called information-gathering and data-processing&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 379&#41;</p>
<p>&quot;As Selye deals with the total environmental situation in his &quot;stress&quot; theory of disease, so the latest approach to media study considers not only the &quot;content&quot; but the medium and the cultural matrix within which the particular medium operates.&quot; &#40;McLuhan, 1994, p. 13&#41; How fascinating&#33; McLuhan knew of the stress theory of disease. I wonder how he knew that? I find it so fascinating the analogy McLuhan is making. It seems as though McLuhan proposes to say that the medium is an organ which interplay’s with Selye&#39;s theory. Rather than contradicting or separate from it, it subsists within and intertwined with this theory. In short, McLuhan seems to say that whereas Selye took an environmental approach to disease, McLuhan is taking a holistic view to mediums in a person&#39;s life</p>
<p>Selye&#39;s work preceded the work of Sir Michael Marmot in creating the Social Determinants of Health. Plus he was starting with the idea of metastatic load.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  The Structure of Scientific Revolutions  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05152022174848-structure-revolutions/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05152022174848-structure-revolutions/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A book review of Thomas Kuhn&#39;s most famous book that challenged all of the philosophy of science and introduced such concepts as normal science, paradigm shift, why non-scientific fields struggle with similar revolutions, and when one can adopt new paradigms.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 15 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A book review of Thomas Kuhn&#39;s most famous book that challenged all of the philosophy of science and introduced such concepts as normal science, paradigm shift, why non-scientific fields struggle with similar revolutions, and when one can adopt new paradigms.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##book ##blog ##outline #review #normal #science #paradigm #shift #revolution #science #philosophy #crisis #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>T. S. Kuhn and I. Hacking, The Structure of Scientific Revolutions, Fourth edition. Chicago; London: The University of Chicago Press, 2012.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Introduction</li><li>What Is <em>Normal Science</em>?<ol><li>What Are the Characteristics of Normal Science?</li></ol></li><li>What Was Kuhn&#39;s Concept of a Paradigm?<ol><li>What Are the Characteristics of a Paradigm?</li><li>What Are the Benefits of Choosing a Paradigm?</li></ol></li><li>What Causes the Downfall of a Paradigm?<ol><li>What Happens When a Paradigm Is in Crisis?</li><li>Extraordinary Problems</li></ol></li><li>&quot;Scientific Revolutions&quot; and the Term &quot;Revolution&quot;</li><li>Invoking New Paradigms on Faith</li><li>On the Non-Linearity of Science</li><li>Additional Notes<ol><li>Paradigm Shifts in Other Domains</li><li>Non-Kuhnian Revolutions or Domain Transformations</li></ol></li><li>Conclusion</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>This book has had an immense impact in the world of science. From how science is taught to how science is thought about, Kuhn&#39;s notions of scientific revolution resonated across nearly all domains of science as well as touching into the arts. The central conceit that Kuhn stated in this book is that the scientific community knows what the world is like. I was recommended this book by my friend, collaborator, and Category Theorist, <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://www.jpfairbanks.com/">Professor James P. Fairbanks</a> I can see why it was recommended as it fits in quite nicely to the ensuing philosophical ideas found in <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11082021041951-category-theory-scientists.md">Category Theory</a>.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_normal_science">What Is <em>Normal Science</em>?</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022044134-normal-science.md">Note for atomic concept</a></p>
<p>According to Kuhn, <em>normal science</em>, is research based on past scientific accomplishments that are considered the foundation for that area of investigation. Generally, this is the area where most scientists spend their time. The research done in normal science can be theoretical or empirical.</p>
<p>In the book, Kuhn referred to this as &quot;mop-up work&quot; and that this mopping up or &quot;filling out&quot; of science is what most scientists do. Although language such as &quot;mop-up&quot; work can make one think that Kuhn was being pejorative to these so-called &quot;scut scientists&quot;, he did not intend it so. In later versions of this book, he made a response to this point of confusion and clarified that this work still is fascinating and crucial in many ways to the advancement of science.</p>
<h4 id="what_are_the_characteristics_of_normal_science">What Are the Characteristics of Normal Science?</h4>
<p>An important aspect of normal science is that it does not engage with or seek out anything new. The invention of theories, development of new phenomena - anything abnormal - is not part of normal science. Novelty is abhorrent and antithetical to normal science.</p>
<p>Aside from this fundamental aspect of normal science, Kuhn posited that there are three general areas of research in normal science. He emphasized that they do not always hold or are always discrete from one another:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Investigating questions around the fundamental facts found in a specific domain.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Questions that are predicted and expected to have answers existing within an already existing research domain.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Further articulating the fundamental facts held in a given domain.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="what_was_kuhns_concept_of_a_paradigm">What Was Kuhn&#39;s Concept of a Paradigm?</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022044626-kuhnian-paradigm.md">Note for atomic concept</a></p>
<p>Kuhn reintroduced into the modern English lexicon the word, &quot;paradigm&quot;. Before his time, the term was rather archaic. A paradigm is the background through which normal science is conducted loosely speaking. Another way of thinking about it is from online user <em>heynonnynonnie</em> suggesting that a paradigm is a consensus agreed upon by a group of practitioners of a field.</p>
<h4 id="what_are_the_characteristics_of_a_paradigm">What Are the Characteristics of a Paradigm?</h4>
<p>When he used the word, as Kuhn admitted himself, he overloaded the term to mean quite a number of things. To my understanding, this was my gist of a Kuhnian paradigm in that paradigms generally have two core characteristics:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Unprecedented and can sustain practitioners</p>
</li>
<li><p>Open-ended and with problems to be solved or investigated</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Endemic to paradigms is that they posit theories around a domain of research. For a paradigm to be accepted, it must propose a better theory than its predecessors or competitors. Furthermore, a proposed new paradigm is not required to address every fact of the world.</p>
<h4 id="what_are_the_benefits_of_choosing_a_paradigm">What Are the Benefits of Choosing a Paradigm?</h4>
<p>When a domain decides upon a paradigm, avenues of research can now be readily scoped. By presupposing paradigm, questions can now be posed within the context of the paradigm. In accordance to the paradigm, it can be reasonably assumed that solutions can be found.</p>
<p>A benefit that did not immediately appear to me was the insulating properties of a paradigm. An example that Kuhn suggested is that in the social sciences, one has to frame an avenue of research by its importance to society &#40;such as studying racial discrimination, etc.&#41;. Problems such as these are notoriously difficult to frame and reach a quorum consensus on due to possibly many competing schools of thought or groups. Instead, by keeping a conversation limited to the adherents of a specific paradigm, a researcher can easily keep moving forward through problems without having to strive against competing schools of thought. Furthermore, the insulating power of a paradigms gives a researcher the ability to solely focus on problems they think they can solve or are solvable.</p>
<p>I will admit, his example of social scientists was at first confusing. But, upon reflection, what made this example make sense is that he later explained his decision to have this as an example due to the fact that there are often many competing paradigms in these areas. This conflict makes progress difficult as many people still argue the fundamentals of these sciences.</p>
<h3 id="what_causes_the_downfall_of_a_paradigm">What Causes the Downfall of a Paradigm?</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022044910-downfall-kuhnian-paradigm.md">Note on atomic concept</a></p>
<p>Normal science certainly is clear, safe, and predictable. But, what if a scientist finds results that do not fit within a paradigm? What if a result, ruling out all possible errors carried forth by a highly scrupulous researcher, is simply unexplainable - an anomaly against the backdrop of a paradigm? To Kuhn, this marks an important inflection point in adopted paradigms.</p>
<p>Novelty in science only emerges with resistance and difficulty because any, as Kuhn wisely points out, researchers who investigate every anomaly will not get much done. But at some point, these anomalies will continue to accumulate to the point of being unignorable to adherents of a paradigm. A sort of malcontent will arise adherents and to <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07222020181007-famous-quotes.md">quote Sherlock Holmes, &quot;When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.&quot;</a> And that truth is that an accepted paradigm is no longer sufficient to explain a domain which leads to a period of significant upheaval.</p>
<p>Kuhn characterized the downfall of a paradigm in three generic ways:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Awareness of anomaly</p>
</li>
<li><p>Further recognition of awareness</p>
</li>
<li><p>Contested possible change or challenge to the existing paradigm</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="what_happens_when_a_paradigm_is_in_crisis">What Happens When a Paradigm Is in Crisis?</h4>
<p>When the anomalies are fully unconscionable, they are finally acknowledged and, to quote Kuhn:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Discovery commences with &#91;...&#93; awareness of anomaly&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The previous paradigm prepared an adherent on how to detect an anomaly and in a way, set up its own downfall. At this stage of upheaval, many will attempt to explain or address the anomalous behavior. A new era of discovery in the face of a failing paradigm marks this interstitial period of an outdated paradigm where many speculative and unarticulated theories abound - often at odds with one another in some way. The previous paradigm&#39;s rules become hazy and the rules of normal research begin to veer away from its typical, standard process.</p>
<h4 id="extraordinary_problems">Extraordinary Problems</h4>
<p>This problem leads normal science into a rather interesting process of science called &quot;extraordinary science&quot;. Extraordinary science is an offshoot of normal science that exists when a paradigm is in crisis and to address the paradigm in crisis. It is the science that either repairs, questions, or proves the deficiency of an existing paradigm. Important to note about extraordinary science is that they are never known at the outset of a paradigm but only after advanced normal research in the context of a given paradigm.</p>
<h3 id="scientific_revolutions_and_the_term_revolution">&quot;Scientific Revolutions&quot; and the Term &quot;Revolution&quot;</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022045723-scientific-revolutions.md">Note on atomic concept</a></p>
<p>According to Kuhn, these crises are the requirements for a new paradigm to come forth. This leads to extraordinary science as this episode in a paradigm&#39;s life is extraordinary that causes a basic shift in how science is even conducted. This period, coined by Kuhn, is called a &quot;Scientific Revolution&quot;.</p>
<p>Kuhn was very particular in invoking the term &quot;revolution&quot;. He related the phrase &quot;scientific revolution&quot; analogously to a political revolution. In the same way that a political revolution is often fomented when a political body fails to serve adequately the growing body of its populace, so too are the grounds set for a scientific revolution.</p>
<p>Although a paradigm may shift how one does science, the world itself does not change. Rather, the way we view and operate in the world does. For the adoptees of a new paradigm, the adoptee must say something to the effect of &quot;I once understood X to be Y, but I was mistaken&quot; and in doing so admit a form of error in looking at reality.</p>
<h3 id="invoking_new_paradigms_on_faith">Invoking New Paradigms on Faith</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022045931-new-paradigms.md">Note on atomic concept</a></p>
<p>A problem inherit to the development of new paradigms is that to adopt these new paradigms is most certainly an act of faith. Early adherents to a new paradigm must stand against the onslaught of problems that were solved or addressed by  a previous paradigm. They must simply have hope and faith that this new paradigm they have adopted will succeed in the areas where the previous paradigm failed. As Kuhn said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;A decision of that kind can only be made on faith&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even when this new paradigm is able to successfully surmount longstanding problems, Kuhn says that even still a vast majority of scientists will be apprehensive to adopt this paradigm. Why? Kuhn observed that two conditions must be met for further adoption:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>The new paradigm must solve outstanding problems that the prior paradigm could not.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Much of the problem solving tools from previous paradigms should still be able to be used in this new paradigm.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>In this sense, there is a type of verification or vetting of a new paradigm – an analogy to natural selection as Kuhn pointed out. For a new paradigm to be successful, not only must it address all problems hitherto encountered by prior paradigms, but be able to solve outstanding problems prior paradigms could not and the barrier to adopting this new paradigm must be minimal. &quot;No theory ever solves all &#91;...&#93; puzzles with which it is confronted at a given time; nor are the solutions already achieved often perfect,&quot; is a fitting bookend from Kuhn to remember when encountering new paradigms.</p>
<p>One small final footnote on new paradigms is an observation by Kuhn: the invention of a paradigm most generally comes from someone very young or new to the field where a paradigm exists that they are trying to change.</p>
<h3 id="on_the_non-linearity_of_science">On the Non-Linearity of Science</h3>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05222022050357-non-linearity-science.md">Note on atomic concept</a></p>
<p>One thing out of this book is that I very much appreciated and agreed with Kuhn&#39;s notion that science is not linear nor is it necessarily the result of a universal truth being uncovered. Rather, it is the confluence of emerging theories that evolve and find they can fit with other theories or paradigms. These newly combined theories then come together to possibly overturn or change the understanding of currently practiced science.</p>
<p>This fallacious notion of linear knowledge going to a particular truth about the world is based in part on science historians and textbook makers. As textbooks are designed to assist students in learning as much material as possible, the teacher with the textbook maker chooses to formulate a textbook around one particular area of knowledge thereby giving a sense of progress to a domain&#39;s particular truth. As science does not deal with all possible experiments but only those which are doable according to an existing paradigm, so too a textbook must be very judicious in what it presents to a student from its paradigm.</p>
<h3 id="additional_notes">Additional Notes</h3>
<p>As I wrap up this review of <em>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</em>, here are some additional notes that didn&#39;t quite fit in the overall review. I did still find these pertinent as well as helpful in expanding thoughts about paradigms.</p>
<h4 id="paradigm_shifts_in_other_domains">Paradigm Shifts in Other Domains</h4>
<p>Outside of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics, Kuhn&#39;s notion of paradigm shifts do occur. Such a paradigm shift based on Kuhn&#39;s writings in an area such as the social sciences could be - and I am making an educated guess here - something akin to the near modern universal condemnation and outlawing of slavery. However, to this end Kuhn posited that unlike the other natural sciences, there still exist competing schools of thought. A visceral modern example is that social scientists also have to defend their choice of a research problem such as examining race in the context of the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07112020161337-social-determinants-health.md">social determinants of health</a> where other existing schools of thought may fiercely disagree on the validity of such endeavors.</p>
<p>Furthermore, Kuhn gave the great example that, &quot;the man who argues that philosophy &#91;...&#93; has made no progress emphasizes that there are still Aristotelians, not that Aristotelianism has failed to progress,&quot; I am in agreement with Kuhn in that it is not that schools of thought outside Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics are not making progress. It is that their are much more fundamental conflicts in these spaces that have yet to be reconciled in sufficient ways.</p>
<p>In an online group discussion, the user <em>ish-i-ness</em> furthered this idea to the arts that, &quot;that in the arts you could even say that there is a desire to discover an aesthetic truth, something that is indisputably, objectively beautiful and thought provoking, rather than just a fad that is only interesting because it’s appeals to a particular, subjective set of preferences.&quot; Here, <em>ish-i-ness</em> invokes this notion of aesthetic truth which is associated with Theodore Adorno.</p>
<h4 id="non-kuhnian_revolutions_or_domain_transformations">Non-Kuhnian Revolutions or Domain Transformations</h4>
<p>In an online group discussion, the user <em>heynonnynonnie</em>, made a great point that non-Kuhnian scientific revolutions happen more frequently than the bigger Kuhnian scientific revolutions &#40;such as the heliocentric versus geocentric theory, etc.&#41;. As these are much smaller scale revolutions and do not affect the entirety of science, I call these &quot;domain transformations&quot; as they transform or affect a particular domain&#39;s way of operating but not the rest of science as a whole. <em>heynonnynonnie</em> gave the example that the discovery of the DNA structure, though fantastic and a major discovery, provided only pure information that fit within the preexisting paradigms.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>I thought this book was well done and also worth this lengthy analysis. It provided context to a lot of ideas that were born from the notions Kuhn coined here. For me, it felt like giving me a bit more of a better foundation to understand better how to operate in domains. Even if this piece is labeled more as a philosophy of science piece, it could easily also be considered a sociological exploration of academia as a whole. I recommend the read, but also, not to take the notions as literally or seriously as possible. Kuhn himself suggested that as he later would get inundated with letters saying that there was a revolution happening because of X - help me. As judicious as Kuhn was in using the term revolution, we too must be careful to recognize when a revolution or paradigm shift is occurring.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  The Picture of Dorian Gray  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/04202022021854-picture-dorian-gray/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/04202022021854-picture-dorian-gray/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Book review on the extreme hedonism, classist privilege, and complete moral collapse written about Dorian Gray  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>The Picture of Dorian Gray</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> April 19 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Book review on the extreme hedonism, classist privilege, and complete moral collapse written about Dorian Gray</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary #review #book #hedonism #privilege #corruption #morality #homosexuality #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>O. Wilde, The Picture of Dorian Gray. OUP Oxford, 2006.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Introduction</li><li>Extreme Hedonism</li><li>Moral Collapse</li><li>On Homo-Eroticism</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>This was a rather odd but enjoyable book. Even though Wilde more depicted this book as the evil and banality of hedonism taken to the extreme, it was a rather nice reminder, for me personally, that it is acceptable to enjoy life. To seek and find new experiences and adventures is perfectly fine, but as Wilde pointed out, there is a limit.</p>
<h3 id="extreme_hedonism">Extreme Hedonism</h3>
<p>What I really enjoyed was the characterizations of Dorian and Lord Henry as these somewhat egalitarians with Dorian being the more novice and Henry being the more advanced. Dorian somewhat starts as a perfect blank template - an Adonis ready to be made Henry&#39;s Pygmalion. With Henry&#39;s influence, Dorian starts to shed his &quot;classist good manners&quot; and evolve into a full hedonist to embrace the darker desires unknown to those belonging to &quot;Dorian&#39;s kind of society&quot;.</p>
<p>As Henry points out to Dorian,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;The only way to get rid of a temptation is to yield to it. Resist it, and your soul grows sick with longing for the things it has forbidden to itself, with desire for what its monstrous laws have made monstrous and unlawful&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which has a bit of truth to it. For sure we have all been tempted by that which we cannot have and perhaps we have given into a temptation. It certainly does give a bit of relief but then, we only want more. We are not bidden to ourselves to pursue that thing at all costs - if so, we would be no different than mere animals chasing every desire. Yet, that is exactly what Dorian believes after Henry explains his ideas to him.</p>
<h3 id="moral_collapse">Moral Collapse</h3>
<p>This begins to manifest in Dorian believing in his inherent superiority due to his charm and good looks that Henry and Basil praises him for. That perspective can be encapsulated in Basil saying, </p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;The ugly and the stupid have the best of it in this world.  They can sit quietly and gape at the play. If they know nothing of victory, they are at least spared the knowledge of defeat. They live as we all should live, undisturbed, indifferent, and without disquiet.&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Although Basil meant this more as a social commentary and not entirely a classist judgement, Henry followed up later with a similar but different sentiment of this same notion. Here, Henry instead says,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Society, civilized society at least, is never very ready to believe anything to the detriment of those who are both rich and charming&#91;.&#93;&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Essentially, Henry&#39;s view is more of the kind saying, &quot;hey, you have more privilege and power than you think. Use it.&quot; In this case, he encourages the use of this privilege and power at the expense of all others. In Basil&#39;s comment, he more encourages Dorian to recognize his privilege and power but to be a wise steward of it. Instead, Dorian follows Henry&#39;s influence to gratify all of himself.</p>
<p>Before Dorian fully sheds his soul, after the suicide of Sibyl caused nearly directly by Dorian, there is a moment of tragic reflective introspection Dorian has:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;&#91;W&#93;hy is it that I cannot feel this tragedy as much as I want to?&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He says as he nearly begs Henry for an answer. Rather than this being a true moment for introspection, Henry instead just encourages Dorian to brush this off as an experience. Perhaps not the most happy of experience, but one nonetheless. Although Dorian knows he out to feel something, he instead allows Henry to salve his wounds.</p>
<p>In so doing, &quot;the life that was to make his soul,&quot; was avoided and any &quot;&#91;marring of&#93; his body&quot;, Dorian was spared. This enabled him to commit even worse terrors. The murder of Basil, the blackmailing of Alan, and the ruin of many of those around him, Dorian was now fully unchained to pursue it all. Dorian&#39;s moral collapse was well and truly complete.</p>
<h3 id="on_homo-eroticism">On Homo-Eroticism</h3>
<p>There was a strong undercurrent of homosexuality and homo-eroticism in this book. With Basil&#39;s unreuited love for Dorian, the homosexuality here was shown rather positively. Yet, with Dorian, this was portrayed as predatory to men and youth around him. A welcome change of the oft-condemning of homosexuals in Victorian literature but rather a sort of early value judgement on what was moral and immoral homosexual behavior for that time. Most likely this was a direct commentary from Wilde himself as a bisexual person but it wove into the narrative rather well.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  X &#43; Y : A Mathematician’s Manifesto for Rethinking Gender  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/04162022002725-mathematician-gender-rethinking/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/04162022002725-mathematician-gender-rethinking/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Book review on an approach of using category theory to decouple and discuss characteristics of gender without conflating the two - great read&#33;  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>X &#43; Y : A Mathematician’s Manifesto for Rethinking Gender</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> April 15 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Book review on an approach of using category theory to decouple and discuss characteristics of gender without conflating the two - great read&#33;</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary ##blog #review #book #gender #ingressive #congressive #category #theory #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>E. Cheng, X &#43; Y: A Mathematician’s Manifesto for Rethinking Gender. Basic Books, 2020.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Introduction</li><li>Category Theory as Tool for Thinking on Gender</li><li>Congressive versus Ingressive Thinking</li><li>Conclusion</li><li>Final Thoughts</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>Eugenia Cheng takes a nuanced approach to the discussion around gender. As she references, some feminists&#39; battle cry is the phrase, &quot;Smash the patriarchy&#33;&quot;. In Cheng&#39;s idea of feminism, she instead looks for language that is less divisive and more inclusive encompassed in her saying, &quot;Let’s transform our world into a more congressively led future.&quot;</p>
<h3 id="category_theory_as_tool_for_thinking_on_gender">Category Theory as Tool for Thinking on Gender</h3>
<p>With this approach, she launches into her core contribution to the discussion on gender which is introducing the mathematics of <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11082021041951-category-theory-scientists.md">category theory</a> to decouple historical characteristics associated genders from the genders themselves. Cheng argues that this is a better approach to take in gender discussions to think more deeply about traits or characteristics in isolation rather than rooted in gender. You can then critique a characteristic or trait rather than a whole group of people.</p>
<p>Rather than being a book on mathematics and gender, category theory is used more as a mental model or framework to enact this decoupling. This works well as category theory fundamentally concerns itself about relationships. In her opinion, category theory enables one to think more clearly about about characteristics with a great degree of flexibility.</p>
<h3 id="congressive_versus_ingressive_thinking">Congressive versus Ingressive Thinking</h3>
<p>Cheng introduced two crucial words into her argument which can describe concepts, behaviors or people: &quot;congressive&quot; and &quot;ingressive&quot;. This is how she defined these terms summarized below:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Ingressive</strong> - putting oneself over society, imposing on others frequently, far more individualistic than collaborative, less flexible thinking</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Congressive</strong> - society over self, prioritizing others, highly collective and community-focused, holistic thought patterns</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In this way, the onus of characteristics is moved from tightly coupled gender stereotypes to decoupled conversations on those characteristics in isolation. However, this isn&#39;t entirely the case all the time as most concepts, behaviors, or people have some tendencies to ingressive behavior and some to congressive behavior. As Cheng herself posits, &quot;When gender is relevant, we need to consider it. When character is relevant, we need to consider it.  But we shouldn&#39;t assume they are linked.&quot;</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>She concludes in her book how she doesn&#39;t want, &quot;to see &quot;masculine&quot; and &quot;feminine&quot; character traits evaluated against each other &#91;...&#93; so only one side can win,&quot; in discussions around gender. She emphasizes how she doesn&#39;t want women having to act like men to succeed. Rather, she believes that there are not only other ways to make contributions to society but rather that there are other traditional forms of success.</p>
<h3 id="final_thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Overall, I really enjoyed this book&#33; I feel like her point was made pretty early on and I appreciated some of the examples. However, as I am acquainted with category theory as well as having read some material on gender studies in the past, I personally was able to skip through various parts.</p>
<p>I think her notion of decoupling is immensely important however I am not sure on her terminology of &quot;ingressive&quot; and &quot;congressive&quot;. Whenever anyone overloads terms with additional definitions, it makes me nervous that confusion in discussion can occur. However, since these are not commonly used terms, at least in my experience, it makes me think this may not be as big an issue.</p>
<p>Finally, it has made me think about where this method of decoupling can be used rigorously. In particular, I am curious about race and concepts such as the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07112020161337-social-determinants-health.md">social determinants of health</a> and how category theoretic approaches can be brought there. I think Cheng even teases readers with this idea so I am curious to see if she revisits the ideas someday:</p>
<p>&quot;The idea of a temporary abstraction also takes into account the thorny issue of intersectionality, and the need to take other forms of power imbalance into account besides those governed by gender, for example race, wealth, sexual orientation, and so on.&quot;</p>
<p>Overall, good read&#33;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  GTD Weekly Review  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03192020050249-gtd-weekly-review/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03192020050249-gtd-weekly-review/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How to conduct weekly reviews using GTD.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>GTD Weekly Review</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 19 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How to conduct weekly reviews using GTD.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #review #weekly #model #productivity #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Each week, you should hold a 30 minute-ish weekly review to guarantee each project on the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020050207-gtd-implementation.md">project list</a> has at least one upcoming next action for the week. </p>
<p>Utilize a <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020050346-trigger-list.md">trigger list</a> to help make sure you did not miss anything. The trigger list should be custom to whatever it is that you are working on or are responsible for.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="transparent_dark"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>