<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Composite guide in using spaced repetition systems in learning maths  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 6 2023</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Composite guide in using spaced repetition systems in learning maths</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #math #learning #anki #flashcards #spaced #repetition #proofs #theorems #definitions #project #archive #blog</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Motivation</li><li>Principles in Making Anki Cards for Maths</li><li>Card Types<ol><li>Definitions</li><li>Theorems<ol><li>Implication Only Theorems</li><li>Implication and Equivalence Theorems</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>The &quot;Ankification&quot; of Proofs<ol><li>Initial Glances of a Proof</li><li>Building Out a Conceptual Roadmap of a Proof</li><li>Consider the Alternatives of a Proof</li></ol></li><li>Conclusion</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>A major goal in my life is to get better with studying maths. As I fully intend to study mathematics more rigorously, a powerful component and tool in my studying toolbox has been Spaced Repetition Systems like Anki or Memrise. In particular, I wanted to know how to use these sort of systems to study and retain math more effectively in my studies – which sometimes face unexpected interruptions. This post serves as a guide to do just that.</p>
<h3 id="principles_in_making_anki_cards_for_maths">Principles in Making Anki Cards for Maths</h3>
<p>These principles are curated specifically to think about maths and Anki:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Anki is a complement to learning – it is not the whole process of learning.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With maths, it is required to sit down, to struggle, and fully work through concepts. Anki is at best a complement to help you remember what you have learned or know.  At worst, a distraction that one ends up frustrated with as one is not seeing the progress they want to see.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><p>Add small pieces that are worth remembering to Anki.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Keep <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles.md">Anki pieces as atomic as possible &#40;see the linked note and think of them as Anki cards instead of &quot;zettels&quot;&#41;</a>. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><p>Be brutally honest in marking an Anki review. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Good cards lead to good results – take the time on making good cards. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>If having problems with a certain topic or set of questions, break the topic down to the smallest components possible to better understand the overall topic. &#91;2&#93;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Identify the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning.md">facts, procedures, and concepts</a> and try to use those in creating smaller supplementary cards to help you with a concept. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<h3 id="card_types">Card Types</h3>
<p>In maths, there are many different types of things to learn. Accordingly, there are a few different types of cards that are useful to make this learning process easier.</p>
<h4 id="definitions">Definitions</h4>
<p>In learning definitions, some useful principles to keep in mind in constructing Anki cards that test definitions are the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>A definition can usually be broken down across the following parts:</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- The object to be defined
- Its descriptor &#40;this is a unique definition for this object&#41;
- Notation conventions for this object
- Properties associated with the object 
- Any context that the object may be associated with &#40;e.g. when exploring a set, are we talking about sets with in ZFC Set Theory or within the category of &#36;Set&#36;?&#41; &#91;4&#93;</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p>There can be many different definitions for the same object</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- In this case, create different cards for each different definition</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p>Use clozes liberally to study each part of a given definition &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="theorems">Theorems</h4>
<p>As identified in &#91;4&#93;, there are typically two types of theorems: <em>Implication Only</em> and <em>Implication and Equivalency</em>.</p>
<h5 id="implication_only_theorems">Implication Only Theorems</h5>
<p><em>Implication Only</em> theorems have the quality that the conditions associated with that particular theorem, when satisfied, imply specific conclusions. Similar to <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/#Definitions">making cards for definitions</a>, there are some principles that can be followed for these sorts of cards:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>An <em>Implication Only</em> theorem can be broken down across the following parts:</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- The theorem name to be defined
- Its descriptor &#40;the definition for this theorem&#41;
- Any context that the theorem may be associated with 
- Notation conventions for this object
- Conditions of the theorem
- Conclusions from this theorem</code></pre>
<h5 id="implication_and_equivalence_theorems">Implication and Equivalence Theorems</h5>
<p><em>Implication and Equivalence</em> theorems possess the virtue where if an associated set of conditions are met, imply that two or more arbitrary statements can be equivalent. &#91;4&#93; Making cards for this type of theorem is <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/#implication-only-theorems">almost identical to making cards for definitions</a>. The only key difference is that one should also add fields for the equivalent statements that result from this theorem.</p>
<h3 id="the_ankification_of_proofs">The &quot;Ankification&quot; of Proofs</h3>
<p>Michael Nielsen wrote an excellent piece on this process called <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://cognitivemedium.com/srs-mathematics">&quot;Using spaced repetition systems to see through a piece of mathematics&quot;</a>.  Basically, he proposes the use of Anki to deeply understand and study proofs. Personally for me, I am not yet confident in an approach to draft proofs in Anki form. I <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01162023063211-ankification-proofs.md">took notes on Nielsen&#39;s &quot;Ankification&quot; and processing of a proof</a> and am including some digested thoughts he had on working through proofs.</p>
<h4 id="initial_glances_of_a_proof">Initial Glances of a Proof</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Pick out single elements of a proof</p>
</li>
<li><p>Convert these elements to Anki cards</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As you pick out these elements and create cards, they may be able to be <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/#definitions">formulated into definition cards</a>. Or, they may be needed to become their own special sort of card or fact – anything that can help in the learning process.</p>
<h4 id="building_out_a_conceptual_roadmap_of_a_proof">Building Out a Conceptual Roadmap of a Proof</h4>
<p>A proof is not a linear list of statements.  Per Nielsen, it is much more valuable to think of it as relationships between simple observations.  Each of these connections between observations are not just made for no reason. Rather, determine how to find multiple ways to think of the same observation or come to the same observation that is useful for a proof. At this stage, we are beginning to learn our way comfortably around a proof and finding multiple ways to get to each step in a proof is imperative in building that comfort.</p>
<h4 id="consider_the_alternatives_of_a_proof">Consider the Alternatives of a Proof</h4>
<p>Once you have built significant comfort with a proof, keep considering different aspects of the proof. Consider the alternatives within this proof – if this assumption were changed or that context was altered, what are the ramifications of this proof? This process can continue endlessly but should only stop when you are wholly confident in your understandings of a give proof.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>To conclude, this short guide is by no means exhaustive. Instead, I made this as a short reference for myself in studying maths using a spaced repetition learning process. I&#39;ll certainly come back to revise this as I continue to work and go through the maths I study to share what works for me.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Making Math Flashcards Using Spaced Repetition Systems</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki">https://jacobzelko.com/01072023041127-making-math-anki</a>. January 6 2023.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; “&#91;Guide&#93; How to Anki Maths the right way,” 31-Jan-2016. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www.reddit.com/r/Anki/comments/43mf83/guide<em>how</em>to<em>anki</em>maths<em>the</em>right_way/. &#91;Accessed: 09-Jan-2023&#93;.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; M. Nielsen, “Using spaced repetition systems to see through a piece of mathematics,” 2019. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: http://cognitivemedium.com/srs-mathematics.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; S. Young, Ultralearning. HarperCollins Publishers, 2019.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; L. Thorburn, “Using Anki for mathematics,” 08-Mar-2020. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www.lukethorburn.com/anki/. &#91;Accessed: 09-Jan-2023&#93;.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; A. Milchior, “How I use Anki to learn mathematics - LessWrong,” 07-Dec-2016. &#91;Online&#93;. Available: https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/8ZugMc4E5959Xh86i/how-i-use-anki-to-learn-mathematics. &#91;Accessed: 09-Jan-2023&#93;.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Zettelkasten  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on the Zettelkasten note taking system as made popular by sociologist Niklas Luhmann.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Zettelkasten</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 2 2022</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on the Zettelkasten note taking system as made popular by sociologist Niklas Luhmann.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary ##zettelkasten #learning #research #tool #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Selecting Notes for a Zettelkasten</li><li><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles.md">Principles of Zettelkasten</a></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="selecting_notes_for_a_zettelkasten">Selecting Notes for a Zettelkasten</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03302020005409-note-criteria.md">Criteria for Creating a Note in the Zettelkasten</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** Simple criteria for when and how to add notes to the Zettelkasten.
- **Rationale:** Enumerates a robust system for how to add notes to the Zettelkasten</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03172020033742-antifragility">Antifragility</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** An overview on Nassim Taleb&#39;s thoughts on Antifragility
- **Rationale:** Zettelkastens should be antifragile -- i.e. they thrive off of disorder and chaos and adapt to it meaningfully.</code></pre>
<h3 id="a_href03092020031618-zettelkasten-principlesmdprinciples_of_zettelkasten"><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031618-zettelkasten-principles.md">Principles of Zettelkasten</a></h3>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** General principles on how to create and use a Zettelkasten</code></pre>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Zettelkasten</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten">https://jacobzelko.com/03092020031549-zettelkasten</a>. December 2 2022.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Flow  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12302020172825-flow/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12302020172825-flow/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  What is the concept of flow and being in a flow state  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Flow</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 30 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> What is the concept of flow and being in a flow state</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #learning #flow #psychology #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p><strong>Flow</strong>: The state of mind where one stops being mentally interrupted and becomes completely absorbed in the task at hand; the enjoyable state between boredom and frustration.</p>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning.md">Idea attributed to psychologist Mihály Csíkszentmihályi</a></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Flow</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12302020172825-flow">https://jacobzelko.com/12302020172825-flow</a>. December 30 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Against Method  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The use of anarchy as a philosophical approach to learning anything.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Against Method</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The use of anarchy as a philosophical approach to learning anything.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #education #philosophy #learning #archive #book</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. Feyerabend, <em>Against method</em>, 3rd ed. London ; New York: Verso, 1993.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>General Themes</li><li>Limits of Current Education</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="general_themes">General Themes</h3>
<p>The goal of Against Method is to show that all methodologies have limits.</p>
<p>&quot;Passion&quot;, in Kierkegaard&#39;s sense, should encourage playful exploration of ideas. This passion results in behavior that facilitates circumstances and ideas which can produce a logical framework regarding an idea. &#91;1&#93;  Feyerabend contends that people rely on too narrow and fixed frameworks to understand the world. Only one principle that guides learning under any circumstance of human development is the principle &quot;anything goes.&quot;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>_His central thesis somewhat reminds me of the teaching about everything being permissible but not everything being beneficial.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder how the two can be related fully._</p>
<p>Knowledge according to Feyerabend is not a harmonious convergence towards an ideal. Rather, it is an ocean of alternatives that forces ideas into succinct articulation. Each idea competitively contributes to the development of consciousness. This makes a lot of sense. Rather than ideas being fixed in the mind, they are ever open to change and influence. Unanimity of opinion works for tyranny contends Feyerabend. Variety however is needed for objective knowledge.</p>
<p><strong>Autonomy Principle:</strong> facts exist and are independent of whether one considers alternatives to the theory to be tested.</p>
<p><strong>Theoretical numerical disagreement:</strong> A theory determines a predicted value. What is obtained in reality differs from the prediction.</p>
<h3 id="limits_of_current_education">Limits of Current Education</h3>
<p>Scientific education has the aim of making concepts more accessible at the cost of strict and unchangeable rules.  An essential part of training inhibits intuitions that might lead to a blurring of boundaries. It does this by simplifying its participants in the following manner:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>A domain of research is defined.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The domain is separated from the rest of history.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><p>This domain is then given a &#39;logic&#39; of its own.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Training in such &#39;logic&#39; then conditions the domain&#39;s disciples.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It makes their actions more uniform and it freezes large parts of the historical process as well.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li><p>Stable &#39;facts&#39;  independent of opinion, belief, and cultural background arise and persevere despite the vicissitudes of</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>history.</p>
<p>Makes me think of Godel&#39;s principle that there is a limit to what can be proved within a given domain given the tools of that domain.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Relevant Quote:  &quot;A person&#39;s religion, for example, or his metaphysics, or his sense of humour must not have the slightest connection with his scientific activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His imagination is restrained, and even his language ceases to be his own.&quot;</p>
<p>The <strong>consistency condition</strong> of modern academia demands new hypotheses to agree with accepted theories. It preserves the older theory but not the better theory. Theories should only be changed when a theory disagrees with facts. Discussion of incompatible facts will lead to progress. Discussion of incompatible hypotheses will not.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Against Method</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method">https://jacobzelko.com/07122020043224-against-method</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; S. Kierkegaard, Kierkegaard’s writings, VI, volume 6: Fear and trembling/repetition. Princeton University Press, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Make It Stick: the Science of Successful Learning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How to not only remember things but to understand work  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Make It Stick: the Science of Successful Learning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How to not only remember things but to understand work</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #learning #education #psychology #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>P. C. Brown, Make it stick: the science of successful learning. Cambridge, Massachusetts: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2014.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Feedback</li><li>Effects of Quizzing</li><li>Characteristics of Learning</li><li>Notable Quotes</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The false idea that repetition improves memory traces back to the mid-1960&#39;s. Psychologist Endel Tulving, from the University of Toronto, tested people on their ability to remember lists of common English nouns.</p>
<h3 id="feedback">Feedback</h3>
<p>Feedback has been extensively studied. &#91;1&#93; It can lead to the following conditions:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Strengthen effects of testing</p>
</li>
<li><p>Be of greater benefit if it&#39;s slightly delayed</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enhance positive and reduces the negative effects of multiple choice testing.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Frequent immediate feedback can be detrimental to long-term learning for motor skills at it provides a crutch during practice that isn&#39;t present during the test. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<h3 id="effects_of_quizzing">Effects of Quizzing</h3>
<p>Quizzing produced a significant improvement relative to no quizzing or directed review of target concepts on unit exams and on cumulative semester and end-of-year exams. A well-placed review quiz produced benefits on the exams that were as robust as several repeated quizzes in some cases.</p>
<p>This phenomenon was first researched at Columbia Middle School. &#91;3&#93;, &#91;4&#93; They reported well-controlled experiments on the benefits of quizzing for middle school students&#39; performances on classroom exams in social studies and science.</p>
<h3 id="characteristics_of_learning">Characteristics of Learning</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Learning needs memory</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learning is a lifelong endeavor.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learning is an acquired skill; often counterintuitive.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="notable_quotes">Notable Quotes</h3>
<blockquote>
<p><em>If you’re good at learning, you have an advantage in life.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Make It Stick: the Science of Successful Learning</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick">https://jacobzelko.com/07122020164149-make-it-stick</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; A. C. Butler and H. L. Roediger, “Feedback enhances the positive effects and reduces the negative effects of multiple-choice testing,” Mem. Cognit., vol. 36, no. 3, pp. 604–616, 2008.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; A. W. Salmoni, R. A. Schmidt, and C. B. Walter, “Knowledge of results and motor learning: A review and critical reappraisal.” Psychol. Bull., vol. 95, no. 3, p. 355, 1984.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. A. McDaniel, P. K. Agarwal, B. J. Huelser, K. B. McDermott, and H. L. Roediger III, “Test-enhanced learning in a middle school science classroom: The effects of quiz frequency and placement.” J. Educ. Psychol., vol. 103, no. 2, p. 399, 2011.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; H. L. Roediger III, P. K. Agarwal, M. A. McDaniel, and K. B. McDermott, “Test-enhanced learning in the classroom: Long-term improvements from quizzing.” J. Exp. Psychol. Appl., vol. 17, no. 4, p. 382, 2011.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Ultralearning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A summary of what the ultralearning framework is  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Ultralearning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A summary of what the ultralearning framework is</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #ultralearning #learning #framework #education #self #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>S. Young, Ultralearning. HarperCollins Publishers, 2019.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Principles of Metalearning</li><li>Make a Roadmap for a Learning Project<ol><li>What Is the Project and What Does It Entail?</li><li>How Do We Approach The Project?</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p><strong>Ultralearning</strong>: An intensive, self-directed study framework for quickly acquiring skills and knowledge.</p>
<h3 id="principles_of_metalearning">Principles of Metalearning</h3>
<ol>
<li><p>Make a roadmap for the skill you want to learn. Determine how best to learn the subject or skill you want to tackle.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Optimize your situation to make learning and concentrating, easy.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Learn by doing the thing you want to become good at.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Master your weakest points by seeking relentless improvement in those areas.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Test and push yourself to remember information as opposed to simply viewing it.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Feedback is not fun but use it and don&#39;t let your ego cloud useful insights.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Know why and what you forget. Begin to remember information for long-term benefit.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Build a thorough understanding of concepts via experimenting or playing with new ideas.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="make_a_roadmap_for_a_learning_project">Make a Roadmap for a Learning Project</h3>
<p>You should invest ~10 percent of your expected learning time into research prior to starting a project.</p>
<h4 id="what_is_the_project_and_what_does_it_entail">What Is the Project and What Does It Entail?</h4>
<p>When asking the question of &quot;What&quot; regarding a learning project, break the knowledge of a subject into &quot;Concepts,&quot; &quot;Facts,&quot; and &quot;Procedures.&quot; This enables the understanding of concepts to be understood in flexible ways. Thankfully, when breaking done this information, facts generally only need to be memorized but a deep understanding may not be not required. In the same vein, procedures are actions that need to be performed and do not involve much conscious thinking.</p>
<h4 id="how_do_we_approach_the_project">How Do We Approach The Project?</h4>
<p>Employing the <strong>Emphasize/Exclude Method</strong> is to find areas of study that align with identified goals. Part of this method is to omit or delay from your curriculum material which do not align with your goals. Familiarize yourself with what is common for <strong>benchmarking</strong>, or the ways people learn a skill or subject, regarding your project.</p>
<p><strong>Directness:</strong> learning being directly related to the way you want to use the information.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Ultralearning</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning">https://jacobzelko.com/07082020163004-ultralearning</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05282020164557-desirable-difficulties/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05282020164557-desirable-difficulties/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Practical discussion about how to introduce desirable learning difficulties into your learning patterns.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 28 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Practical discussion about how to introduce desirable learning difficulties into your learning patterns.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography ##finish #performance #storage #strength #difficulty #desirable #learning #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, and others, &quot;Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,&quot; Psychology and the real world: Essays illustrating fundamental contributions to society, vol. 2, no. 59–68, 2011.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Performance is a quantifiable metric that is observed in teaching or practice.</p>
<p>Performance is not a valid metric to determine if learning is occuring.</p>
<p>Storage strength defines how interassociated a representation of memory is to relevant experiences &#40;such as knowledge or skills&#41;.</p>
<p>Learning is the idea of creating permanent changes in one&#39;s understanding or knowledge regarding a particular subject.</p>
<p>Factors that quickly improve retrieval strength are different from those that improve storage strength. If learners mistake retrieval strength as storage strength, a learner could mistakenly be led to believe that situations which improve retrieval strength could improve storage strength.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020164557-desirable-difficulties">https://jacobzelko.com/05282020164557-desirable-difficulties</a>. May 28 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How increasing difficulties in learning can increase better long-term learning. Examples included.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 25 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How increasing difficulties in learning can increase better long-term learning. Examples included.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography ##finish #performance #learning #forgetting #retrieval #strength #storage #generation #effect #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, and others, &quot;Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,&quot; Psychology and the real world: Essays illustrating fundamental contributions to society, vol. 2, no. 59 - 68, 2011.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Difficulties which can encourage learning: </p>
<ol>
<li><p>Varied learning conditions as opposed to constant and predictable ones.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Interleaving instruction on separate topics together.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Spacing study sessions on a given topic.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Using tests as study events. &#91;1&#93;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Learning how to learn is the ultimate survival tool. </p>
<p>Rather do not fret over inputs but rather, output. Consolidate reading material from memory. Get with others to drill one another with questions. Activites that test your ability to generate explications yields more robust learning experiences.</p>
<p>Memory does not function like a video recorder. Reviewing the same material ad nauseam is not effective for memory. Learning involves attaching novel information to what is known by oneself. </p>
<p>Generating an explanation about a topic rather than just being given a solution can be more effective than the spacing effect. This is called the generation effect.</p>
<p>Learning difficulties which are desirable trigger encoding and retrieval processes that support storage strength. If the learner is unable to successfully handle presented difficulties, they become impediments rather than helps to learning.</p>
<p>Retrieval strength explains the ease in accessing a representation of a specific memory in the brain. It is signficantly affected by factors such as cues and recency of exposure to a material related to that representation.</p>
<p>Studying the same material in two different rooms rather the same room leads to increased recall of that material. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>Interleaved practice produces higher quality prolonged retention and promotes skill transferability. In comparison to blocked practice and other sorts of mass practicing. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Blocked practice is deceptive; it is not the best form of learning though it can appear to be so. &#91;3&#93; </p>
<p>It is suggested that interleaving material forces one to differentiate between different topics. When pressured, this can heighten one&#39;s perception about differentiators. It leads to better embedding of abstractions that foster retention and transfer. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Participants in a motor skills test received 18 patterned trials via a pinball-like machine set-up. Participants were presented with randomly determined patterns &#40;interleaved&#41; or individual patterns that were practiced consecutively &#40;blocked&#41; on the machine. Blocked participants quickly improved versus interleaved participants. After a 10 day break, participants retested under blocked or interleaved conditions. Presented random conditions, the original interleaved participants performed superior to the blocked participants. Blocked participants appeared to have learned nothing. Presented blocked conditions, results were approximately the same but the minimal differences favored interleaving. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Testing is seen as a means of quantitative assessment but not for learning purposes. This is in contradiction to the fact that testing can be highly a highly beneficial tool for learning rather than a measurement of learning taking place. </p>
<p>8 and 12 year olds practiced tossing beanbags at a target on the floor while having their vision blocked at each throw. Half of each age group practiced throwing at a fixed distance target. The rest threw at targets of varying distances. After sufficient practices and a break, all children were tested under fixed target conditions for their age group. Children who practiced at variable distances performed better than fixed target participants. Introducing variation outmatched benefits of fixed distance practice. &#91;4&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Making Things Hard On Yourself, But In A Good Way: Creating Desirable Difficulties To Enhance Learning</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self">https://jacobzelko.com/05252020211350-hard-on-self</a>. May 25 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; R. A. Bjork, “Memory and metamemory considerations in the,” Metacognition Knowing Knowing, vol. 185, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; S. M. Smith, A. Glenberg, and R. A. Bjork, “Environmental context and human memory,” Memory &amp; Cognition, vol. 6, no. 4, pp. 342–353, Jul. 1978, doi: 10.3758/BF03197465.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; J. B. Shea and R. L. Morgan, “Contextual interference effects on the acquisition, retention, and transfer of a motor skill.” J. Exp. Psychol. &#91;Hum. Learn.&#93;, vol. 5, no. 2, p. 179, 1979.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; R. Kerr and B. Booth, “Specific and varied practice of motor skill,” Percept. Mot. Skills, vol. 46, no. 2, pp. 395–401, 1978.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Spaced Repetition Systems  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  What are Spaced Repetition Systems and what is available?  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Spaced Repetition Systems</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 25 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> What are Spaced Repetition Systems and what is available?</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #spaced #repetition #system #spacing #effect ##learning #software  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Software Implementations</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>There are multiple algorithms available used for effectively implementing the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020163507-spacing-effect.md">spacing effect</a>. The earliest algorithm comes from the original discoverer of the spacing effect, Hermann Ebbinghaus. The algorithm <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05282020172154-replication-ebbinghaus.md">has been replicated</a> and scrutinized examined multiple times. &#91;1&#93;–&#91;3&#93; Spaced repetition systems are based around proper implementations of such algorithms.</p>
<p>Before the advent of computers, it was very difficult to implement such a system. The best system to take advantage of this effect was the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system.md">Leitner System which used paper note cards</a> to assist with remembering information. However, this was still a somewhat fragile system and difficult to manage.</p>
<p>With computers, there have been several pieces of software made to automate and keep track of repetitions <em>for a learner</em>. A majority of these systems directly adapted the Leitner System from the analog to the digital world. Each software generally has proprietary algorithms that supposedly maximize the spacing effect but are directly inspired by the original work done by Ebbinghaus.</p>
<p>Whether analog or digital, key features of these systems are as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Uses an algorithm implementation of the spacing effect for a user.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Each piece of information is spaced automatically per a user&#39;s perceived difficulty in either remembering or processing that piece of information on a repetition.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pieces of information are generally presented in a &quot;flashcard&quot; format and are stored in &quot;decks&quot;.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="software_implementations">Software Implementations</h3>
<p>There are many pieces of software that utilize spaced repetition. Provided is a table listing some of the most popular ones:</p>
<table><tr><th align="right">Software</th><th align="right">Description</th><th align="right">Reference</th></tr><tr><td align="right">Anki</td><td align="right">Open source flashcard based learning software.</td><td align="right">@AnkiPowerfulIntelligent</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Duolingo</td><td align="right">Popular language learning platform.</td><td align="right">@LearnLanguageFree</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Memrise</td><td align="right">Flashcard based language learning app.</td><td align="right">@zotero-1378</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Quizlet</td><td align="right">Multi-faceted learning platform.</td><td align="right">@Quizlet</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Supermemo</td><td align="right">Software for spacing and incremental reading.</td><td align="right">@LearnFastForget</td></tr></table>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Spaced Repetition Systems</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems">https://jacobzelko.com/05252020183020-spaced-repetition-systems</a>. May 25 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. M. J. Murre and J. Dros, “Replication and Analysis of Ebbinghaus’ Forgetting Curve,” PLoS ONE, vol. 10, no. 7, p. e0120644, Jul. 2015, doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0120644.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; H. Ebbinghaus, “Ueber das gedächtnis,” 1885.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; E. L. Bjork, R. A. Bjork, et al., “Making things hard on yourself, but in a good way: Creating desirable difficulties to enhance learning,” Psychol. Real World Essays Illus. Fundam. Contrib. Soc., vol. 2, no. 59–68, 2011.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Leitner System  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A brief overview of how the Leitner system works  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Leitner System</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> May 10 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> A brief overview of how the Leitner system works</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #learning #repetition #flashcards #spaced  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The Leitner system uses flashcards to implement a spaced repetition learning system. It was created by German science journalist Sebastian Leitner in the 1970s.</p>
<p><img src="1589148887796.png" alt="" /></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Successfully recalled cards are moved to the next group. Unsuccessfully recalled cards go back to the first box.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Using the Leitner system, learners create flashcards with discrete facts on them. These cards are grouped based on how well a learner knows the information on the card. They are arranged via the following method:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>If a card is successfully recalled, the card is put into the next group.</p>
</li>
<li><p>If a card is not successfully recalled it is sent to the first group.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The cards are kept in a box and are partitioned by spacings in the box. The size of each participation determined when cards were to be reviewed. For Leitner&#39;s implementation, this consisted of 1, 2, 5, 8, and 14cm partition sizes. Reviews only took place when a partition is filled to proper sizing.</p>
<p>In Leitner&#39;s original method, published in his book So lernt man Lerne &#40;How to learn to learn&#41;, the schedule of repetition was governed by the size of the partitions in the learning box.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Leitner System</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system">https://jacobzelko.com/05102020220941-leitner-system</a>. May 10 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>