<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Pure Functions in Programming  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11082021225843-pure-functions/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11082021225843-pure-functions/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An attempted overview on what is meant by pure functions  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Pure Functions in Programming</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 8 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An attempted overview on what is meant by pure functions</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #pure #functions #functional #programming  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>The definition of pure is somewhat of a moving target. Pure can mean many things and when applied to programming functions - even more so. Based on querying the <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://discourse.julialang.org/t/can-programming-in-julia-be-pure/71165">Julia community</a>, here was what I understood pure functions to be.</p>
<p>Based on Milewski&#39;s definition, &quot;A pure function is one in which the same result is always produced with no side effects given the same input.&quot; &#91;1&#93; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/https://github.com/CameronBieganek">Cameron Bieganek</a> explained how, in Julia specifically, you can write functions that are &quot;probably&quot; pure. However, there is no real guarantee that a function is actually pure, because it depends on the various methods that have been implemented. I like the notion of &quot;probably&quot; pure as it encapsulates a more pragmatic approach to the internals of a given language. It lets one get away without having to necessarily be completely aware of all the internals when discussing purity.</p>
<p>Finally, pure functions are different from mathematical functions for the reason that mathematical functions map a value to another value. Pure functions written in a programming language involve more than just a mapping. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; B. Milewski, Category Theory for Programmers, Version v1.3.0-0-g6bb0bc0. 2019.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Functional Programming  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/11032021180434-functional-programming/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/11032021180434-functional-programming/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on what functional programming is and the  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Functional Programming</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> November 3 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on what functional programming is and the</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #functional #programming #paradigm #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Paradigm</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="paradigm">Paradigm</h3>
<p>The approach of asking programming questions that functional programmers take is much more overarching. &#91;1&#93; Examples are:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>When designing an interactive program, they would ask: What is interaction?</p>
</li>
<li><p>When implementing Conway&#39;s Game of Life, they would ruminate on the meaning of life.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>To a functional programmer, the essence of programming, per Milewski, is to take big problems and decompose them into smaller problems. Then create small solutions that can then be composed together to solve the big problem. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; B. Milewski, Category Theory for Programmers, Version v1.3.0-0-g6bb0bc0. 2019.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Dynamic Functional Connectivity  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020003106-dynamic-functional-connectivity/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020003106-dynamic-functional-connectivity/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The brain exhibiting changes to functional activity over time.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Dynamic Functional Connectivity</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 27 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The brain exhibiting changes to functional activity over time.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #brain #dynamic #functional #connectivity #time #dfc #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Dynamic functional connectivity refers to functional connectivity changing over a short time.  The primary tool for analyzing DFC is <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12282020003750-functional-mri.md">fMRI</a>. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<p>DFC is related to a variety of different neurological disorders, and has been suggested to be a more accurate representation of functional brain networks.</p>
<p>Functional networks of the brain fluctuate on the scale of seconds to minutes. The changes are generally movements from one short term state to another, rather than continuous shifts. &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>There exist a few different types of stability in the kinds of brain analysis. &#91;3&#93; Here are a few with there associated descriptions:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Dynamic functional activity: shown a distinct hierarchical organization of the networks of the brain.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Bilaterally symmetric regions: most stable form of connectivity in the brain</p>
</li>
<li><p>Direct anatomical connection: similar to bilaterally symmetric regions.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Steady state functional connectivity: have less temporal stability than anatomical connections.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/11302020054836-sliding-window-analysis.md">Sliding window analysis</a> is most common for functional connectivity and was first introduced in 2009. &#91;4&#93; Sliding window analysis is performed on DFC data by conducting analysis on a set number of scans in an fMRI session. The number of scans is the length of the sliding window.  The defined window is then moved a certain number of scans forward in time and additional analysis is performed.  The movement of the window is usually referenced in terms of the degree of overlap between adjacent windows. Data from sliding window analysis generally must be compared between two different groups to prove accuracy.</p>
<p>THOUGHT: This is very similar to analysis with <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03272020064312-exponential-smoothing.md">exponential smoothing</a> or <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/04252020024813-median-filtering.md">&quot;salt-and-pepper&quot; filtering</a> and reminiscent of convolution filtering.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; Wikipedia contributors, “Dynamic Functional Connectivity — Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia,” 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; R. M. Hutchison et al., “Dynamic functional connectivity: Promise, issues, and interpretations,” Neuroimage, vol. 80, pp. 360–378, 2013.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; W. Majeed, M. Magnuson, and S. D. Keilholz, “Spatiotemporal dynamics of low frequency fluctuations in BOLD fMRI of the rat,” J. Magn. Reson. Imaging Off. J. Int. Soc. Magn. Reson. Med., vol. 30, no. 2, pp. 384–393, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; U. Sakoglu and V. Calhoun, “Dynamic windowing reveals task-modulation of functional connectivity in schizophrenia patients vs healthy controls,” in Proc. Intl. Soc. Mag. Reson. Med, 2009, vol. 17, p. 3675.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Functional Connectivity  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020004327-functional-connectivity/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/12282020004327-functional-connectivity/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Brain activity which occurs between spatially separated  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Functional Connectivity</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> December 27 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Brain activity which occurs between spatially separated</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #brain #activity #functional #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Functional connectivity refers to the functionally integrated relationship between spatially separated brain regions.  Functional connectivity is related to similar patterns of activation in different brain regions regardless of the apparent physical connectedness of the regions. &#91;1&#93;, &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>Functional connectivity is usually measured during resting state <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/12282020003750-functional-mri.md">fMRI</a>. &#91;3&#93; This is predicated on the assumption that functional connections in the brain remain constant in a short time over a task or period of data collection. Generally examined items based on temporal similarities during analysis of the brain are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Correlation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Coherence</p>
</li>
<li><p>Spatial grouping</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; B. Biswal, F. Z. Yetkin, V. M. Haughton, and J. S. Hyde, “Functional connectivity in the motor cortex of resting human brain using echo-planar MRI,” Magn Reson Med, vol. 34, no. 4, pp. 537–541, Oct. 1995, doi: 10.1002/mrm.1910340409.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; K. J. Friston, “Functional and effective connectivity: A review,” Brain Connect., vol. 1, no. 1, pp. 13–36, 2011.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; R. M. Hutchison et al., “Dynamic functional connectivity: Promise, issues, and interpretations,” Neuroimage, vol. 80, pp. 360–378, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>