<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Mobility Network Models of COVID-19 Explain Inequities and Inform Reopening  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01202021043643-mobility-network-models/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01202021043643-mobility-network-models/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How estimations of mobility patterns were used to estimate infections and identify disparities in Census Block Groups  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Mobility Network Models of COVID-19 Explain Inequities and Inform Reopening</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 19 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How estimations of mobility patterns were used to estimate infections and identify disparities in Census Block Groups</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #places #interest #policy #bipartite #graphs #counterfactual #mobility #models  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>S. Chang et al., &quot;Mobility network models of COVID-19 explain inequities and inform reopening,&quot; Nature, vol. 589, no. 7840, pp. 82–87, Jan. 2021, doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2923-3.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Points of Interest</li><li>Counterfactual Mobility Network</li><li>Limitations</li><li>Conclusions</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Iterative proportional fitting &#91;1&#93; was used to make POI –&gt; <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01202021043013-census-groups.md">CBG</a> networks from SafeGraph data. SafeGraph mobility data was validated against Google mobility data.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: What is iterative proportional fitting?</em></p>
<p>Model fits observed daily case counts from 8 March to 9 May 2020</p>
<h3 id="points_of_interest">Points of Interest</h3>
<p>POI hourly infection rate determined via:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Area</p>
</li>
<li><p>Median visit duration</p>
</li>
<li><p>Time-varying density of infectious individuals</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Three free time-invariant parameters that scale:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>POI transmission rates</p>
</li>
<li><p>CBG transmission rates</p>
</li>
<li><p>Initial amount of exposed individuals</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Points of interest for this paper are such as: </p>
<ol>
<li><p>Restaurants</p>
</li>
<li><p>Grocery stores</p>
</li>
<li><p>Religious establishments</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Certain categories of POIs contributed far more to infections like restaurants and hotels The model predicted time-dependent variation - likely due to policy change.</p>
<p>Model can identify at-risk populations and determined that disadvantaged racial socioeconomic groups face higher rates of infection.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: This conclusion seems very obvious – of course people are going to have to move and keep doing things.</em></p>
<h3 id="counterfactual_mobility_network">Counterfactual Mobility Network</h3>
<p>Counterfactual mobility network creation:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Scaling magnitude of mobility reduction down</p>
</li>
<li><p>Positioning the model at different times</p>
</li>
<li><p>Apply model to counterfactual networks to simulate infection trajectories.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: What is a counterfactual network? I wonder in what sense they are using the word &quot;counterfactual&quot;?</em></p>
<h3 id="limitations">Limitations</h3>
<p>Limitations of dataset:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Some populations missing</p>
</li>
<li><p>All POIs not ID&#39;d</p>
</li>
<li><p>Does not break up CBGs</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The model is sparse.  It does not include all real-world disease transmission variables.</p>
<h3 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<p>COVID-19 superspreader events &#91;2&#93;–&#91;5&#93; motivate risk modeling. Infection rates among different people groups &#91;6&#93;–&#91;12&#93; require modeling effects of the virus on disadvantaged groups.</p>
<p>The observed disparity was driven by a few POIs. Majority of infections from small fraction of superspreader POIs.</p>
<p>&quot;Probably because they cannot work from home as easily.&quot; &#91;10&#93;</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: It almost feels insulting that after this entire analysis, there is only one footnote on the topic of what people actually experience. On the flip side, I can empathize where a research group could lack time and/or means to contextualize results. Either way, it feels ripe to build on top of this work/paper to better examine the actual effects of policy adjustments and life changes.</em></p>
<p>CBGs with fewer white residents had higher predicted infection risks.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: Seems somewhat odd? This is interesting to me in how they keep bringing up race or economic status as a variable, but never fully commit to an investigation. Feels really weird to talk about issues without actually addressing them.</em></p>
<p>Mobility data showed average grocery store visits from lower-income CBGs had 59&#37; more hourly visitors per square foot. Median metro area data showed they stayed 17&#37; longer.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Mobility Network Models of COVID-19 Explain Inequities and Inform Reopening</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01202021043643-mobility-network-models">https://jacobzelko.com/01202021043643-mobility-network-models</a>. January 19 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; W. E. Deming and F. F. Stephan, “On a least squares adjustment of a sampled frequency table when the expected marginal totals are known,” Ann. Math. Stat., vol. 11, no. 4, pp. 427–444, 1940.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; Q. Bi et al., “Epidemiology and transmission of COVID-19 in 391 cases and 1286 of their close contacts in Shenzhen, China: A retrospective cohort study,” Lancet Infect. Dis., 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; S. Y. Park et al., “Early release-coronavirus disease outbreak in call center, south korea,” 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; D. Adam et al., “Clustering and superspreading potential of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 &#40;SARS-CoV-2&#41; infections in Hong Kong,” 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; A. Endo, S. Abbott, A. J. Kucharski, S. Funk, et al., “Estimating the overdispersion in COVID-19 transmission using outbreak sizes outside China,” Wellcome Open Res., vol. 5, no. 67, p. 67, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; M. Chowkwanyun and A. L. Reed Jr, “Racial health disparities and Covid-19—caution and context,” N. Engl. J. Med., 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; C. W. Yancy, “COVID-19 and african americans,” Jama, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; A. van Dorn, R. E. Cooney, and M. L. Sabin, “COVID-19 exacerbating inequalities in the US,” Lancet Lond. Engl., vol. 395, no. 10232, p. 1243, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;9&#93; M. Pareek et al., “Ethnicity and COVID-19: An urgent public health research priority,” The Lancet, vol. 395, no. 10234, pp. 1421–1422, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;10&#93; R. Reeves and J. Rothwell, “Class and COVID: How the less affluent face double risks,” Retrieved March, vol. 30, p. 2020, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;11&#93; S. Garg et al., “Hospitalization rates and characteristics of patients hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed coronavirus disease 2019—COVID-NET, 14 States, March 1–30, 2020,” Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep., vol. 69, no. 15, p. 458, 2020.</p>
<p>&#91;12&#93; C. Wilson, “These graphs show how COVID-19 is ravaging New York City’s low-income neighborhoods,” Time, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  The Book of Why  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021082043-book-of-why/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01072021082043-book-of-why/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How causality gives us tools to understand the question of cause-and-effect and confounders  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>The Book of Why</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 7 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How causality gives us tools to understand the question of cause-and-effect and confounders</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #causality #diagrams #counterfactual #statistics #graphs ##book ##blog #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. Pearl and D. Mackenzie, The book of why: the new science of cause and effect, First edition. New York: Basic Books, 2018.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Benefits of Causal Analysis</li><li>Critiques of Statistics</li><li>Causal Calculus</li><li>Inference Engine</li><li>Ladder of Causality</li><li>Mini-Turing Test</li><li>Bayesian Analysis</li><li>Causal Diagrams<ol><li>Paths in Path Diagrams<ol><li>Chain junction</li><li>Fork Junction</li><li>Collider Junction</li></ol></li><li>Lessons from Path Diagrams</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This book shows that data is stupid. Data can record events but cannot answer why any of the events are the way they are.</p>
<p>Causal inference posits the brain as the most advanced tool for understanding cause and effect.</p>
<p>Forcing an occurrence means to submit it to one influence to trigger the desired event</p>
<p><strong>Counterfactual:</strong> When scientific inquiry involves retrospective reflection. &quot;Why?&quot; is a counterfactual question.</p>
<p>Probabilities encode our beliefs about a static world. Causality explains probabilities in a changing world.</p>
<h3 id="benefits_of_causal_analysis">Benefits of Causal Analysis</h3>
<p>Create a smoother human-machine interface.</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: I wonder if that is what attracted me to the idea of Causal Inference - that it enables better human-machine interfaces. Like human-machine interaction as a discipline; I wonder if they have much in this area. Perhaps reach out to Valentine Wilson about the question?</em></p>
<h3 id="critiques_of_statistics">Critiques of Statistics</h3>
<p>Galton separated causation from statistics in 1889 causing the two separate fields to fully manifest.</p>
<p>&quot;Granger causality&quot; and &quot;vector autocorrelation&quot; exists to accommodate for causal explanations. Associated Thoughts: Judea&#39;s critique on probability-based causality</p>
<h3 id="causal_calculus">Causal Calculus</h3>
<p>Causal calculus uses two communications forms: </p>
<ol>
<li><p>Causal Diagrams: communicates what is known.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Symbolic language: defines what is wanted to be known</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="inference_engine">Inference Engine</h3>
<p>The inference engine assumes perfect and unlimited data for the given figure:</p>
<p><img src="assets/01082021030619-inference-engine.png" alt="" /></p>
<p><strong>Estimand:</strong> generalized mathematical formula to answer data questions. A statistical quantity estimated from data that can represent an answer to a query.</p>
<p>A given estimand is computed on the basis of the causal model alone, prior to an examination of the specifics of the data. This gives the inference engine better adaptibility.</p>
<p><strong>Binary Evaluation of Query:</strong> determines if a query can be answered under an existing causal model.</p>
<p><strong>Knowledge:</strong> experience from the past such as prior observations and education.</p>
<p><strong>Assumptions:</strong> explicit statements from available Knowledge.</p>
<p><strong>Queries:</strong> the scientific questions to be answered.</p>
<p><strong>Testable Implications:</strong> observable patterns or dependencies resulting from the listening pattern of a causal model.</p>
<p><strong>Estimate:</strong> Estimate for the answer is determined alongside uncertainty metrics.The metrics reflect limited data, measurement errors, or missing data.</p>
<h3 id="ladder_of_causality">Ladder of Causality</h3>
<p>First rung: observation. This concerns recognition of patterns. This rung asks, &quot;What if I see ...?&quot;</p>
<p>The second rung: Doing. Altering an environment to achieve a certain goal. This rung poses the questions of &quot;What if we do...?&quot; or &quot;How?&quot;</p>
<h3 id="mini-turing_test">Mini-Turing Test</h3>
<p>Mini-Turing Test: Encode a simple story on a machine and see if it can answer causal questions a human can answer.</p>
<p>Rules:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Limited only to causal reasoning and language.</p>
</li>
<li><p>The story can be encoded in the easiest way for the programmer.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="bayesian_analysis">Bayesian Analysis</h3>
<p>Simplified Bayesian analysis: prior belief &#43; new evidence &#61; revised belief.</p>
<p>Bayesian inference enables one to express personal experiences mathematically and combine it with data in a principled and transparent way.</p>
<h3 id="causal_diagrams">Causal Diagrams</h3>
<p>&quot;Causation&quot; via a causal diagram is straightforward. A variable X is a cause of Y if Y listens to X. Y&#39;s value is determined by what it hears.</p>
<h4 id="paths_in_path_diagrams">Paths in Path Diagrams</h4>
<h5 id="chain_junction">Chain junction</h5>
\[
A \rightarrow B \rightarrow C
\]
<p>B is the mediator which relays the effect of A to C. B filters information about A from C.</p>
<h5 id="fork_junction">Fork Junction</h5>
\[
A \leftarrow B \rightarrow C
\]
<p>B is a confounder of A and C. B makes A and C statistically correlated despite no direct link between them.</p>
<h5 id="collider_junction">Collider Junction</h5>
\[
A \rightarrow B \leftarrow C
\]
<p>Conditioning on B will make A and C dependent</p>
<h4 id="lessons_from_path_diagrams">Lessons from Path Diagrams</h4>
<ol>
<li><p>Causal analysis allows us to quantify real world processes</p>
</li>
<li><p>Path analysis draws conclusions about individual causal relationships by examining the diagram as a whole.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Two people creating differing causal diagrams for the same data and may not arrive at the same result.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>The Book of Why</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/01072021082043-book-of-why">https://jacobzelko.com/01072021082043-book-of-why</a>. January 7 2021.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="dark_dimmed"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>