<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Rest Is Best: The Role of Rest and Task Interruptions on Vigilance  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020172346-rest-best/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How resting during vigilance tasks can actually improve focus long-term  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Rest Is Best: The Role of Rest and Task Interruptions on Vigilance</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How resting during vigilance tasks can actually improve focus long-term</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #vigilance #rest  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>W. S. Helton and P. N. Russell, &quot;Rest is best: The role of rest and task interruptions on vigilance,&quot; Cognition, vol. 134, pp. 165–173, Jan. 2015, doi: 10.1016/j.cognition.2014.10.001.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Based on the results, taking rest is best for maintaining vigilance. A different perspective can proffer an explanation for this: </p>
<p>Differing tasks which interrupt one during a vigilance task may both utilize distinctly unique resources and require different amounts of resources. The tasks may have elicited different levels of cognitive load.</p>
<p>There exist on-going debate about the origins of vigilance decrement &#91;1&#93;. The best known is based on resource theory. However critics think it is a circular mode of reasoning &#91;2&#93;.</p>
<p>Current findings suggest that vigilance decrement comes from repeated use of executive resources. There may be domain specific interference when the primary task and activities during a break make use of the same resources.</p>
<p>The findings by Ariga do not support the idea that vigilance decrement is due to task under-load. &#91;3&#93; Knowing why resting can assist with refocusing is difficult. Perhaps, rest allowed participants to engage in day dreaming which eliminated task monotony. </p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; W. S. Helton and J. S. Warm, “Signal salience and the mindlessness theory of vigilance,” Acta Psychol. &#40;Amst.&#41;, vol. 129, no. 1, pp. 18–25, 2008.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; D. Navon, “Resources—A theoretical soup stone?” Psychol. Rev., vol. 91, no. 2, p. 216, 1984.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; P. A. Hancock, “In search of vigilance: The problem of iatrogenically created psychological phenomena.” Am. Psychol., vol. 68, no. 2, p. 97, 2013.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Brief And Rare Mental &#39;Breaks&#39; Keep You Focused: Deactivation And Reactivation Of Task Goals Preempt Vigilance Decrements  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06052020031214-brief-breaks/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06052020031214-brief-breaks/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How brief breaks can help you keep focused during long tasks  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Brief And Rare Mental &#39;Breaks&#39; Keep You Focused: Deactivation And Reactivation Of Task Goals Preempt Vigilance Decrements</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> June 5 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How brief breaks can help you keep focused during long tasks</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #breaks #vigilance #tasks #decrement #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>A. Ariga and A. Lleras, &quot;Brief and rare mental ‘breaks’ keep you focused: Deactivation and reactivation of task goals preempt vigilance decrements,&quot; Cognition, vol. 118, no. 3, pp. 439–443, Mar. 2011, doi: 10.1016/j.cognition.2010.12.007.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Study Methods</li><li>Concepts</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="study_methods">Study Methods</h3>
<p>84 students &#40;37 males, 47 female&#41; involved.</p>
<h3 id="concepts">Concepts</h3>
<p><strong>Mindlessness theory:</strong> vigilance decrement is due to gross inattention or mindlessness. During monotonous vigilance tasks, supervisory attentional systems lose their effectiveness and observers perform the task in a thoughtless manner. Essentially, zoning during a task such as driving a regular path to work or making a bed. &#91;1&#93;, &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>Vigilance tasks often show a negative sloping curve as a function of time. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Vigilance decrement does not concern depletion of attention resources. It is about a loss of control over our thoughts.</p>
<p>Heightened levels of vigilance can be maintained over prolonged periods of time with the use of infrequent, controlled breaks from a particular vigilance task. &#91;4&#93;</p>
<p>Ariga proposes that with respect to cognitive control, vigilance decrement may have difficulties due to goal habituation. Ariga argues thatgoals which draw on cognitive faculties should show effects similar to habituation.</p>
<p>Arriga argues that vigilance decrements ought be observed for any task that is performed continuously if goal habituation happens.  It should not depend necessarily on the extent to which the task can be routinized</p>
<p><strong>Task-Unrelated-Thoughts:</strong> when we subconsciously disengage from a task and start thinking about other related subjects</p>
<p>How Ariga believes vigilance decrement should be viewed. Cognitive control is also known as executive control. &#91;5&#93;, &#91;6&#93; Ariga&#39;s posits vigilance decrement is a failure of cognitive control. This is in contrast to the current thought that vigilance decrement is the inability to recover resources needed for retention as a function of time.</p>
<p>The defintion of habituation </p>
<p><strong>Habituation effect:</strong> the gradual diminishing of representation to sustained stimulation. Can occur even when being actively involved in tasks that require cognitive effort &#91;7&#93;, &#91;8&#93; and in tasks regarding meaning &#91;9&#93; This links back to how Ariga views vigilance decrement.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; T. Manly, I. H. Robertson, M. Galloway, and K. Hawkins, “The absent mind:: Further investigations of sustained attention to response,” Neuropsychologia, vol. 37, no. 6, pp. 661–670, 1999.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; I. H. Robertson, T. Manly, J. Andrade, B. T. Baddeley, and J. Yiend, “Oops&#33;’: Performance correlates of everyday attentional failures in traumatic brain injured and normal subjects,” Neuropsychologia, vol. 35, no. 6, pp. 747–758, 1997.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; D. R. Davies and R. Parasuraman, The psychology of vigilance. Academic Pr, 1982.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; P. A. Bourke and J. Duncan, “Effect of template complexity on visual search and dual-task performance,” Psychol. Sci., vol. 16, no. 3, pp. 208–213, 2005.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; E. K. Miller and J. D. Cohen, “An integrative theory of prefrontal cortex function,” Annu. Rev. Neurosci., vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 167–202, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; M. I. Posner, C. R. Snyder, and R. Solso, “Attention and cognitive control,” Cogn. Psychol. Key Read., vol. 205, 2004.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; Y. S. Bonneh, A. Cooperman, and D. Sagi, “Motion-induced blindness in normal observers,” Nature, vol. 411, no. 6839, pp. 798–801, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; D. Troxler, “On the disappearance of given objects from our visual field,” Ophthalmol. Bibl., vol. 2, pp. 1–53, 1804.</p>
<p>&#91;9&#93; W. E. Lambert and L. A. Jakobovits, “Verbal satiation and changes in the intensity of meaning.” J. Exp. Psychol., vol. 60, no. 6, p. 376, 1960.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>