<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/10092021131742-advantaged-to-disadvantaged/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Advantage to Disadvantage - Working Thoughts</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> October 9 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on my current thinking about equity and those who</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> #advantage #disadvantage #equity ##thought #race #class #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</li><li>The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</li><li>An Emerging Tension</li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This concerns my evolving thoughts concerning those who move from a state of historical advantage to one of disadvantage. The language of advantage to disadvantage comes from a Dr. Sylvie &#91;XXX&#93; who described this notion first at the &#91;2021 NAHDO Conference&#93;. &lt;&#33;–Find Dr. Sylvie&#39;s last name–&gt;</p>
<h3 id="thoughts_on_the_emerging_disadvantaged_trends_in_us_caucasian_populations">Thoughts on the Emerging Disadvantaged Trends in US Caucasian Populations</h3>
<p>Of particular note, there has been the emergence of a sub-class of persons in the United States amongst the low-income communities. Unlike historically marginalized people groups, such as African Americans, Asian American and Pacific Islanders, or Latin Americans, this particular sub-class exists at the intersection of traditional disadvantage and historical advantage: Caucasian. How can a class of such long-standing advantage find itself disadvantaged is the very question I have been thinking about.</p>
<h3 id="the_intersections_of_advantaged_and_disadvantaged">The Intersections of Advantaged and Disadvantaged</h3>
<p>I recall from a talk from the MIT Health Equity Conference that a Dr. &#91;XXX&#93; said the phrase, &quot;Race is not monolithic.&quot; &lt;&#33;–Find reference to MIT talk and Dr&#39;s name–&gt; That statement I think could also be extended to class structure as the aphorism, &quot;Class is not monolithic.&quot; In popular discussion, the conversation about disadvantaged populations generally have focused particularly at the intersection of disadvantage-disadvantage with respect to race and class. Yet, the intersection of advantage-disadvantage produces an uncomfortable problem: how should we handle these populations?</p>
<p>This intersectional breakdown could be summarized loosely as follows:</p>
<table><tr><th align="right">Type</th><th align="right">Race</th><th align="right">Class</th><th align="right">Examples</th></tr><tr><td align="right">Historically advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Victorian aristocracy, robber barons</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Emerging advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Textile traders, public servants</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Transitional disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Advantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Coal miners, share croppers</td></tr><tr><td align="right">Apparent disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Disadvantaged</td><td align="right">Slaves, serfs</td></tr></table>
<h3 id="an_emerging_tension">An Emerging Tension</h3>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Race  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01202021041928-what-is-race/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01202021041928-what-is-race/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Overviews on what race is as a concept  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Race</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 19 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Overviews on what race is as a concept</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #race #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p><strong>Race:</strong> organizing inequalities across economic, environmental, social and political domains of human interactions &#91;1&#93;–&#91;3&#93;</p>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: I am somewhat confused by this definition of race. Perhaps ask someone for further explanation on the matter.</em></p>
<p><strong>Whiteness:</strong> power, privilege and identity organized along white racialized ideologies and practices. &#91;3&#93;, &#91;4&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; J. Acker, “Inequality regimes: Gender, class, and race in organizations,” Gend. Soc., vol. 20, no. 4, pp. 441–464, 2006.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; A. Sriprakash and S. Walker, “Questions of Race in Education and Development,” presented at the Questions of Race in Education and Development Workshop, 2018.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; G. Marchais, P. Bazuzi, and A. Amani Lameke, “‘The data is gold, and we are the gold-diggers’: Whiteness, race and contemporary academic research in eastern DRC,” Critical African Studies, vol. 12, no. 3, pp. 372–394, Sep. 2020, doi: 10.1080/21681392.2020.1724806.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; D. van Zyl-Hermann and J. Boersema, “Introduction: The politics of whiteness in Africa,” Africa, vol. 87, no. 4, pp. 651–661, 2017.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  ‘The Data Is Gold, And We Are The gold-diggers&#39;: Whiteness, Race And Contemporary Academic Research In Eastern DRC  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/01132021041501-gold-diggers/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/01132021041501-gold-diggers/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  How data mining in African countries is a type of neocolonialism  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>‘The Data Is Gold, And We Are The gold-diggers&#39;: Whiteness, Race And Contemporary Academic Research In Eastern DRC</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> January 12 2021</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> How data mining in African countries is a type of neocolonialism</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #race #whiteness #africa #data #gold  #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>G. Marchais, P. Bazuzi, and A. Amani Lameke, &quot;‘The Data Is Gold, And We Are The gold-diggers&#39;: Whiteness, Race And Contemporary Academic Research In Eastern DRC,&quot; Critical African Studies, vol. 12, no. 3, pp. 372–394, Sep. 2020, doi: 10.1080/21681392.2020.1724806.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Background<ol><li>Review Process</li><li>Research Projects Are a Lucrative Business</li><li>Accidental Whiteness</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>References</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<h4 id="review_process">Review Process</h4>
<p>First stage, a white European male&#39;s reflection on academic research in DRC and setting up Marakuja Kive Research group.  Second stage, two Congolese researchers and Marakuja Kive Research founders review ideas in initial draft.</p>
<p>Retreating to safety founded on racial inequality creates a resource for researchers to access - consciously or not. This is often hard to identify due to delicacy of research endeavors. In Africa, is race colonial legacy or a resource for projects actively relied on, or both?</p>
<h4 id="research_projects_are_a_lucrative_business">Research Projects Are a Lucrative Business</h4>
<p>International research projects are beginning to much more resemble supply chains &#91;1&#93;</p>
<p>Increased demands for data in research enabled businesses based on multi-actor business models and knowledge value chains to exist &#91;2&#93; Quantitative research is closer to the big data sector. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Three main groups of people enable the collection of data. </p>
<ol>
<li><p>Western, generally white researchers control project resources; namely funding.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Non-Western associates: their work is usually hidden from outputs &#91;4&#93;, &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Subjects who are generally from lower socio-economic positioning.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><em>THOUGHTS: Point 1 reminds me of the Communist Manifesto by Marx on those that control the means of production.</em></p>
<p>Data derives its value from its rawness at extraction and via processing.  International academic pipeline construction is analogous to generic resource mining: </p>
<ol>
<li><p>African data is collected</p>
</li>
<li><p>Exported</p>
</li>
<li><p>Processed</p>
</li>
<li><p>Converted to high value goods &#40;papers, reports, etc.&#41;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>This mirrors very closely how international academic endeavors can look like a supply chain.</p>
<h4 id="accidental_whiteness">Accidental Whiteness</h4>
<p>White academics incidentally separate to give themselves a sense of racial inapplicability &#91;6&#93;, &#91;7&#93;</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="references__2">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; D. Desai and R. Tapscott, “Tomayto tomahto: The research supply chain and the ethics of knowledge production,” Humanity J. Online, 2004.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; F. Bédécarrats, I. Guérin, and F. Roubaud, “All that glitters is not gold. The political economy of randomized evaluations in development,” Dev. Change, vol. 50, no. 3, pp. 735–762, 2019.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; L. Mann, “Left to other peoples’ devices? A political economy perspective on the big data revolution in development,” Dev. Change, vol. 49, no. 1, pp. 3–36, 2018.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; T. Middleton and E. Pradhan, “Dynamic duos: On partnership and the possibilities of postcolonial ethnography,” Ethnography, vol. 15, no. 3, pp. 355–374, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; S. A. Jenkins, “Assistants, guides, collaborators, friends: The concealed figures of conflict research,” J. Contemp. Ethnogr., vol. 47, no. 2, pp. 143–170, 2018.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; S. Sullivan, Revealing whiteness: The unconscious habits of racial privilege. Indiana University Press, 2006.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; C. Mills, “White ignorance,” Race Epistemol. Ignorance, vol. 247, pp. 26–31, 2007.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
    data-repo="TheCedarPrince/thecedarprince.github.io"
    data-repo-id="R_kgDOHRFrHA"
    data-category="General"
    data-category-id="DIC_kwDOHRFrHM4CPGIX"
    data-mapping="url"
    data-reactions-enabled="1"
    data-emit-metadata="0"
    data-input-position="top"
    data-theme="preferred_color_scheme"
    data-lang="en"
    data-loading="lazy"
    crossorigin="anonymous"
    async>
</script>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>