<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  the cedar ledge  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jacobzelko.com </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob S. Zelko&#39;s personal website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jacobzelko.com/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Direct Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Direct Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 12 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of direct self harm and how it differs from other types of self-harming behaviors</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #direct #self #harm ##mentalhealth #illness #mental #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Direct self-harm is defined as the deliberate, direct destruction or alteration of body tissue without conscious suicidal intent, but resulting in injury severe enough for tissue damage to occur &#91;1&#93;. </p>
<p>Examples are of Direct Self Harm are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Cutting, burning, scratching, and hitting of oneself &#91;2&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Skin bleaching &#91;3&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hair-pulling &#91;4&#93;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ingesting hazardous chemicals &#91;5&#93;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The term &quot;direct self-harm&quot; is often used interchangeably with the terms self-injury &#91;6&#93;, self-mutilation &#91;7&#93;, and self-wounding &#91;8&#93;. Despite the exact wording, the distinction of direct self-harm is that it is non-suicidal but does cause direct injury to the body.</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Direct Self-Harm</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm">https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm</a>. July 12 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; A. R. Favazza, “The coming of age of self-mutilation,” J. Nerv. Ment. Dis., vol. 186, no. 5, pp. 259–268, 1998.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; B. Møhl, P. La Cour, and A. Skandsen, “Non-suicidal self-injury and indirect self-harm among Danish high school students,” Scand. J. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry Psychol., vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 11–18, 2014.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; C. A. Charles, “Skin bleaching, self-hate, and black identity in Jamaica,” J. Black Stud., vol. 33, no. 6, pp. 711–728, 2003.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; B. A. Iwata, M. F. Dorsey, K. J. Slifer, K. E. Bauman, and G. S. Richman, “Toward a functional analysis of self-injury,” J. Appl. Behav. Anal., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 197–209, 1994.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; K. L. Gratz, “Measurement of deliberate self-harm: Preliminary data on the Deliberate Self-Harm Inventory,” J. Psychopathol. Behav. Assess., vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 253–263, 2001.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; E. D. Klonsky, “The functions of deliberate self-injury: A review of the evidence,” Clin. Psychol. Rev., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 226–239, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; A. R. Favazza and R. J. Rosenthal, “Diagnostic issues in self-mutilation,” Psychiatr. Serv., vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 134–140, 1993.</p>
<p>&#91;8&#93; D. Tantam and J. Whittaker, “Personality disorder and self-wounding,” Br. J. Psychiatry, vol. 161, no. 4, pp. 451–464, 1992.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Loose hypothesis on worsening of cytokine regulation via ASD and COVID19  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 10 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Loose hypothesis on worsening of cytokine regulation via ASD and COVID19</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #asd #autism ##hypothesis #health #mentalhealth #cytokine ##pandemic #covid19 #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Be careful about conflating correlation with causation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have been closely examining the Hypothalamus Pituitary &#40;HPA&#41; axis and have seen how cytokines directly interact with it. &#91;1&#93; Therefore, since ASD has been correlated with cytokine dysregulation &#91;2&#93;, it can be reasonable to suspect that as coronavirae can also impact cytokine regulation &#91;3&#93;, ASD is a risk factor for COVID19 causing direct problems with the HPA axis leading to multiple downstream issues.</p>
<p>ASD has been correlated with abnormal immune function. This includes:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Cytokine dysregulation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Inflammation</p>
</li>
<li><p>Presence of autoantibodies</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Studies show the presence of anti-brain immunoglobulins in ASD patients. &#91;4&#93; ASD status could also be directly correlated with patients’ cytokine and chemokine levels which cause organ inflammation &#91;2&#93;</p>
<p>There is a second phase resulting in a cytokine storm which particularly affects respiratory epithelium &#91;5&#93;. The storm activates cytokines IL-1-beta, IL-6 and TNFalfa. These activations aggravate respiratory symptoms. These cytokines cause damage to pulmonary microvasculature. It simultaneously affects apoptosis and chemotaxis resulting in decreases of epithelial barriers and alveolar edema <em>Back up references about cytokines</em></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Hypothesis on Cytokine Dysregulation Worsened by COVID19 for People with ASD</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19">https://jacobzelko.com/07102020174816-cytokine-asd-covid19</a>. July 10 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; M. Marmot and R. Wilkinson, Social Determinants of Health, 2nd ed. Oxford University Press, 2006.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; A. M. Depino, “Peripheral and central inflammation in autism spectrum disorders,” Mol. Cell. Neurosci., vol. 53, pp. 69–76, 2013.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; S. N. J. Korsman, G. U. van Zyl, L. Nutt, M. I. Andersson, and W. Preiser, “Human coronaviruses,” in Virology, Elsevier, 2012, pp. 94–95.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; A. Meltzer and J. Van de Water, “The role of the immune system in autism spectrum disorder,” Neuropsychopharmacology, vol. 42, no. 1, pp. 284–298, 2017.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; Q. Ye, B. Wang, and J. Mao, “Cytokine storm in COVID-19 and treatment,” J. Infect., 2020.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What is Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Exploration of the idea of Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What is Digital Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Exploration of the idea of Digital Self-Harm</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #harm #digital #non-suicidal #self #mentalhealth #illness #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>Digital Self Harm is any online communication and activity that leads to, supports, or exacerbates non-suicidal yet intentional harm or impairment of an individual’s physical wellbeing. It includes consuming and generating online content. Digital self-harm occurs when a person’s behaviors are negatively influenced through his or her online activities in such a manner that these online activities lead to the infliction of non-suicidal direct or indirect physical harm to oneself. </p>
<p>Digital self-harm is believed to be growing at a rate that will not stop without check. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What is Digital Self-Harm</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm">https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm</a>. July 8 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Defining Digital Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview on what is digital self harm  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Defining Digital Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview on what is digital self harm</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##bibliography #self #harm #online #digital #suicide #mentalhealth #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>J. Pater and E. Mynatt, &quot;Defining Digital Self-Harm,&quot; in Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing, Portland Oregon USA, Feb. 2017, pp. 1501–1513, doi: 10.1145/2998181.2998224.</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li><ol><li>Examples of Digital Self-Harm</li><li>Problems with the Internet</li></ol></li><li>How To Cite</li><li>References:</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>This paper aims to define what digital self-harm is.</p>
<p>Digital self harm: online communication and activity that leads to, supports, or exacerbates non-suicidal yet intentional harm or impairment of an individual’s physical wellbeing.  It includes consuming and generating online content.  Digital self-harm occurs when a person’s behaviors are negatively influenced through his or her online activities in such a manner that these online activities lead to the infliction of non-suicidal direct or indirect physical harm to oneself. </p>
<p>Traditionally, eating disorder treatments generally include individual and family therapy or group therapy. Interpersonal and cultural forces that sustain self-harm activities are scrutinized.</p>
<p>As a field, CSCW and HCI health research appears to unconsciously emphasize the positive health benefits of technology &#91;1&#93;–&#91;3&#93;.  This unaddressed bias can have great consequences on platform design and policy and must be scrutinized.</p>
<p>Digital self-harm is believed to be growing at a rate that will not stop without check. &#91;4&#93;</p>
<h3 id="examples_of_digital_self-harm">Examples of Digital Self-Harm</h3>
<p>Pro-anorexic digital self-harm example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>IF YOU WANT TO LOSE WEIGHT, GO ON A DIET FATTY.  ONE IS EITHER ANA/MIA OR NOT. IT IS A GIFT AND YOU CANNOT DECIDE TO HAVE AN EATING DISORDER. SO IF YOU ARE LOOKING FOR A WAY TO LOSE WEIGHT, S-S-S-S-SORRY JUNIOR&#33;&#33; MOVE ON, TRY JENNY CRAIG</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Two different ways the language around cutting is used:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Normalizing behavior: attempts in legitimizing activities to deal with mental health issues</p>
</li>
<li><p>Pathologizing behavior: focuses on a bodily disgust with the behavior being wrong morally.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="problems_with_the_internet">Problems with the Internet</h3>
<p>The internet creates an environment for reinforced strengthening of behavioral issues within an affected individual through encouragement of destructive behaviors. This sort of cybernetic reinforcement mechanism could lead to the fast and serious manifestations of underlying disease symptoms.</p>
<p>ED websites may have contagion-like effects on individuals investigating eating disorders prior to exhibiting any commitment to a disorder. &#91;5&#93; Regarding adolescents, a concern is a healthy desire for weight-loss could lead to unintended exposure of ED content.</p>
<p><em>QUESTION: I wonder if there is a corollary definition about unintentional digital self-harm? People who are not necessarily interested in self-harm, but come into it anyways.</em></p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Defining Digital Self-Harm</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm">https://jacobzelko.com/06202020205907-digital-harm</a>. July 8 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References:</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; M. De Choudhury, M. R. Morris, and R. W. White, “Seeking and sharing health information online: Comparing search engines and social media,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 1365–1376.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; J. Huh and W. Pratt, “Weaving clinical expertise in online health communities,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 1355–1364.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. L. Jacobs, J. Clawson, and E. D. Mynatt, “My journey compass: A preliminary investigation of a mobile tool for cancer patients,” in Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems, 2014, pp. 663–672.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; D. L. Borzekowski, S. Schenk, J. L. Wilson, and R. Peebles, “E-Ana and e-Mia: A content analysis of pro–eating disorder web sites,” Am. J. Public Health, vol. 100, no. 8, pp. 1526–1534, 2010.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What Is Self-Harm  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>What Is Self-Harm</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> July 8 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##zettel #harm #self #suicide #mentalhealth #illness #hurting #pain ##summary #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<p>In 2014, WHO found that 20&#37; of children aged 15 confirmed having self-harmed within the last year. &#91;1&#93;</p>
<p>Self-harm is a mental illness that results in causing pain or harm to oneself. &#91;2&#93; Examples include restrictive and binge eating, cutting, hitting, scratching, burning, bleaching of an individual’s body, and other forms of self-mutilation. &#91;3&#93;</p>
<p>Self-harm generally pertains to non-life threatening actions individuals perform to negatively impact their health. This starts with actions like cutting and wrist slashing. &#91;4&#93; It can then lead to more severe acts of injuring human body tissue &#91;5&#93; and to <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm">indirect self-harming behavior</a> such as eating disorders &#91;6&#93;</p>
<p>There are many types of self-harming behavior such as:</p>
<ol>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020174529-indirect-self-harm">Indirect Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020185239-direct-self-harm">Direct Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020155623-digital-self-harm">Digital Self-Harm</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Further complicating discrete categories is that not all people that self-harm are <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07122020192840-suicide">suicidal</a>. &#91;7&#93;</p>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>What Is Self-Harm</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm">https://jacobzelko.com/07082020161946-self-harm</a>. July 8 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>&#91;1&#93; C. Currie et al., “Social determinants of health and well-being among young people,” Health Behav. Sch.-Aged Child. HBSC Study Int. Rep. From, vol. 2010, p. 271, 2009.</p>
<p>&#91;2&#93; E. D. Klonsky, “The functions of deliberate self-injury: A review of the evidence,” Clin. Psychol. Rev., vol. 27, no. 2, pp. 226–239, 2007.</p>
<p>&#91;3&#93; M. K. Nock, “Self-injury,” Annu. Rev. Clin. Psychol., vol. 6, pp. 339–363, 2010.</p>
<p>&#91;4&#93; H. Graff and R. Mallin, “The syndrome of the wrist cutter,” Am. J. Psychiatry, vol. 124, no. 1, pp. 36–42, 1967.</p>
<p>&#91;5&#93; E. D. Klonsky, T. F. Oltmanns, and E. Turkheimer, “Deliberate self-harm in a nonclinical population: Prevalence and psychological correlates,” Am. J. Psychiatry, vol. 160, no. 8, pp. 1501–1508, 2003.</p>
<p>&#91;6&#93; C. Zlotnick, J. I. Mattia, and M. Zimmerman, “Clinical correlates of self-mutilation in a sample of general psychiatric patients,” J. Nerv. Ment. Dis., vol. 187, no. 5, pp. 296–301, 1999.</p>
<p>&#91;7&#93; J. Quigley, S. Rasmussen, and J. Mcalaney, “Normative misperceptions of suicidal and self-harming behaviours in an undergraduate student population,” 2014.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Bullet Journal  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jacobzelko.com/03192020013253-bullet-journal/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jacobzelko.com/03192020013253-bullet-journal/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  An overview of how to use a bullet journal and how to make one.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1>Bullet Journal</h1>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> March 19 2020</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> An overview of how to use a bullet journal and how to make one.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> ##summary ##bulletjournal #productivity #model #writing #journaling #reflection #projectmanagement #mentalhealth #creativity #archive</p>
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<p>Not Available</p>
<h1>Table of Contents</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>How To Cite</li><li>References</li><li>Discussion: </li></ol></div>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020013347-bullet-journal-month">Monthly Planning in a Bullet Journal</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** How to create a monthly plan when using a bullet journal.</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020035337-bullet-journal-weekly">Weekly Planning in a Bullet Journal</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** How to create a weekly plan when using a bullet journal.</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020035441-bullet-journal-daily">Daily Planning in a Bullet Journal</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-julia">- **Summary:** How to create a daily plan when using a bullet journal.</code></pre>
<h2 id="how_to_cite">How To Cite</h2>
<p>Zelko, Jacob. <em>Bullet Journal</em>. <a href="https://jacobzelko.com/03192020013253-bullet-journal">https://jacobzelko.com/03192020013253-bullet-journal</a>. March 19 2020.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion: </h2>
<script>talkyardServerUrl='https://site-vbm8wbc57o.talkyard.net';</script>
<script async defer src="https://c1.ty-cdn.net/-/talkyard-comments.min.js"></script>
<div class="talkyard-comments" data-discussion-id="" style="margin-top: 45px;">
    <noscript>Please enable Javascript to view comments.</noscript>
    <p style="margin-top: 25px; opacity: 0.9; font-size: 96%">Comments powered by
    <a href="https://www.talkyard.io">Talkyard</a>.</p>
</div> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Zelko</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>